Chapter 4: Strangers on a Train

Draco strolled onto Platform 9 and three-quarters while adjusting the robes he'd just put on over his charcoal suit with a quiet purple tie and silver cufflinks. Before crossing he'd attracted minimal attention. On a normal day he'd stand out, but the steady trickle of wizards and witches made Draco a safe eccentric. Just a rich brat, not some delusional redheaded homeless clan who wore blankets and pushed a shopping cart loaded with birds. Commuters glanced past Draco and stared at the freaks. They might remember him and look back, but they never could spot him. An accountant offered investment services, Draco nodded dismissively and walked past him. One middle-aged woman stage-whispered "Why can't Andrew dress that well?" Draco silently agreed with her after glancing at Andrew. Muggle style existed, he was proof. Draco had no idea why most choose to ignore it.

Draco got some glances. Mother attracted no attention, a shocking accomplishment given her beauty. Draco had sold the elegant black dress, Narcissa's concession to Muggle fashion, by pointing out that wearing robes stood out and invited a conversation. Mother's dread of interaction defeated her rejection of her Muggle past. Draco feared she'd change back to robes once he departed, Muggle curiosity be damned. Then he'd see exactly how much leverage he had with Li.

As Draco crossed the threshold to Platform Nine and Three Quarters memories of last year washed over him. It felt like ages ago. Last year he'd gawked nervously at the sights and experience, until Father coughed slightly, reminding Draco his place. Now he glanced around the station. Pansy Parkinson sat in one car of the train, staring down at the platform through a window. Gregory stood next to the news-stand, beside Vincent, carefully counting out Knuts to the vendor, candy in hand. Gregory waved to Draco and said something to Vincent. Draco shook his head and motioned towards the train.

He'd meet them later. He had to get out of the suit and adjust his robes.

An oomph behind him and Draco's trunk bumped into his leg before backing away to a fight for position against the interloper. He saw Neville rubbing his shin and Draco realized he'd stopped right at the entrance. Thankfully nobody had bolted through full tilt, as nervous first years sometimes did.

"My fault, Neville." Draco moved away, trunk padding quietly after him. Draco nodded to Augusta Longbottom as she appeared at the entrance. He realized - amused - that her purple flowing dress and wide brimmed hat sporting yellow roses looked equally outlandish on either side of the crossing, too improbable to be accidental.

Prefects from three Houses helped stow first years' trunks, older girls screamed greetings and ran into hugs. Shyer students boarded the Hogwarts Express quickly, loud students mingled on the platform gossiping. A large clock showed 10:45. A new girl, hair almost as blonde as Draco's but shoulder-length, examined the train's steam through outlandishly large orange glasses. With rainbow lenses. Judging from her expression she'd invented some secret of the universe, hidden in the cloud. Cho Chang's hands demonstrated maneuvers she'd seen at Puddlemere United's latest match to the rest of the Ravenclaw team. Lavender Brown and Hannah Abbott stood comparing modified uniforms and giggling. Draco took this all in a quick glance.

Dozens of students, but not Harry. No Hermione, either.

"I'll go. I don't want to embarrass you, Draco." Draco turned around and hugged Narcissa tightly.

"I'll have time to be embarrassed later, Mother," he said, eyes closed, and held the hug. Draco didn't want to see people watching. He might blush. He wasn't embarrassed, not yet, but if he thought about it that could change. He released Mother and stepped back. "I'll see you at Christmas," he said in a normal tone. Tears rolled down her cheeks and Draco wondered if he saw Mother, or if his own mask had been as effective.

Ignoring several slack-jawed stares, Draco boarded the Hogwarts Express behind sixth year Gryffindors, following smoothly in their wake as they scattered younger students. He stopped in the lavatory to fix his attire, and then went to the car he'd seen Vincent board.

"Vincent. Gregory" he said, standing at the entrance. "Hi. Can I come in? I'll leave. If you want."

Vincent let out his breath. "Come in. Greg and I talked about it. I mean, we're all in the same boat. Dad said you'd have secrets, even from us. He told me once most of the time that meant you were either protecting us, or afraid. Of losing us."

Gregory said "Maybe it was a mistake, trusting Lucius advice. My dad worried, time to time, especially when they decided to throw in with You-Know-Who. They understood the risks. Who could have seen that coming? They were close, our parents. Maybe we saw that more than you did Draco. We spent every Boxing Day together. But you weren't invited until last year."

Draco closed the door behind him. "So … we're on again for Boxing Day?"

"Christmas with Family. Friends for Boxing Day. That's what we do."

Draco couldn't express the profound relief he felt. He'd confessed almost everything in his letter. Revealing plots, even his Patronus, felt easy, even cleansing. More difficult was admitting rage at Father, at Father's mistakes, at the emptiness between him and Mother. It felt like opening a wound and handing out salt. Gregory and Vince had reasons to hate Lucius Malfoy and Draco. He'd feared giving out more, showing weakness about his inner conflicts.

It seemed he still had friends, which meant Draco must complete his confession.

"I know it's been hard, even before Voldemort"- they didn't flinch - "killed our Fathers. I know you disapproved last year my helping Granger, or suspected some deep plan. But it was just like it appeared."

"Why?" asked Crabbe.

"Why not? At first I was polite because Potter expected it. Useful. And where is it written we have to be jerks, even to Muggles? Random rudeness makes us all look terrible. I was … I'm still trying to save our House. And I realized, hating Muggles it's not just wrong, it's a sign of weakness, even if it's politically useful."

Draco sighed. "Yet another time Father was wrong. Even last summer at my house, I feared admitting the truth to you after it drove a wedge between me and mother. "

Vincent frowned, and Draco saw them exchange glances as he sat down heavily.

"If she lived with Muggles for a decade and still hates them, doesn't that mean there's something to it," asked Gregory.

"Mother hates them because her life was on hold. She blames them, that's easier than blaming Father. Or maybe herself. I spent a lot of the summer investigating. At first I was trying to find a reason to hate them. And there are reasons, but no different from why I'd hate anybody."

"And this hatred is one reason Slytherin is dying. At some point I'm going to reveal this, to challenge the others' beliefs. If Father were around, I could convince him and it would just be a matter of time, but without him, I might become a pariah."

Vincent and Gregory waited, and Draco made his final confession.

"I could lose. Even winning will cost me friends and support.. 'The boy who tried to have it both ways, who hated Muggles when Voldemort lived and championed them after he fell.' I don't want to drag you down with me. Our arrangement was made by our Fathers."

"And they're gone," said Gregory, "but you know we had a choice."

"Why would I want out now?" said Vince. "Voldemort murdered our families and everyone thinks we're the bad guys?"

"Our fathers bowed to him," said Gregory sharply. "Of course they think we're the bad guys."

"Voldemort championed hatred. Obviously we'd reconsider once he killed everyone. A backlash, starting by victims. In any case I didn't care one way or another. I'm not sure father did. Even if he did really hate them, that wasn't us. We didn't join as Death Eaters," said Vince.

"We might have," said Draco softly. "If he hadn't killed everyone. If he'd returned quietly and kept hidden. It would have been tough not to."

"Yeah, maybe." Vincent bit his lower lip. "Voldemort made it easy to hate him."

"I don't know," said Gregory. "I hate him,too, but I don't know if this will work. Maybe. As long as you don't reveal you were pro-Muggle last year"

"Don't decide now. We can keep being friends without being allies."

Vincent gazed at the ceiling as the train's piercing whistle hurried stragglers on board . "Our year is fine, mostly. Nott and Potter are close, the witches are neutralish, but listen to Hermione, Zabini doesn't like you..."

Gregory said "That's envy. He feels overshadowed."

"He can join the club" said Draco, more bitterly than intended. "Potter and Granger in the same year? In any case he can be General this year, that will cool him off." Draco saw their look. "Potter and Granger resigned. So there's no upside for me as General. If I beat up on rookies everyone shrugs, because I've had a year's experience. And if I don't. Well. Anyway Greengrass is in, too."

Gregory interrupted "How are they deciding replacements?"

"Depends. Some classes are keeping the same generals. It's still up in the air for our year, but Longbottom gets it if he wants. The class gets some say but the Professors do, too. "

"Professors?" they both said. Gregory continued without pause "So, it's a committee thing?"

"Yeah," said Draco with a smile.

Gregory ignored the bait, tacked back to the earlier conversation. "I worry about the older students. Thoughts?"

Draco leaned forward conspiratorially. "I can't tell about the Jugsons. The Carrows lost both parents and hated me to begin with. They'll view this as a personal insult."

"They weren't stable anyway." said Vince. "Most upperclassmen want to bully someone. They'd prefer to pick on Gryffindorks but don't care much" The train lurched once and the platform appeared to be rolling back. Draco saw Harry Potter hurriedly walk by and wondered if he'd just boarded, but snapped his attention back to Vince who was saying "Yeah, we'll be targets."

Gregory shrugged. "We can take them."

Chapter 5: Strangers on a Train, Pt 2

Draco looked out the window as the train lurched out of the station, still listening to Gregory and Vincent. Once the conversation turned to tactics, he'd finally finally relaxed. He'd confessed everything and they saw the tension flow out of him. They'd lived with him for a year, knew when he wore a mask.

Platform Nine and Three Quarters disappeared from view as the train rolled noisily past a wall. Draco lost sight of the wizarding oasis in rigidly ordered Muggle London. Potter called his army 'ChaosLegion,' but in many ways Potter strode both worlds. Muggle society abhorred chaos. Staring out the window, Draco saw rectangular skyscrapers that stood gleaming, looming over older, elegant stone structures. Modern buildings dominated the horizon like disapproving adult children towering over their parents' shrunken frames, rolling their eyes while listening but not hearing stories of "the good old days."

Ignoring the stories made sense. The good old days were mythical. Some Londoner Muggle transported back a mere century would be shocked at the squalor, filth, and disease. Wizards lived in luxurious style even before Hogwarts. Draco could match Merlin's lifestyle, argue who lived better; only a Muggle blinded by Romantic lies would choose to live in the distant past.

The skyscrapers silently testified the truth. Muggles had arrived but recently.

As the train ch-ch-clunked through London, Draco envisioned the two parallel steel rails underneath it. Perfectly aligned, slightly rusted but no less useful. Well ordered, guiding him at this moment. He hadn't noticed it last year. He'd blindly mocked Muggles with fellow students, laughed at their pathetic ignorance while riding their invention. Wizards stole ideas from Muggles, and not even their best.

Draco had researched trains after Harry's visit. Most Muggles flew, these days. Why waste a full day traveling to Hogwarts when you can arrive in an hour? Trains? Muggle relics. Even the Hogwarts Express, now plodding through the suburbs, belonged in a museum when compared to bullet trains.

In the modern world trains carried coal, cattle, and Wizard children.

Draco stared at the skyline. All this knowledge could have been his, last year. He'd dismissed it with the phrase "Dumb Muggles." Didn't even dismiss it, because that implied he'd considered it. Draco remembered other phrases he'd used: Gryffindorks, Ravenclods. NothingPuffs. (Centuries of trial had not yet cracked the insult code for the 'Puffs, but it had been a lazy effort. All other Houses quietly looked down on Helga's brood so consistently that they'd never felt threatened enough to try hard). The Carrion sisters. Draco saw how amusing quips blinded him.

He'd never truly lost sight of his lessons. He might generalize Houses and stereotype people but he knew that groups contained subtleties: their own intrigues and factions. His training pointed out time and again that everyone viewed themselves the hero of the story. From true kings to the lowliest pawns, to those who never stood atop the board. So even though Draco didn't know or care about most people, he'd tried to remember that they existed. His contempt had dulled that lesson.

Potter and his Father thought nothing odd about discussing how Muggles could help Wizards, that Wizards deserved better than their unfortunate lot. His adventures in London demonstrated dozens of ways wizards could benefit. He'd seen innumerable ways to help individual Muggles; but nothing on a scale. Even ignoring the Statute of Secrecy, even if Draco studied healing and medicine and became Saint Malfoy The Praised to convert Muggle heathens and save their bodies and souls, it wouldn't matter much. He'd be just as useless giving his money to the beggars. They'd overwhelm him, Muggles in London.

Perhaps they'd come by train, nearly two centuries ago, when trains were new to the world.

Vincent and Gregory had been considering the news of Potter and Granger's retirement. They'd grasped the implications accurately and thoroughly, in Draco's opinion. Except for one point, something they couldn't know.

"One thing, though. Potter loved being General. He loved it," Draco said, still staring out the window as the suburbs had fallen away to a not-quite-picturebook countryside. He turned back, rejoining the discussion. "It reminded him of a Muggle story he adores, children generals fighting mock wars. In many ways, our armies were his childhood … a chance to play and bond with children he could consider equals, or close enough. He finally pushed himself and wasn't be treated like a child. He said he envied the respect we Wizards had, from our parents. And he discovered camaraderie, something like … us."

Vincent and Gregory considered this new information. They'd been around Potter, but Harry rarely dealt with them, preferring to deal directly with Draco.

Vincent started first. "If that's true he'd still run an army. He could give away more troops or even fight against the older years. He's not that good, Potter couldn't personally defeat the seventh year armies. There's a balance somewhere."

Gregory chimed in. "They wouldn't mind, as long as he put up a good fight. They'd complain, but just grumbling, nothing serious. Be great to watch, too."

Draco nodded. "Potter's giving it up because he believes he must. Not just to be fair. He has another reason, a compelling reason." Draco glanced out the window again, the landscape finally looking bucolic. "And I have no idea what it is."

Draco pulled down the window shade, conspiratorially. "But we're neglecting half of the equation. Two thirds, actually. What do the two of you want? What are your goals? We'd talked about going out for Quidditch, and you should both do that, obviously."

Gregory, clearly shocked, said "You aren't trying out?"

"I'm not sure. I think my … " he lowered his voice as a group of Hufflepuffs walked by the carriage, giggling at something Hannah Abbot said while she pointed at Gregory, "... slate will be full. We'll see. Besides, I'm a classic seeker build and there's no call for that anymore. What about you, Gregory? Apart from Quidditch. I mean, you're the best flyer we've got."

Gregory mulled it over, eyes closed. "I don't know. Doesn't it seem, you know, premature? Do I have to declare goals right now? We'll be doing all we can to get by. It's not that I'm complacent, but our position isn't stable. For now, we're reacting more than plotting. Chaser for me."

"I'm more of a Beater," Vincent said, then stuck his head into the hallway to gawk as a passing toad flew by. They laughed when Neville shouted "Found him!"

Draco continued. "Yes, we're reacting. But we've got a lot to consider. It may take a month or two. I spent the last few days doing little else, and I'm still not sure."

Vince nodded, then sprawled out across two seats. "Thanks. I appreciate it. When I was younger, I asked Dad why we do it, and he told me that I'd understand the rewards. I never really believed him."

Draco stood up. "Father told me something similar. But if you'll excuse me, I need to consult Potter and Granger." He opened the door to the hallway and paused as a gaggle of first years rushed by.

"About what?"

"Our lecture for first year Defence." Grinning, Draco slid the door shut behind hm and headed for the front of the train. The blond girl with orange glasses lectured a Weasley girl (judging by her hair) about something called a Crumple-Horned Snorkack. He dodged past the food cart, stomach rumbling slightly although it was too early to eat, and sauntered past four older Slytherins, nodding coldly. Two ignored him, but Randy Rookwood nodded back only to glared at by Ethan Jugson. Draco went car after car until he found Harry sitting with Neville and Hermione. Hermione waved him in cheerfully.

"Hello," Draco said. "I had some questions for the Generals..." Neville started to leave. "I didn't mean it like that Longbottom, and anyway, " Harry's lips twitched and Hermione shook her head NO, hair twisting into a tight spiral and then unwinding slightly after her head. Draco coughed to cover his reaction.

It wouldn't do to get infatuated with Hermione Granger.

"Thanks," Draco said, and stood aside as Neville walked past. "You didn't tell him? Great, now I'm the prat." Draco arranged himself in the seat opposite the other two. "Harry, I'm sorry I ignored you all summer. It's just hard. And … and Mother wanted to apologize in person but you weren't out there ..."

"You told your Mother that Harry was an Occlumens?' asked Hermione.

"No, you did Hermione," said Draco. "as did every single adult in the room." He let that sink in.

"Seriously Harry, you are the worst actor ever. Your parents reacted like you'd turned into a four-headed hydra declaiming in iambic pentameter. Even Hermione's parents looked stunned, and I imagine they barely know you. What did you do to them?"

Hermione started laughing. Harry just shook his head as she pointed at him.

"I've read the books," said Hermione, smiling sweetly.

"Shut up" Harry sighed.

"Occlumency is basically acting," tone serious, but quizzical.

"Shut.. Up. Shut. Up. Shut. Up."

"So. how can you be any good if..."

"Shuttity- Up" he said, voice rising.

Hermione dissolved into quiet giggles. Draco wondered if they'd started dating.

"I agree with you both. Professor Binns would have noticed. Of course Mother spotted it right away. If you had been alone, Potter, you might have gotten away with it. In any case, she said she just looking for stuff about me."

"With no respect for my privacy," Harry said.

"You aren't family." Draco shrugged. "I had expressed … mixed feelings about you. And your history. Where Father would simply threaten you ..."

"... Narcissa rummages around in my mind" Harry finished.

"Basically. Anyway, she thought you would make a decent friend and apologized to me for mucking it up."

After I'd confirmed the truth of what she saw. Harry Potter hadn't lied, not even during an invasion of his privacy. But, Draco realized that Harry looked good in all the exposed memories. He'd plotted with Draco, allied with him, been tortured by him. And several memories showing Lucius dealing with Harry, possibly afraid of him. He'd left out the truths from a particular point of view. It made Draco wonder exactly how bad an actor Harry actually was. He'd ask, but he could imagine Harry's answer, "I can neither confirm nor deny that I threatened your mother by acting like a normal 12 year old."

"Did she read my thoughts?" asked Hermione, more ominous than Draco ever remembered.

"She says she didn't."

"And why not?" Hermione's threat level jumped from hippogriff to troll.

"Harry'd already been revealed as an Occlumens. She probably didn't dare risk it. He doesn't go attacking Azkaban. Or maybe some female courtesy. I'm not sure how Mother thinks, really."

"Maybe she doesn't consider me your friend?" Hermione continued.

"Are you? You weren't last year," Draco said.

"I'd be delighted, Draco!" she said. The room seemed to brighten slightly and Draco thought get control of yourself. Don't fall for Granger! Hermione smiled sweetly. "But tell your mother that I will absolutely destroy her - in a nice way befitting of Sunshine Regiment of course - if she ever tries that with me."

"Of course." Draco decided to go get lunch. "By the way ... about Slytherin. Harry, if there's anything you think I should know..." Just then something chimed from Harry's belt.

"Excuse me. Muffliato." Harry put down his wand and spoke into a mirror, like they'd all had last spring. Draco only heard buzzing.

"You know, Draco, we aren't going to share many classes. Harry and I got tutored over the summer. Harry always did that before Hogwarts and I suspect you did too, but its surprisingly …. efficient."

"So you're in third year?" Draco asked.

"Er, I think you could be tutored and move ahead too. You know we're all ..." Hermione couldn't bring herself to say gifted.

Draco thought about it as Harry put his mirror away and canceled his spell. "It would isolate me even more. I can't afford that now. Although I may request tutoring from Professor … Asimov?"

Hermione raised her eyebrows. "Muggle studies?"

Harry interrupted. "That was Peverell Hospital. Another failed break in. No real problem."

Draco, who had started to get up yet again, fell back into his seat as the train lurched sharply. "And you are providing security." It wasn't a question, more a statement.

"I'm consulting" said Harry steadily. "You must admit I have a talent for those kind of things."

"I do." Draco paused. "Actually, it makes me feel better. That's why you got tutoring."

"Tell me, Draco. What would you do for security?"

"Apart from the fact that you faked the Chalice, I have no idea."

"What?" said Hermione.

Harry looked smug. "Now who can't act?"

Hermione glared at both of them briefly. "What gave it away?"

"I was just fishing," Draco mimed casting a line towards Hermione, "Actually a few things over the summer. The timing seemed too convenient. To suddenly find the Chalice right after all this other stuff. It reeks of you, Potter. Then the Chalice is better than legend? How often does that happen? I'd been confused while reading the stories in the Prophet and I noticed. And you consulted on security so naturally nothing can be easy."

During all of this Harry kept his gaze steady, some unreadable emotion playing across his face, and Hermione nodded sadly.

"Most of the security is by Mad-Eye Moody, really. I don't suppose you've heard of Security by Obscurity, Draco?"

"No."

"Well, you can have security by not telling people how things work. That's OK. It can be pretty good. But if you can show someone exactly how things are protected and that person can't break into it, then you've got real security. To break into Slytherin's Dungeons - oh don't look at me like that Ravenclaw is worse - you just need to know a password. A small bribe, a bit of spying does it. But if I laid out the exact floor plan of Gringotts you'd still have a hard time getting in."

"So you tell your security to everyone?"

"Some Muggles do, but they use amazingly complicated Arithmancy and do it to prove their security is unbreakable. For them, if you don't describe your security everyone thinks something is wrong with it. But I do share the security with a select group, and they try to break it."

Draco listened to this lecture with fingers steepled together, right hand drumming a slight pattern onto the left hand. He'd given Harry his full attention, of course, but he was thinking.

"Mad Eye tells me his security, I try to break in. When I find a new way of sneaking in, he figures out a way to stop me. So do you want to try and break in?"

Draco jumped slightly. That sounded fun, actually. "I doubt I could find something you've missed, especially with your head start all summer. But I could use a distraction. Are there real ways to break in?"

"Nothing's perfect. We have to use the ... " he glanced at Hermione and made air quotes "Chalice to heal people, so it can't be locked away in a vault. Would-be thieves hopefully don't know all the precautions. We've had a lot of attempts over the last month; they've all been arrested. The next set of thieves should be smaller and smarter. They'll plan. Rumour is that German Dark Wizards have formed an alliance..."

Draco forgot about lunch.

Chapter 7: Unknown Unknowns, Pt 1

They'd barely reached the common area when Ethan Jugson snarled "Why'd you go and do that, Malfoy?"

Professor Slughorn had escorted them himself, chattering merrily about students' parents, aunts, and uncles. But when they arrived at the solid oaken door that formed the entrance to the Dungeons he'd said his goodnight and tottered off, leaving the students to themselves.

Draco faced Ethan, and as he did Gregory quietly interposed himself between them. Not exactly between them; off to Draco's left. Normally Vincent would be at his right. Ethan wasn't as tall as his older brother Robert, but still stood almost a foot taller than Draco, gray robes with black and green trim, black hair matted down as though just recently washed, hard stubble on his cheeks. His eyes never wavered off Draco and the rest of the crowd moved out from between them, watching.

"I know this will surprise you, Jugson." Draco saw Robert Jugson, who'd returned for his final year, next to Ethan. He didn't see their sister Sara, he glanced around. "But not everything is about me. I understand your confusion, though," he added with a smirk. He spotted Sara directly to his left, casually lounging against a pillar near the fireplace. Harry stood right behind her, talking to fellow ex-Ravenclaw Padma Patil.

"What do you mean by that?" said Ethan.

"That wasn't for me. No great plan. I did that for Crabbe. He felt ... not miserable but not happy. And after last year I shouldn't have to tell you what he's gone through." Draco slowly turned as he was speaking, to take in the crowd and to let them see him. Daphne met his gaze, but Tracy Davis had her eyes downcast. Draco saw guilt and anger and rage and regret in equal measures. "I shouldn't have to tell any of you. I should have seen all of you at the funerals."

Colin Creevy let out a gasp, then tried to make himself invisible by pressing up against the stone wall, hiding in greenish reflections of waves.

"Hate me all you want," Draco continued, "but everybody knows I would have attended your father's funeral whether my father was killed or not. It wouldn't have helped you." Draco had finished his slow circle and again stood facing Ethan.

"It didn't help, Ethan, that I was there?" Ethan stood in front of him, motionless. Even in the dim light of the Slytherin commons room, awash in blues and greens, Draco could see Ethan flush. Robert glowered menacingly next to him.

Draco looked to Gregory. "Did it help, Gregory?" Gregory shook his head no, his jaw muscles clenched tight. "Theodore? Michael?" He looked at the other kids.

Robert spoke tightly, with control. "So you went to the funerals for what, Malfoy?"

"I might have been wrong. It didn't help, but it would have hurt more if you felt shunned. Seeing people, being together when you feel most alone, that's when you need it the most. It is not about me. It is about Us. This House." The Carrow sisters whispered amongst themselves. Draco ignored them.

"And the Sorting wasn't about me. I saw an out for Vincent and nudged him to Hufflepuff." Hestia sniggered at that and started to say something.

"Longbottom showed up at the funerals for the fathers of everyone in my year's armies." Draco said, whirling on her to keep the initiative, the floor. He dare not let this turn into a debate. "He didn't have to." Draco took a deep breath. "Anyway, if you think that was some gambit then figure it out. I left myself with one less friend in a House full of apparent enemies, so it must be a particularly subtle move."

Throughout all of this Harry Potter had managed to keep silent, Draco realized. There were some heads nodding yes, mostly murmuring, but one head slowly shook no. Blaise Zabini stepped forward. "I don't believe you, Malfoy."

"I imagine you'll struggle manfully on," sneered Draco. "Hopefully you'll provide a better reason than just envy."

"I will during our Duel." The murmurs stopped. Gregory eyed Blaise, then Draco. Pansy Parkinson giggled quietly behind him.

"Not to be a spoilsport," Harry started but the crowd shushed him.

"It's ... traditional Harry." Draco said.

Draco considered the implications of a Slytherin Duel and blanched inside. He didn't know why Zabini challenged him. That disturbed him. He hadn't written off Blaise yet as an enemy; Zabini felt too important to write off. He obviously considered Draco an obstacle, perhaps he'd seen his chance here. Was I a target of opportunity, or had this been planned? Nobody could have planned what happened at the opening feast, but it was a legitimate excuse. Draco tried to judge Blaise's confidence. He seemed happy, even smug. Of course, Draco looked supremely confident, did they have the same tutors?

Gregory's hand made a subtle chopping motion, barely waving back and forth.

That settled it. Draco didn't know why Gregory opposed dueling; but even if he was wrong Draco wouldn't gain by going against his advice. Gregory didn't have Father's training, but his own education had helped make Draco better.

"I decline" Draco said firmly and saw Gregory relax. Now to salvage the situation.

"You are up to something, Malfoy" sneered Blaise. "And if it was just to help Vincent, if it was just that, I could forgive you. But you've been skulking around, you and Potter who is suddenly in Slytherin, and that can't be good."

The crowd let out their breath. Someone in the back made chicken clucks. "Blaise, you seem a touch too eager. You've probably been preparing for this all summer. And I don't have much dirt on you." He hoped the crowd caught his implication. Draco turned to leave for his room.

"What about me, Malfoy?" said Ethan Jugson. Draco turned back. "I wasn't going to challenge you, never considered it until just now. But I'm curious. I challenge you."

Draco glanced at Gregory, who did the closest he could to a shrug without moving.

"Fine," he said. "I won't fall for his ambush, but I accept. Seeing as how the question arose we'll limit it to Summer?"

Ethan considered for a bit. "Summer in general, but plots affecting Slytherin ..." he paused, thinking. "The full year."

"Agreed. Start in ten minutes?" Ethan nodded. Draco glanced around the room, considering. "As challenged, I say no seconds apart from enforcing the rules. Sorry Gregory."

"That's OK" replied Gregory, relaxed.

Everyone burst into motion, grabbing the chairs lining the room's edge. Others brought chairs in. Harry started towards Draco, but Gregory intercepted him.

"You can't talk to him now" said Gregory. "Rules." Draco left to go to his room, his lazy walk showing a serenity he didn't feel. Harry watched him go then turned to the assembled crowd.

"What are the rules, anyway?" Draco heard Harry say, as he walked out.

Draco walked into his room and pulled out his journal. What do you know about the Jugsons? He wrote quickly, then he slammed the book shut, not waiting for the answer. Draco closed his eyes, took a deep breath, held it, held it, held it and then let it out slowly.

Draco kept breathing slowly and reviewed lessons in his head. He'd had many tutors, of course, but Father had always, always provided the closing lecture, had tied things together, reviewing the exact same lesson multiple times, each time going into more detail as Draco could understand more levels. And the first lesson, well the first formal lesson anyway, had occurred on Draco's fifth birthday.

There had been cake and ice cream, a lovely vanilla that even a five year old could enjoy without any flashy ornamentation or gaudy syrups. But as the day proceeded that had been it. Draco kept waiting for more, for his due, and by mid-afternoon he'd started sulking, even going so far as to kick Dobby, who was cleaning the hallway when Draco stomped to his room screaming that it was his birthday. Draco flinched at the memory.

Father had opened the door, frowning. Draco wanted to tell him to go away, but didn't. Even now he remembered his tiny rage at the world, at Father. It should amuse him now, at such a distance, but he felt it while he remembered it, past rage mixed with present shame.

"Draco, why are you upset?" Father asked, calmly. He stood in the doorway (Father never leaned, not that Draco could remember) and looked at Draco, who rolled off his stomach and sat up on the bed.

"It's … it's my birthday, and I didn't get any presents." Draco wiped away a tear and looked up at Father. "I'm supposed to get presents."

Father had nodded solemnly. "Yes, indeed. On your Birthday you get presents, and you haven't gotten any yet." He paused, then said quietly. "What present do you want?"

"You know! I've been talking about the children's Nimbus. They are safe to fly from age four! And now I'm five!" A crushing argument that brooked no challenge.

Lucius Malfoy nodded "Indeed. And how does kicking my elf get you a Nimbus?"

Draco started to talk, then stopped. Then words poured out of him, words of desperation and pleading tripping over his tongue and past his lips in a mad rush to get his present. Lucius held up a hand.

"It didn't help you. You know this, my son." His voice was gentle. "You were just mad. You lashed out at Dobby because you were mad. You knew what you wanted, but what you did doesn't help you get what you want. What would have helped?"

Draco thought about it. "I could have asked you about my present. Or tried to find where you hid it."

Lucius nodded. "You could have even asked Dobby. House elves know everything about the house."

"Dobby could have told me?" Draco had stopped sniffling by this point.

"No. But they are simple; you may have tricked him into revealing where I hid it. The point is that you've kicked Dobby, which didn't help you; and you've thrown a tantrum which hurts you. How can I give you a present when you shout and rage? You would be as spoiled as a child in a play, and you know what happens to spoiled children."

As he remembered the scene Draco realized, not for the first time, that he actually had been spoiled fairly rotten, but there had been limits. He'd gotten no birthday present that day although a Nimbus mysteriously appeared as a gift several weeks later, for no reason that Draco could remember.

"Still," Father had said, "even though you made mistakes at least you knew what you wanted." And then he closed the door to let Draco cry in privacy.

Draco took a deep breath. He'd been forced into this duel. His instinct, which Draco trusted because it was instinct forged in childhood playground bullying, told him that declining a second duel would leave him alone and vulnerable for the rest of the year. He'd cultivated an air of mystery, acting suspiciously, and while Slytherins could respect that they would turn on him if they felt his actions were against them.

Ethan Jugson didn't matter. Even Blaise Zabini didn't matter, right now.

What are my goals for this duel? Worry about achieving them later.

Draco thought about it. He wanted to preserve his secrets. Dominance over the rest of Slytherin, at least over those young enough to sway. To crush Ethan so completely that nobody would casually threaten him again. He wanted people to consider him cleverer, deeper, than he was actually capable of.

I need to be cleverer. He filed that away for the future. Later, after the duel, he'd review what happened and his mistakes. Perhaps he'd even review it with Potter, as a sign of friendship. Draco pushed that thought away, it wasn't an immediate problem.

What is my primary goal, right now? Draco figured he had five minutes to consider that. Tactics be damned, I need to know my strategy.

Draco Malfoy took a deep breath, held it, and let it out slowly.

Ethan stood next to the small table, placed carefully in the center of the room. The normal chess board had been set aside, leaning against the fireplace. Other games and quills lined other tables shoved back against the walls to make space for more chairs. First years sat on or (in the cases of smaller ones) crouched under those table. Even Potter didn't rate a chair. To Ethan's left the taller Robert Jugson loomed over the table. Draco calmly walked over to the empty high-backed chair opposite Ethan. The table stood empty except for one crystal flask perfectly centered.

Draco sat down as soon as he got to the table and, while Ethan still stood, Draco reached over and pulled out the flask's stopper. He dipped his index finger in, stuck out his tongue and let one viscous drop of Veritaserum fall, making sure that those nearby could see it. Draco pushed the flask back towards Ethan.

The first drop tasted of winter and almonds, a taste Muggles might call spear-a-mint for lack of a better word, and Draco felt a chill run down his arms. Ethan carefully placed one drop on his tongue, surprise on his face. Robert took the stopper and put it back into the flask.

"The second drop burns, and it reminds me of mandrake but it's still cold. You didn't accidentally swallow too much, did you?" Draco said pleasantly.

"You don't have to worry about me, Malfoy," Ethan said.

"But I do worry for you! Hm, I guess it hasn't taken affect yet." It was an obvious joke, but some younger students still laughed. Draco needed more time to think, so he closed his eyes. Otherwise he'd spend too much time trying to read the room and that was a distraction, now. He'd figure out the impact later. It would be much less efficient, but he'd have more time.

After a few minutes, the chill in his arms suddenly ignited and raced back up past his shoulders and into his face. Draco opened his eyes and the room took on a clarity, a sharpness like the opposite of a dream, and he could see the lines of the walls, the firmness of the table. Shadows which danced and would normally conjure up daydreams of monsters and images appeared as nothing more than tricks of light and darkness, lies the light played.

Draco nodded and waited for the first question. Ethan ran a hand through his hair, which didn't change its appearance at all. Draco wondered how he'd spent his time before the duel. Worrying?

"I don't suppose any of what you said before was a lie?" Ethan asked.

"It was true. Well, since you wasted a question, I may as well. Did anyone put you up to this?"

"Of course not. That's insulting." Ethan held the bottle of Veritaserum and idly pushed it back and forth between his hands. Draco didn't think that it was a gambit, just a nervous gesture. He didn't know Ethan well. Robert, his older brother, was a thug and Draco had expected him to be the boy's prefect, but maybe his outburst last year had cost him. In a Slytherin duel, Robert was too dull witted to be a threat to Draco and probably even aware of it. But Ethan, unknown fifth year Ethan. Draco wasn't sure.

"No more so than your question. As if I'd be stupid enough to accept a Slytherin duel right after making a bald-faced lie."

"It could have been a double bluff" said Robert, quietly.

"This isn't a play, Jugson." Draco snapped. Father used the line often enough; it felt good to be on the giving end and Draco saw the barb hit home. He almost sighed, then caught himself. Focus on your goal. "I apologize. That was uncalled for, but you know the rules. Next question?"

Ethan tilted his head towards Blaise. "Why didn't you accept his challenge, why mine?"

"Because you're doing this fair, to discover my secrets. I think Blaise already knows a secret and his challenge was just an excuse. You just wanted to know. That's the difference." Draco paused. "Are you plotting to kill or assault me?"

"No! Why would you think that?" Ethan looked confused.

"I saw how you looked after Crabbe sorted." Draco paused. "I assume your last question was rhetorical, so it's still your turn."

"Do you think you'll be attacked?" Ethan had stopped playing with the bottle, and had put his hands underneath the table.

"Yes. With Father dead I'm much more exposed than last year, and I have enemies. And now with Crabbe gone I can't expect Goyle to stop every attack, sorry Gregory, but we both know it." Draco drummed his fingers slightly across, then tilted his head.

"Did you know your father was a Death Eater before he died?"

"I … I didn't have proof. But yeah, some of his comments, some of his brags only really made sense. I knew." Robert moved away from the table. Questions were supposed to go quickly, but Draco didn't push things, and he knew that he'd use the time more effectively. As he waited Draco saw a look of dawning comprehension on Ethan's face.

"Why are you going easy on me, Malfoy?"

"What makes you think I'm doing that?" Draco shot back.

"Answer or concede."

"I don't have a problem with you, Ethan. Or your family. It does me no good to drag a secret out of you and make an enemy."

"How do you intend to win the duel?" asked Ethan, turns forgotten.

Draco shrugged. "I don't. I don't … OK, I care about losing." He surrendered a wan smile. "Stupid Veritaserum, but losing isn't important compared to the good of Slytherin. To save it, because it is in danger."

Blaise Zabini, forgotten and sparked with a growing rage, said "This isn't a duel, it's a love fest!" Half of the room (but only half, Draco noted) shouted him down. Robert, now back against the wall, looked thoughtful. Draco saw the nods, the glances. "You're just doing this for your own gain!" Blaise continued.

Draco pushed back his chair and stood up to full height. "I could tell you things, Zabini. You felt snubbed by Quirrell so you dig stuff up on me instead of seeking real power, like I did. I have more important things than internal intrigues of our House. Anyway, I don't have to answer your questions. I'm not dueling you." He sat back down and faced Ethan.

"That wasn't a denial, Malfoy" said Zabini. Draco ignored him.

"Ethan, do you hate your father? For going out that night or joining up in the first place?"

There was no hesitation. "Of course. But you already knew that. You feel the same way about your Father." Draco nodded, smiling on the inside.

Draco didn't trust divination, practically nobody did, but he saw the future. Blaise stood furiously by the table, impotent and unable to ask the question left hanging, that the room was dying to ask.

Draco couldn't tell people about last year, all the things he'd done. Even under a drop of Veritaserum admitting it would be too dangerous, too risky. It would be bragging – an eleven year old being set up as Minister of Magic – he could hear Professor Quirrell's first rule in his head when he'd considered the idea. Even revealing his Patronus felt premature.

Everything had resolved, if not perfectly then well enough. He hadn't embarrassed Ethan or any of the Jugsons, not much. Just enough to show respect, he thought. Blaise was an enemy but no worse than before. Draco had stated under Veritaserum that he felt the House was in danger and he was trying to save it. That was the important point. He'd given enough proof to assuage any doubts. His secrets remained hidden.

Any minute Ethan Jugson would ask about some confidence – or some plot - and Draco would quickly concede and leave having achieved all his goals. The small loss of face would be more than compensated by giving providing confidence to those inclined to trust him. Draco wondered what Harry Potter thought of this, would he recognize Draco's victory … Just like in a play … Draco frowned as Ethan spoke.

"So tell me, Malfoy, do you fancy Granger?"

Chapter 8: Unknown Unknowns, Pt 2

"So tell me, Malfoy, do you fancy Granger?" Ethan had asked.

The word No stuck in Draco's throat. Draco heard boys sniggering. The girls made no sound and he didn't know which bothered him more. Harry Potter lounged against the back wall, expression no longer unreadable. He's smirking, damn him. Draco tried saying 'No' again, just to check.

Ethan Jugson smiled, lips pressed together. "Take all the time you need. No rush." He dramatically interlocked his fingers and put them behind his head. Draco considered conceding and instantly discarded the idea. Conceding now meant failure, his preceding speech forgotten. Father had taught him In any experience, people remember only the most dramatic moment and the final moment. This was the most dramatic moment - Draco dare not make it the final one as well.

"I don't know. I may be infatuated," he said.

Draco now faced another problem. Going on the offense meant admitting Ethan had struck a nerve. So, he'd keep lobbing easy quaffles at the center ring until the topic changed.

"What makes you ask?" said Draco.

"Oh, Sara saw you talking to her and Potter on the train and said you seemed … distracted."

"We were discussing... " Draco started casually, but Ethan cut him off even before Blaise snorted.

"I didn't ask. Why do you think you may be infatuated? Seems an odd thing to not know." Ethan had the initiative and planned on keeping it. Draco had planned to lose, but that was before Ethan started winning. That's what I get for considering this a solitaire exercise.

"The last few times I've seen her she's had this glow around her. I'm worried I'm falling for her."

I didn't have enough time or information to take Ethan into account. Draco scanned the crowd for fellow children of Death Eaters. Ethan's eyes narrowed at Draco's answer, but he was in a duel, that could be anything. The Jugsons seemed calm. Earlier the Carrow sisters had hidden behind their tangled black hair, like Bellatrix Lestrange sported during her heyday, faces hidden from Draco's view. They'd whispered amongst themselves all during the duel, clearly on Zabini's side. But now they'd brushed their hair back, leering and making smooching noises in Draco's direction.

"Would you date her, Ethan. If she was older?" Draco kept his voice light. Just another simple question, chatting with an old friend. He projected the calm he felt slipping away.

"Of course not. She's a mudblood." One question answered, thought Draco. "That doesn't bother you, Malfoy?"

"Not as much as dating a girl who destroys Dementors," Draco shot back, waiting for the laughter to fade as an excuse to consider his question. He hadn't planned on winning but now saw several options. He didn't have time to compare. Plots were best pursued at leisure, planned carefully, but Draco didn't have time. That's the point of dueling. Draco chose a non-committal gambit.

"Since you disapprove, instruct me. What do you look for in a witch?" Draco smiled - that question was a minefield. Ethan might consider it not worth answering, just to win a duel. And if Ethan answered and pressed the point, well, he was younger. He could (truthfully) plead ignorance with no loss of face. Draco tried to remember who Ethan had dated, but couldn't. Draco suspected he'd never known. He paid attention to everyone but Time is a Malfoy's most valuable commodity. Older students' hadn't been a priority. He hoped the assembled witches would glance at Ethan's girlfriend (or crush); but their looks didn't form a pattern. Ethan hadn't answered yet.

"Conceding?" Draco asked. Elsie Ambrose stood looking down at the floor, hands clasped together tightly. She had a crush on Ethan, possibly; Draco filed that away. Pansy Parkinson stared directly at Draco, watching his eyes slowly scan the crowd.

"Obviously looks are important, and a nice figure. And not bossy."

Harry Potter had watched with growing interest as the duel unfolded before him. He didn't have Draco's experience, his tutelage in manner, tone and bearing. He'd been in many arguments but never formal debates. He'd never even imagined a Slytherin duel until a few minutes ago. But Harry didn't need any particular training to recognize that as a bad answer, at least as Slytherin witches judged. They hooted ample feedback.

Harry thought Draco seemed distracted. No, not distracted. Attentive to many things. A wide-angle lens. Harry couldn't see Ethan's face, wondered where his focus was. Harry's hands sweated. Very lightly. He'd never faced social anxiety, not the stereotypical nerd shyness. When 'In the moment' Harry didn't feel social pressure, possibly didn't recognize it. And threatening situations, social or otherwise, provoked his Dark Side which forcefully shoved fear and self-doubt aside.

But watching Draco play Slytherin Truth-or-Truth with a fifth year left him nervous.

"So, just like your mother?" asked Ethan. Harry started to say something. He hadn't caught all the rules but he'd gathered duels shouldn't dissolve into playing the dozens. "How does it feel, her coming back from the dead?"

"Family is off limits, Jugson." Harry heard the edge, the threat.

"I'm not asking about her. I'm asking how you feel." Ethan pressed the point.

"You are fishing. Too vague. I don't have to answer." Draco hadn't been leaning forward, but leaned further back.

"You didn't complain when I asked how you felt about Granger" came the smooth reply.

"That brooked a single implication," Draco said flatly.

Before, words had drifted out slowly, and there were pauses. Some awkward, some artful, and not all of those had belonged to Draco. Over the last minute, though, lulls and empty spaces had fallen away. The legato fireside chat transformed – accelerando - into a brisk march. Harry wondered if that was traditional, part of the unwritten rules that so often formed a larger part of any game than the rulebook. Perhaps this was some strategy, but Harry couldn't tell whose. Now there were no pauses as words volleyed back and forth. Question and answer, call and response. Draco sounded the same to Harry, no change in timbre or pitch. Ethan sounded excited; he'd found a thread worth pulling. Harry leaned forward, for once part of a crowd.

"You're mad she's back, Malfoy?"

"Yes. You resent your brother's outburst after your father died, Jugson?"

"Yes. Because she abandoned you?"

"No. Because he'd been invited to join, and you hadn't?"

"Yes. Because Lucius should have figured it out and rescued her?"

Draco stuttered slightly. "N...Not really. That's only a minor part. You wish Robert lay dead beside your Father, don't you Ethan?" The last came out quickly, raggedly. The exchange had only taken seconds and now time seemed like it should slow, like it should stop.

"I withdraw the question, Jugson. I concede."

A second later Draco stood up as the chair pushed back from the table. Gregory preceded Lord Malfoy by several steps. To Harry Potter it seemed like they'd moved as a single unit, he couldn't tell if Draco pushed the chair back as he'd stood up, or Gregory had tugged the chair and Draco, responding to the motion, stood up. Gregory had never said a word, never threatened the integrity of the duel or interfered. But ... his hand had been clasped on the back of the chair, grip tightening at each of Ethan's last questions. Goyle and Malfoy were practically out of the common room by the time Ethan heard the words.

Padma Patil turned to Harry Potter. "I'm beginning to think this was a mistake."

Footnote - Lucius's rule (In any experience, people remember the most dramatic moment and the final moment) is a restatement of the "Peak End Rule"

Author's Note - The next update will be Weds.

Chapter 10: Defence and Offence, Pt 1

For problems: Attack the urgent, consider the important, ignore the rest.

- Lucius Malfoy, as told to Draco Malfoy (Age 9)

Just before sunrise Draco listened to Hogwarts coming alive.

(Hogwarts is not alive.)

Thousands of wizards and witches scattered around the world - but mostly in the UK - love Hogwarts dearly. They succumbed easily, often before their sorting. Riding in gondolas under the moonlight, stomachs knotted in excitement and dread, they'd glimpse the stonework for the first time and feel reassured by Hogwart's quiet majesty. Older students cheered their entrance, applauded their sorting, slapped their backs as they joined their future home. First Years loved everyone by the end of that feast. Soon enough they'd be disappointed, scolded, overworked, and betrayed. They'd run to class, dodging Peeves, fall asleep during lectures and get sent to detention. Reality intrudes and feelings complicate. If students had to assign an average feeling, they'd label it 'Good' but could rarely point to one person that made them feel consistently good. They felt a subconscious desire to assign the credit somewhere.

(Hogwarts is somewhere.)

Not all students instantly loved Hogwarts. Some required another year. Most succumbed eventually, and even if they considered their years a terrible experience, they blamed people. Severus Snape - wherever he was - loved Hogwarts. If they knew of it, Muggles would adore it and become enchanted (in all senses) by its ancient splendor and bewildering secrets. Hogwarts exasperated and intrigued and intoxicated those lucky Muggles on campus. They explored a strange old world ripped from children's fables only more fantastic.

Besotted sixth years often adopted the jaded pose typical of teenagers and denied their love. (Fifth years studied and crammed and what little time for love they possessed we will not discuss). But as inevitable as winter turning to summer some new wonder grasped their imagination and shook away false ennui. The wrong hallway could lead to a month long quest. Strolling outside could turn a warm spring day into a wondrous adventure with beasts unknown, or a legend believed mythical. Romance blooms rapidly in exciting times and Hogwarts adds zest to life, after a brief visit to Madam Pomfrey.

Foreigners express shock at the attendance of Hogwarts reunions, held during Summer Solstice. Those who attend, typically as 'plus-ones,' bask in the sheer joy expressed by the returning alumni. They listen to the stories, see the camaraderie. Guests search in vain for In Memoriam placards around the halls, or graveyards and mausoleums on the grounds. They wonder how Hogwarts banished almost all the ghosts. Durmstrang is more respected than beloved.

For his part, Harry Potter forgot all about Oxford once he stepped foot on Hogwarts. Oxford now reminded Harry of Geordi LaForge: talented, interesting, and a good man to have around. But you only listened to LaForge's stories out of politeness. He won't draw a crowd or get the green-skinned girl like Hogwarts did. (Harry had a complicated relationship with Spock). Potter respected the Next Generation, but classics endure.

Harry loved Hogwarts knowing he loved a system, not a creature. He knew Hogwarts didn't care, wasn't alive. He never projected emotions on it, except as linguistic shorthand. Not like his classmates. One march morning Harry lectured his fellow Ravenclaws about that mistake. Afterwards, Cho Chang pointed to Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres' receding form and solemnly intoned "That, fellow students, is a Dork. It may, at times, appear to have tact. But rest assured you are just projecting it onto him. A common fallacy."

Potter hadn't even pontificated much. Anthropomorphizing Hogwarts barely registered as a fallacy: it wasn't harmful like attributing meaning to a simple text program like ELIZA or believing in Muggle psychics. His halfhearted lecture stopped well short of his typical pedantry. Hogwarts stood – except for a few floating parts – uncaring. Harry knew that, but he suspected that Hogwarts (that name being shorthand for the amazingly complex magical system designed by the Founders) did help those who roamed its halls.

Why else had Salazar laid down secret paths? Surely not to trap his students. Rowena had strewn puzzles to be found and solved, not to be ignored. Godric scattered magical traps to be avoided and duels to be defeated. And it just seemed like Helga Hufflepuff's style. The Founders hid treasures behind apparently fearsome obstacles that rarely did permanent damage (as wizards counted these things). They'd bequeathed Hogwarts, their glorious clockwork sanctum, a bewildering array of enchantments. And those enchantments changed. Just last summer a staircase that rose from West to East every Tuesday for as long as anyone could remember (except during New Moons, when it lilted slightly to the North-East and turned into a water slide) suddenly rotated into southerly facing trampoline and added a wading pool.

Hogwarts mutated according to some set of complex and contradictory rules that changed over the years, as the Founders intended. Hermione, in an mild debate with Harry in early August, pointed out that a system that had goals, acted on them, and evolved might not be biologically active, but the word 'Alive' seemed to apply. She'd eventually left angry, pointing out that Harry Potter had finally reconciled creationism with evolution.

Harry conceded the point (but only silently, to himself) and spent his spare time coaxing secrets from these halls to unwind after the frustrations of the day and renew his sense of wonder.

Harry knows love makes people irrational.

Harry believed in Hogwarts (the system) because true learning happens outside classrooms. Experience and enthusiasm trump rote lectures and the Founders knew that. So Harry Potter believed that indifferent, dead Hogwarts existed as a complex educational system. He was hardly the first to come to that conclusion. Most Headmasters grasped this eventually. Albus PWB Dumbledore understood well before assuming that mantle. Tom Riddle knew the truth and Quirinus Quirrell based his pedagogy on that insight.

While Draco spent those pre-dawn hours reconsidering and agonizing, Minerva McGonagall started learning this lesson.

Last January a lovestruck student discovered a single passenger dirigible. It showed up on a fairly predictable schedule, provided you knew a smattering of Mermish. On those nights it appeared it drifted towards music. One admittedly precarious jump from an 8th floor window near his bed would see our fifth year Ravenclaw safely in the basket undercarriage and then whisked to a secluded parapet in the Gryffindor girl's dormitory. Over the summer he'd gathered his courage and made arrangements, pleased at his cleverness. This route avoided nosy prefects and hallways patrolled by Argus Filch (who had been hired back on over the summer, much to the chagrin of all the students).

He'd studied the patterns, perfected his whistling, and plotted the astronomical charts. He'd double checked the dates: balloon would drift by at 1am the first night of school. He'd hadn't realized the tiny red zeppelin only followed its assigned course if the basket was empty.

At 2am Hagrid, out searching for a wounded Hippogriff he'd seen from time to time, noticed an Acromantula web stretched between treetops. He'd politely asked why it was there. Aragog ominously answered "Breakfast," but by then Hagrid heard the boy's cries and untangled him while fending off famished spiders with a pink umbrella.

And so, at 3am, Headmistress McGonagall lectured the unfortunate boy and assigned one weeks detention helping Hagrid, who'd agreed to repair the web in an effort to smooth over the incident.

Seeing no chance of getting any more sleep, she'd made a cup of tea while despairing about the students in her charge. The trick was to lean on the undercarriage railing, which had seemed obvious to her back in her sixth year. That propelled the balloon in the opposite direction for some reason. Her thoughts drifted while she sipped her tea, wondering what she'd ever seen in the rotund, balding, and utterly boring Undersecretary of Charms and Curses.

Draco hadn't heard that adventure, just some trees rustling that he thought was just the wind. But by five am the gentle grinding of staircases announced the start of the day, and Draco Malfoy decided he might as well get up. After getting dressed Draco slipped out the door, diary in hand, to do some research in the remaining hours before breakfast.

The first years fell silent as Draco strode into the lecture hall with Hermione and Harry Potter. They'd agreed to enter as a group after everyone was seated. Waiting looked unimpressive - unless you suddenly snapped out of a catatonic state - and they needed to signal authority. Professor Lockhart, newly appointed Head of House Gryffindor, stood behind the professor's desk next to an empty leather seat. Draco and his fellow generals walked in front of the desk. Once again Draco reflected that he hadn't looked nervous on his first day of class, one long year ago.

They'd come straight from breakfast to teach the first class of the year. ("Learning how to think precedes learning what to do," Harry Potter had explained to the Headmistress, who had sighed and re-arranged the schedules several weeks ago).

"We are Generals Granger, Potter and Malfoy." Draco said, indicating each in turn and bowing slightly at his own name. The class murmured, not all of them knew some classes would be taught by students. Many pointed at Hermione and whispered. Colin Creevey was pointing to Hermione and gesturing, but the nearby students ignored him. A few less pointed to Harry Potter and barely anyone talked about Draco.

"No talking!" said Lockhart to immediate effect. Draco continued, while Potter surreptitiously reviewed his notes.

"Welcome to the Hogwarts, and welcome to class. For centuries, until last year, this class was known as 'Defence Against the Dark Arts.' An appropriate name, although for years our instructors only pretended to teach that subject. Last year's Defence Professor, Quirinus Quirrell, actually taught us. We learned, as you will learn, how to defend ourselves. Professor Quirrell sat in that chair behind me slowly dying with an illness. Outside of classes he could barely move. But he taught vigorously and he taught us well."

Professor Lockhart nodded approvingly.

Hermione continued "Professor Quirrell, also known as David Monroe, named the class and the lessons he covered 'Battle Magic.' He broke tradition in many ways, adding the armies we Generals led as a new feature. He taught us how to fight. He taught us how to win. I can't describe how much I learned and how much fun I had. Today, you get the chance. I suggest you sign up for the first year armies."

Hermione cocked her head and continued, "Because without Professor Quirrell's training, I stood no chance against the troll that killed me."

Lockhart made no attempt to silence the class this time.

Harry Potter spoke over them. "Professor Quirrell taught us that trolls are the third most perfect killing machine in nature. General Granger would have defeated the troll but what she didn't know - what nobody knew - is that she was actually fighting the most perfect killing machine of a generation. Voldemort sent the troll."

Some students gasped at the name. Harry had started shakily, but he'd gotten the rhythm and had the full attention of the class.

"Voldemort sabotaged her weapons. Hermione Granger would have escaped, except for Voldemort's interference. She had learned enough to survive a mere troll."

Draco continued without pause.

"General Potter killed the troll. Later Professor Quirrell, despite being near death, fought Voldemort to a standstill. General Ganger's aid was enough to tip the balance and defeat him."

It was Hermione's turn.

"Make no mistake. You won't know enough to defeat an adult Dark Wizard this year. I didn't. Even weakened, Voldemort killed dozens of wizards. Dark wizards are dangerous, and it takes decades to achieve enough power to match them. Few do. I took advantage of lucky circumstances in that Battle. Voldemort's ritual weakened him, Professor Monroe's attack wounded him further, and I caught him by surprise."

Harry Potter continued. "You could say she got lucky. But plenty of people have opportunities. It's not sufficient to be lucky. You need to seize your luck, recognize it and act. The best way to win a battle, to win decisively, is overwhelming force. Unless you are a powerful Wizard or Witch, you won't have it. If you are weaker, the easiest way to win is to take the initiative and do the unexpected."

He nodded to Draco, who hid his annoyance. Draco Malfoy did not forget lines or miss his cue.

"Professor Quirrell was the greatest Slytherin of our generation. We honour his sacrifice. His empty chair sits watching over future classes. He didn't respect tradition but I think he'd approve this one. He'd approve students teaching each other in the lecture halls, just as we taught ourselves on the battlefield."

"Welcome," said Hermione Granger, "to your first lecture in 'Offense Against the Dark Arts.'"

"Take out your wands. Our first spell is Mahasu," said Harry Potter as the globes descended from the ceiling.

The first years chatted excitedly as they poured out of the lecture Hall. Professor Lockhart returned from the back room and greeted the trio. "Well done, excellent poise and an important lesson. I know I hadn't learned those skills until I had been out of school at least a decade. I worry my lecture will seem dull," he said, flashing them all a smile.

2nd year Defence classes had posed a problem. Last year Professor Quirrell had effectively taught first year classes to each grade. The older students hadn't needed targeting spells to gain confidence; older students cast more powerful spells than even Draco knew, but they'd spent years thinking of Defence Class in a totally different way. So Professor Quirrell covered many of the same lessons for each year. He hadn't done the exact same lectures, in the exact same order. Part of his special talent involved grasping the mood of a room, understanding where he stood, and what his young apprentices did (or, more typically, did not) understand, and explaining.

Draco envied that talent.

In reviewing Professor Quirrell's notes the Generals discovered that even N.E.W.T. classes had started from roughly the same position as they had. Older students had progressed faster since the Professor wasted less time teaching spells. But he'd lost time helping them unlearn bad habits picked up from prior teachers. In some ways, Dragon, Chaos and Sunshine armies had demonstrated Quirrell's pedagogy best. Which left the question – How to follow up? All Generals across the years had roughly the same grasp of strategy. If Percy Weasley's army fought Diggory's the elder students would have an advantage, but that was just the natural consequence of magic increasing with age. Why should 3rd years respect a 4th year lecturer, when they knew the same thing? In under a decade the problem would solve itself but right now there was effectively one first year class and six second year classes.

An authority figure seemed necessary, at least to get things started.

Draco sat in the same seat he'd used last year. Gregory sat down next to him as other students arrived. People gravitated to the seats they'd used last year but the resorting made for some awkward situations. Harry sat in Vincent's old seat.

"I thought you skipped ahead," Gregory asked, leaning across Draco to whisper conspiratorially.

"I'm curious. I want to hear this."

Vincent sat next to Neville. The Hufflepuff group had no infighting over seats, unlike other houses.

Draco felt grateful the classes occurred in order. Being able to just wait a few minutes between lectures saved him an extra trek to and from Offense, which would have eaten into his already full schedule even more. Draco, Harry and Hermione had agreed to split teaching duties after the introductory lecture. Harry would teach Wednesday's class and figure out who the most dangerous students were. Hermione's lessons focused on mechanics, helping students learn spells.

Draco, the only Wizard-born General of the year, would lead after-action discussions and draw comparisons to prior battles (mock battles in school and historical battles) and cover the history of Battle Magic. He was also in charge of quashing inter-army fights, making sure battles didn't stray off the field. (Quirrell hadn't cared about that. Unsanctioned battles occurred roughly weekly from Fall until the Abolition of the Houses and current fourth years aligned more by armies than houses. A true mess).

Professor Lockhart put his wand to his throat, said Sonorus, and his voice echoed throughout the room.

(Nobody knew exactly how Professor Quirrell's small pedagogical charms worked. The giant viewing screen for watching battles was well known, but his small personal screens and audio/visual system appeared to be unique. Quirrell's notes only listed spells taught, not spells used. Professor Flitwick had struggled over cryptic handwritten references for the entire summer. Harry Potter dropped his investigation after a week, once he considered his own sense of humor, and urged Flitwick to let the matter rest).

"Good morning. I am Professor Gilderoy Lockhart, your occasional lecturer during Offense against the Dark Arts. And I want you to know – I am a fraud." Harry sat up straight. Draco, already somewhat tired from his sleepless night, woke up fully. The class hadn't seemed bored, more wary, but now they were all listening intently.

"Why, just last night our Sorting Hat warned you not to trust someone just because they seem confident. Oh, I've achieved some items of note and minor glory. I've fought terrifying creatures. I've fought a Krogan and they are dangerous, believe me. You don't want to get ambushed by a Krogan. But then, you don't want to get ambushed by anything."

The class laughed. Professor Lockhart shrugged.

"But I've never fought a Dark Wizard. Just pests. Your Professor rightly mocked minor pests. I suppose for a Wizard of his calibre they are all minor. Personally, I steer clear of Hungarian Horntails. For lesser wizards such as myself and dare I say you, major pests exist. I pride myself a pest control expert so I doubt Professor Quirrell would have much use for me. He'd consider me a fraud."

"Oh yes, I know of his lectures. 'The only thing you have to fear is a Dark Wizard.' I suppose that's true, but I spoke to Miss Granger. That troll terrified her. Maybe you shouldn't be afraid, but that won't help you when the fear comes. And it does come, even for brave Gryffindors like myself. Or Miss Granger now, I suppose."

The Gryffindors cheered, but Professor Lockhart cut them off with a wave of his hand. Tracey Davis mock whispered "Where is she, anyway?" to Harry Potter, who shrugged. Lockhart turned to her.

"One point from Slytherin. Where was I? Ah ... 'One killing curse will bring it down.' A good rule, if you know the Killing Curse or any other suitable curses I'll teach. Perhaps I should have used a Killing Curse when I encountered a Geeger. It stands seven feet tall, strong enough to lift you off your feet and rip you in half. I've seen one stab its razor sharp tail clean through a man's chest, but I was lucky. I saw it. The Geeger is pitch black and almost impossible to spot although not technically invisible. In a darkened forest, you could pass feet from one and think it part of a tree if you noticed it at all. And they often perch in trees, or lurk in caves. Their teeth..."

He trailed off for a second, eyes distant in memory, then recovered.

"Anyway, one killing curse will indeed bring it down. And then it will explode, splattering those nearby with its blood. There are only a dozen uses for Dragon's Blood, but I can personally imagine hundreds of uses for Geeger blood. If only it didn't burn through anything in seconds. If you do use a Killing Curse on that nasty beast, you must be at a safe distance. Actually, always keep your distance."

He paused and stared around the room.

"While scanning for Geegers, make sure the tree itself isn't a Triffid. Easy enough to avoid, Triffids, but if you stumble onto one it may drain your blood or even bite your limbs clean off. You needn't even Apparate away from one. A few steps will suffice. It can be brought down by a single curse, even inflammare. No need to get fancy.

"Or consider the Iudices. This creature looks like a tall, well dressed, smiling man. They don't fly so much as float. Grinning like a hyena Iudices stalk their prey at the speed of a brisk walk. You'll need a few killing curses as they travel in packs. You'll also need to be able to cast them wordlessly, since they steal the speech of their intended victims. They' cut your heart out with a knife and cook it, while you scream without making a sound.

"Monachiko Dolofonous disguise themselves as statues. They move so quickly they could cross this lecture hall in the blink of an eye. So fast you'll never see one move. They are vulnerable to killing curses. Any one of the suits of armor you pass along the hallway could have been a Monachiko. But which statute? How to know? An Aliquid has no true form. It assumes yours after digesting you. It speaks with the voice of the deceased and retains its victims memories. The student sitting next to you could be one, right now. They are vulnerable to practically any spell except Diffindo. They don't transfigure exactly like a troll, but each limb retains the ability to move and an admirably murderous instinct even when hacked apart. Even if its no match for a Dark Wizard such as himself, Professor Quirrell unjustly slighted this creature when he made his list. I'd rank Aliquids well above Dementors. You always know when a Dementor is nearby.

"A few years ago an expedition of Aurors disappeared in South America. The only survivor raved wildly that the jungle itself attacked them; one Wizard a day, killing them and then skinning them. After the second day they Apparated away. It, or something like it, tracked them down to the village they'd gone to. The villagers found the skin. I happened to be in Argentina and they kindly asked for my expertise. I knew it wasn't an Aliquid since those consume the skin, leaving no trace, and do not track victims. In fact, I could quickly deduce that it was none of the monsters I've mentioned or that you'll find in any of your textbooks.

"I declined to investigate. Some pests terrify me. So, what do I have left to teach you?"

Students shifted around. Several were still inspecting their neighbors, trying to determine if any Aliquids lurked nearby.

"I am new to public speaking and teaching, but my question was not rhetorical. What do I have left to teach you?"

Draco doubted the first part. The ironic admission of fraud gave it away. Lockhart may be self taught, but he'd grabbed Draco's attention with his easy charisma and confidence. Most students looked towards Potter and Malfoy. Harry Potter smirked, folded his arms in front of himself and tightened his lips. Draco followed suit.

"Your Generals expect you to fight your own battles, this time. Well now," he pulled a looking glass out of a cape pocket and, looking through it, read off the name. 'Mr. Weasley?'"

"I dunno. All about those creatures, I guess?" Draco stifled a chuckle, and then a yawn. It had been a long night.

"That I will most definitely teach. It is my area of expertise, after all. What general point was I making, Mr. Weasley? What can I teach you that Quirrell didn't?"

The red-haired boy blushed. Professor Lockhart sighed and swung the looking glass across the audience. "Miss Abbott?"

"Uh, Pests are dangerous?"

"An obvious point. One that Quirrell knew even though he minimized their danger as a teaching example. I suppose you are correct, so let me digress. 'One killing curse will bring it down.' But you didn't learn the killing curse. Your lessons from last year emphasized two things. Efficiency and intent to do violence. Reflect on my pests. A Dark Wizard may be the most dangerous creature in the world, but none of those horrors I've describe lack murderous intent. They murder Wizards and do it quite well. None cast charms, but all possess innate magic and at least a low cunning, if not actual intelligence. But that was not my lesson, just examples. As I've said, I've personally never fought a Dark Wizard."

Professor Lockhart returned the looking glass to his pocket. As Lockhart drew his hand out Draco noticed the wand and then Harry's movement startled Draco who looked over at Potter bolting and Draco woke fully up while Gregory shouted and Potter dove towards the floor behind Padma Patil and Pansy Parkinson and only then did Draco dive and he glanced up and saw...

Lockhart's wand centered on him.

"Stupefy! Stupefy!"

Draco Malfoy hit the ground, unconscious. A second later Professor Lockhart's shields flared and sparked but easily absorbed the scattered charms fired at him. Lockhart calmly put his wand away and took out his looking glass.

"Very good. Two Quirrell points each to, let's see ... Mr. Longbottom, of course. Miss Patil. Mr. Crabbe. Miss Patil? Two of you, and in different houses? Oh, that will cause confusion. Mr. Zabini. Miss Abbott. I'm rather surprised I don't have to award you points, Mr. Potter. You had your wand out fast and dodged easily enough."

Harry Potter had, by this time, carefully stepped over the body of Draco Malfoy and returned to his seat. The entire time he kept his wand raised high, practically at the level of his eye, pointed at Professor Lockhart. He slowly lowered it to point at Draco.

"Enervate"

Harry helped Draco back to his chair. "You weren't attacking us, so much as proving a point."

Professor Lockhart nodded. "You withheld fire on gut instinct? Professor Quirrell would not approve. But I do. At least, when I am the target. Mr. Potter gets two points for grasping the point I clearly failed to teach. And I owe Mr. Malfoy an opportunity. He would have undoubtedly fired if I had shot anyone else. Just a touch slow, but better than his defenders. Mr. Malfoy, what do I have left to teach you?"

Draco had been rubbing the small bump on his forehead that threatened to grow, and had amplified the ringing in his head.

"How to recognize when we are in a fight."

Professor Lockhart nodded and turned to the rest of the class, after one last glance at Harry Potter.

"Five points for being correct and as way of apology. Last year you fought at a set time and place, when a bell sounded. You fought well but in my personal experience wizards rarely announce their intent to attack. Creatures never line up for battle. Pests do sometimes sound a bell ... to those who know what to listen for. You must learn to recognize when you are in danger. For magical beasts, learn the signs. It's easy spotting murderous intent one second too late. So recognize the early signs. Professor Quirrell knew this. But he only had so much time. It's a complicated subject."

"Some final points. The reason I declined to investigate that creature in South America was that it clearly had murderous intent and I had no earthly idea what I was dealing with. If I had investigated, maybe I would have discovered what it was, but I feared I would find myself in Mr. Malfoy's position. Remember that. I will also award several points to any students who put forth a plausible theory by next lecture and if I think you are actually right...well, I don't expect that to happen but I will try to think of a fitting reward."

Normally students would be packing, once a Professor started summing up. Some had taken out scrolls and scribbled down quick notes.

"Dark Wizards are rare, subtle ones practically mythical. Be thankful. Imagine if Voldemort could have held his temper in check or Grindenwald hadn't openly plunged the world into war? Pests hide when they feel vulnerable or to sneak up on you. If you know what you face, the danger diminishes. Just like Dark Wizards.

"Finally, in the future I will deduct one Quirrell point from anyone laughing about ambushes. Now, let us turn our attention to the variety of shield spells..."

Author's Note - An early post, since I have finished this and got a few other draft chapters done this weekend. I realized later that I could have posted this in three small chunks relatively easily. It would take me equally long to write this but would people rather see 3 small updates or a big one (assuming the final update took place on the same day?) Let me know.

Next update - Early next week I have some travel between now and then, but I believe I will be able to change back to a more aggressive schedule soon enough (except that I have further travel this summer).

I would be remiss if I didn't credit Ginny Weasley and the Sealed Intelligence for making me believe that G.L. could be an interesting character. (I have not in fact finished it, although I did get as far as the first defence lecture before I decided to greatly reduce my reading of HPMOR fan fiction).

I also now remember that Draco had a private room in the original work (HPMOR Ch 98). Oh well. I'm sticking with my version.

Chapter 12: Defence and Offence, Pt 3

"A fact your enemy does not know is a handful of Galleons. A fact your enemy knows incorrectly is a treasure beyond price."

- Lucius Malfoy

Draco got up gingerly from the table, dinner unfinished.

"Aren't you hungry?" asked Gregory. When Draco shook his head, Gregory grabbed the roll off of Draco's plate. At least this year Draco wouldn't have to listen to Crabbe ranting about the caloric injustice that was the Goyle metabolism. Gregory ate just as much, more perhaps, as Vincent and never gained an ounce of fat, so Vincent had a point. But it had been made, stated, reiterated, made unfunny and then funny again, and general discussed from all angles. No point complaining about the unfairness of life.

They made their way back to the Dungeons, but Draco passed their room, went through the Commons, and continued down another flight of stairs. In the common room fifth years sat, writing out scrolls and pouring over text books, already studying for their O.W.L.S. The left most entrance led to the upper year boys dorm, and Draco started that way as Gregory pulled up beside him, coughing slightly in place of a question.

"Robert," Draco explained. Gregory fell back. Draco went up the stairs and poked his head into the main room, glancing around, and saw Robert sitting on his bed talking to his brother Ethan. Draco cleared his throat. Ethan saw Draco first. His face dropped slightly, shock then annoyance followed by masked indifference. Draco hadn't set foot in the room, not really, he'd just poked his head in. Robert frowned, but got up and came over.

"What is it, Malfoy?" he asked.

"I just wanted to thank you, again. After last night, I didn't know what to expect. I shouldn't have done that, brought you up in the duel. I'm sorry."

"You're right. You shouldn't have."

Draco stood in the doorway, waiting. For once he didn't bother trying to hide the awkwardness he felt. In some cases, appearing awkward helped.

"Well, what? Spit it out."

"I wanted to ask you a favor, but I don't want to impose. Sorry, never mind." Draco started to leave.

"What makes you think I'd do you a favor?"

"My mistake. I'll go." Draco turned and went up the stairs, not looking behind him. Thankfully you ascended as you exited the Dungeons (or went from the main area back to Draco's room). He trusted his footing more, more going up. Going downstairs on a bad leg felt treacherous.

"What was that all about?" Gregory asked when they got back to their room. "This makes no sense."

"I was curious, why did Robert help me? There are lots of ways to go about making a friend. Giving a gift, sharing a secret. Getting someone to do you a favor works fairly well too. And if the favor actually winds up helping us both. I think Robert's an ally, or at least on the fence. But he feels, I don't know, honour bound to appear indifferent. I can work with that. Besides, sometimes ideas take time, and now I've planted the idea that I'm thankful and want to ask a favor. Although ... Now that I think about it, we should practice. I don't actually know if I can do this, yet."

"Do what?"

"Teach the Patronus charm. All right, let's see if you can learn it. I think the mechanics are easy enough, but you just have to believe," Draco said, holding his hands up defensively. "Yes, I know, it sounds like something out of that children's fable about the dog made out of paper."

Harry Potter walked into his room and then did a double take. "An owl. Huh. I like it, elegant." He closed the door behind him. Gregory's Patronus sat on the window ledge, looking out over the dusk.

"How did you know, Potter?" Gregory asked. "How did you know we could do this when we didn't. I mean, I don't think any of my dad's classmates did, ever heard of..."

"Sometimes it takes an outsider's perspective. And sometimes it's tricky. Did you ever, I don't know, look at clouds and spot shapes? Yes, well, that's harmless. It's what we're good at, finding patterns. And sometimes we get strange beliefs in them. Take Basketball, its like … Muggle Quidditch. No flying, but you throw a ball into a hoop. There are more goals, each team may make 40-60 goals a game. Well, many of the best players believe that once a player makes a few goals, he gets 'hot' and is more likely to make his next goal."

"But it turns out that they've studied it. And a player who has just made 3 free throws – a shot from a fixed point - is no more or less likely to make their next free throw. But all the players believe it. And, the belief got passed down. Players retire, they become coaches, they talk to their player's about the hot hand. But the statistics don't bear it out. Anyway, at some point, maybe one year of Slytherins couldn't learn it, or had a teacher who didn't think Slytherins could, so didn't bother teaching it, and then everyone started believing it."

"So what made you think we could?" asked Draco.

"It just seemed … highly unlikely that there were be a significant distinction between the houses on this ability. Clearly there are some forms of magic that depend on the caster's mental state, but happiness? Slytherins can be happy."

"Apparently so." Gregory walked over to his Patronus, whispered to it, and it flew off into the night.

"That's the kind of stuff Harry is teaching. I mean, apart from practical things, but how to think."

Harry watched Draco pick up his cane, that had once belonged to Lucius Malfoy. Draco was idly flipping it, first catching it by the snake handle, then by the toe. It seemed irreverent, to be almost playing catch with the walking stick. Harry remembered his meeting on Platform Nine and Three-Quarters with Lucius, how the sudden crack of the stick against platform removed the two of them into the pale haze, isolated from the rest of the world.

What else could that cane do? Harry thought.

"So why so secretive about it?" asked Gregory.

"Well, losing a cherished belief takes a toll. It's hard, admitting you were wrong," said Harry. Draco flipped the cane, then swung it in front of him like a baseball bat, or sword. He flipped it again, swung it again, snake handle gleaming as it arced through the air in front of him. "I suppose Draco filled you in about the experiments on magical potency and blood? He didn't take that well."

Flip, swing.

"You aren't seriously going to use that in a fight, are you?"

Draco paused, mid swing.

"I wasn't planning on using it comically. Or ironically. And so you do hear gossip, Harry, wherever it is you disappear to all day. Good to know. No, I'm not planning on using my Sigil in some random fight. But if things get out of hand, well. Who always says 'be prepared?' Actually, you sing it. Which is annoying, you know." Draco set the cane back down on top of his desk.

"He's one of those singers?" said Gregory, sarcastically. "And you didn't think to mention that yesterday?"

"What else does that do, anyway?" asked Harry.

"I don't know. It's one of those mysteries I have to unlock. According to legend it can do just about anything but I think we Malfoys invented those stories up ourselves just to keep everyone guessing. I haven't seen it do much more than make you disappear with Father. But it's been in the family forever."

"Can I?" asked Harry, holding out his hand. Gregory stiffened for a moment.

Draco glanced up. "I don't see why not." He picked up the cane and handed it across to Harry, who took it an inspected it. "But I'd advise against picking it up when I'm not around. Just in case some of those stories happen to be true."

Harry hadn't known what to expect. The cane clearly possessed power. He'd seen it last January. Harry's first thought - a thought he'd never been able to do anything about since he could hardly experiment on Lucius Malfoy's cane - was that the cane worked like a wand. After all, where was it written that you had to use a small piece of wood to use magic? Why not a four-foot long branch? But the Malfoy Sigil, as Draco had called it, didn't feel like a wand. It lacked the responsiveness of a wand, that small tingling sensation that Harry associated with defying physics, like licking a battery. But while Harry didn't feel the magic, he felt an emotion when he touched the cane, just as he felt when he first grasped the Elder Wand. But while the Elder Wand's presence cried out like a cascade of trumpets calling to glory, like the purity of righteous aggression, this cane's presence reminded Harry of an elegy. A quiet minor key, slightly out of tune. Was the cane mourning? The thought came to Harry unbidden.

He handed it back to Draco. "Thanks. Just curious."

"You can take the Ravenclaw out of the library..." said Gregory with a laugh, then turned to the window as his Patronus landed on the ledge.

The next day, as Harry sat poring over a few books he'd pulled from the Library shelves, he felt Hermione's hair brush past his shoulder as she bent down over him. He sat back with a jump, narrowly missing Hermione's chin with his head.

"You should cough, or something," Harry said. "You know you don't make much noise when you move. It's unnerving."

Hermione had actually forgotten about that, hadn't yet fully internalized all of her differences of her transformation. She knew she moved gracefully and quietly on an intellectual level, but she didn't feel any different than before. Still, she didn't apologize. Hermione and Harry had taken to playing a game where they never actually conceded they were wrong unless it was about something important. She'd been hoping to catch him reading Hogwarts: A History, since she was sure he'd actually read it. Well, not sure, but more probable than not. Harry knew too much. So she quietly stalked him whenever he disappeared with a book or to the library.

(Harry, of course, only read that particular book when hidden inside his trunk).

"Mm-hmm. What are you doing," Hermione asked innocently, "Studying History?"

"Research. Did you ever read any stories about that cane of Draco's?"

On the other side of the Library, Draco sat writing notes in his journal.

Urgent - The fight for Slytherin. Yesterday has shown this issue is more pressing than I'd feared.

Important, but not immediately urgent- Investigating Harry's relationship with Voldemort.

Author's Note – Harry read about The Hot-Hand effect based on research published prior to 1991. For example, see Gilovich, et al. "How we know what isn't so: The Fallibility of Human Reason in Everyday Life" for details. Recent studies - using the more detailed shot tracking metrics in the NBA, which record exactly where shots are made from and how far away defenders are - have reopened the issue. Players with a Hot Hand don't necessarily have a better percentage on their next shots but they take more difficult shots (as they gain confidence, or attract more defenders). And their percentage doesn't go down noticeably when taking these more difficult shots. (Other studies just looking at free throws also throw the original research into question).

So, it could be argued that they are, in fact, outperforming expectation. The data from earlier studies showed no effect, the current data implies it. Science marches on.

Of course, this research will not occur until 20 years after HJPEV makes this speech, so Harry is right according to the science of the time. I include the Hot Hand discussion because it was, 25 years ago, a good example of non-scientific experts believing something that scientists could "refute" (with the data at hand) but it turns out that the unscientific belief had something going for it, was not obviously wrong, and may in fact be true.

Skeptics - Be aware that its not just the unscientific who are sometimes smugly wrong. Be doubly aware when criticizing domain expertise in a highly competitive, high-stakes field where people are usually searching for an edge, however small.

Chapter 15: Chess

"Trust but verify. Distrust and verify. Remain uncertain and verify. Always verify." - Lucius Malfoy

Imagine you are a future Voldemort, aged twelve.

You are surrounded by lesser wizards, wizards you will mock, torture, and kill with impunity when you are older. They are, all of them, beneath you. You long for that day to come, when you cast off your mask of civility and seize control. But now you are at Hogwarts and while you are considerably advanced for your age, such that you defiantly face down older students, possibly even seventh years, there are teachers that wield far more power than your tiny body can hold.

After all, Magic grows with age, and you are so very young.

Not only magical power, but magical efficiency increases with knowledge, and while you are a diligent future Dark Lord you've only had so many hours of life and some of those around you have a century head start. You gnash your teeth, but railing against the injustice inherent in youth does not (so far as you can see) increase your power. So you control your rage.

Perhaps you bully smaller children or lesser children, but that would be a risk if discovered. A teacher might notice, might decide that you are too unstable to share any secrets with. You dare not bully Muggles outside of school, not with magic, lest you attract the attention of the Ministry of Magic and have your wand snapped. Your rage is great, but so is your intellect because you have no intention of being a stupid Dark Wizard.

Imagine your frustration.

In older, less enlightened times, undoubtedly you would let your rage fly off the handle from time to time. You couldn't keep it bottled in for years or decades. You would arrange for 'accidents' and fights that could be labeled as youthful indiscretions - just kids being kids - a heat-of-the-moment duel that got out of hand.

But those were other times and you, you are a Dark Wizard who learned how to lose at the youngest of ages, which meant how to pretend to lose. Professor Quirinus Quirrell taught you personally, in your first week of classes. No, you will not make that mistake. You will be charming - as charming as you can stand, which isn't much but you'll try - and beloved by teachers who will be happy to reveal their secrets to you, their favorite student. You will then research on your own and reveal your improved, better knowledge to them. They will mark you as important, and seek to curry favor with you, not because you are Dark but you may very well grow up to be the next Albus Dumbledore, and they would like to be able to brag, to say "I taught him that" or "I knew him when he was just a child." Yes, even a Dark Lord needs allies, at this age.

So you make allies.

You channel your rage, mask it with a bewildering array of habits that may sometimes harm those around you but never appear malicious. Even those you hate will be able to consider you as a friend, or if not friend then at least a convenient and useful ally. You cannot bring yourself to act as if you were beneath anyone else your age. But you can pretend you have equals. A few, not many. With them, you are usually friendly but sometimes put them in terrifying situations as a joke, a way to blow off steam. You may even get one of them killed, if you can arrange it. That would be useful, a memory you can treasure. You are a smart Dark Wizard, and if you do murder from time to time, you'll get away with it.

You will grow up to be a Dark Wizard. Your rage won't trip you up.

But you may make another mistake that would let an observer unmask you, reveal your intentions to the world. Maybe one you don't even notice.

Draco Malfoy sat as his desk, drumming his fingers, trying to imagine what mistake Harry Potter would make if he were a future Dark Wizard. He'd done this exercise several times already. And he'd always reached the same decision: Harry Potter would act identically whether he intended to be Voldemort or not, if he were clever. And Harry Potter was definitely clever.

It was no help, imagining yourself as Harry Potter.

Draco needed evidence that he lived with a future Dark Lord. Luckily this was important, not urgent. Draco had a head start in studying, and Potter couldn't reveal himself anytime soon. If Draco could get proof enough to convince others, he guessed he still had five years. Maybe a bit less.

If it came to that.

Draco stood in the middle of the Hospital. He'd been thoroughly searched, as he had been every time. He'd gone through the anti-magic zone. The Aurors hadn't found anything, and since they normally didn't do more than keep a watch on this area, the safe area, there was only one Auror on duty staring at him. He looked at the rows of beds on it, most of the patients were unconscious, but some were moaning. Orderlies were fetching water, trying to make them comfortable.

"Could you please turn around, sir" said Draco to the burly Auror watching him.

"Now why would I do that," he asked?

"Because you know I'm trying something," said Draco. "And that's a false advantage. In a real security breach you wouldn't know who to be watching. There are other people here. This is hard enough without you knowing who is the bad guy. So this extra attention is unfair."

"Oh, I was just watching to see what happens," said the Auror. "It gets a mite boring these days, not like the summer when everyone was attacking this place. Right filled up Azkaban's cells. Well, what's left of it, anyway." The Auror paused, thinking, tapping his wand against his cheek in an offhand manner. Draco had noticed that patients who went into the healing area never came out. There was another exit, into a different area. One way doors, probably. "Tell you what, anything funny happens and I'll count to three, which is slower than I'd give. And if it's subtle, I'll count to ten."

Draco sighed. "I suppose that's fair," Draco said, and walked over to the spot he'd arranged.

There was a small Whamf and Dobby appeared.

"One …. oh hahahahaha! Oh, that's good!" The Auror had stopped counting, doubled over in laughter.

"Dobby is very sorry, sir. The others ambushed him." Dobby wasn't holding Draco's wand, wasn't holding anything at all. In fact, he rolled slowly around on the spot where he appeared. Several of the patients sat up from their bed to look and see what the commotion was. Dobby rolled, tied up in small ball of what looked like Acromantula webbing, leaving only his face free. "It wasn't Dobby's fault, sir! Oh dear..."

Another House Elf appeared in a small puff and bowed to Draco, and then the Auror.

"Your wand is safe, sir! And we will return it," the elf said, "once you leave the hospital area." The elf bowed again, then disappeared.

Dobby kept spouting apologies but, bundled as he was, couldn't smash his face into anything and just rolled around the floor, as the other patients started laughing.

"Thank you all for coming to this optional evening session of Muggle Studies," said Professor Asimov.

Draco sat in the Muggle Studies lecture hall, which was packed to capacity with students of all years and houses. Draco could see Luna Lovegood sitting in the front row, wearing bizarre glasses made of paper with one red lens and one green one. Ron Weasley sat chatting with Fred and George, who were ignoring him. The hall was full of students, those who thought Muggles exotic, the teacher's pets, the curious, and a few with nothing better to do. Harry had dropped hints for days that Draco should really attend, that everyone who missed it would be jealous, that he envied Draco the experience and Draco agreed just to get Harry Potter to shut up.

Which wasn't rational, except that it achieved Draco's desired goal. In any case, Draco planned to attend because he'd triggered this session during one of his discussions with Professor Asimov. Draco had stopped by to ask a few questions and had been asked "Why do so many of your colleagues resist my class?"

Draco had thought about it, then answered.

"Inertia, mostly. Many believe that Wizarding society is better, as a matter of course. To a certain extent it depends on your viewpoint, but until the last two centuries they were probably correct. Some Muggles lived better than the average Wizard, but very few. But mostly, you are teaching a class that they can't see any benefit from."

"Ah, of course. It's obvious once you say it. Students ignoring professors is the natural order in both worlds. I have to find something interesting."

So, when last class the Professor had announced a special session that "Would not be on your test, but would be 'something interesting.'" Draco resolved to go.

So he sat there, while Professor Asimov walked the stage. "Thank you all for attending opening night. This is a movie, a muggle play. As you may know muggles can make moving pictures like wizards, but require special equipment to do so. We've finally fitted out this hall with that equipment and worked out some of the problems with magic and technology. In consultation with some of your Muggleborn students, I've tried to pick a movie that is educational about muggle society. And we'll see some of those … later. For now we've picked something that is just enjoyable. Rest assured that none of the beasts you see in this film exist, at least not as we know, and that most of the technology is also make believe. In many ways, this is a modern day children's story, but as we all know fairy tales form a large part of any society. And it is undoubtedly popular."

Harry Potter, sitting in the projectionist booth, dimmed the lights and flicked on projector, which had taken him days to set up, but incorporating magic and technology was a long term research goal anyway. He reached over for his popcorn just as the main theme blare of John Williams famous score announced the beginning of the movie and the slow introductory text crawled.

The next day eight students received detention for Lucius Gladius fights in the hallway.

Muggle Movie Night became a popular tradition.

It was late Wednesday night, several days after the last meeting of the Bayesian Conspiracy, when Harry Potter walked into the room he shared with Draco and Gregory.

"Why don't you include us in your other conspiracy," Draco asked, "the one you do instead of going to classes all day like a normal student?"

"I don't have to be in," Gregory added, right hand by his ear. "Unlike some people, I like having down time. Of course, if its interesting..." They'd been playing exploding snap and Gregory felt that Harry Potter's sudden entrance had robbed him of his glory. Some of it. Gregory flicked his fingers forward and pop! felt vindicated.

"I've considered it a lot. I want to. But I just can't, not yet. I need to manage risks." Telling secrets was frequently just one of those things Harry Potter couldn't do. Not without Hermione's blessing. He could tell those who already knew, of course. He could evade. But Hermione's arguments that summer about slowing down had actually bound his tongue even more. He couldn't trust Draco Malfoy completely.

Draco's training wasn't complete.

"And we're a risk," Draco said flatly.

"I don't think so," said Harry. "It's one of those things that's impossible to know, so the only cure is more time. It's like we discussed last year, you can't just barge into a fast friendship, or something like this. And last spring raised the stakes dramatically."

"Do you know why I conceded my duel, Harry?" Gregory gave a start, then went over and closed the door, and started to ward it. His wards weren't as advanced as Harry's own, or even Draco's, but Gregory knew more than the curriculum had covered.

"To avoid upsetting the Jugsons. Which apparently worked, if rumour is true."

Gregory spoke up. "A great move serves multiple purposes."

While Draco nodded, Harry thought. He could see a lot of possible reasons. But reasoning from so little information was difficult...

Draco interrupted "Do you play chess, Harry? I've got two sets."

"I know the rules to Muggle chess," Harry said, "not Wizard Chess."

They set up the board, Draco explaining while Gregory took out the the pieces - green for Draco and silver for Harry - and placed then on the board carefully, so as not to annoy them. After each piece was set down, it marched over to its assigned square. Draco had already covered pawns and knights when Harry interrupted.

"The rook moves horizontally, and the pieces seem to be heading for the right starting locations. I think they are the same rules for Muggle chess, actually."

"How do Muggles make the pieces move, then?" asked Gregory.

"They just pick them up and move them. How do wizards do it? Wands?"

"No, you tell which piece what you want to do and you have to convince it," said Gregory. "That's what makes it interesting."

Draco looked stunned. "So, you just physically move the pieces? That … That's … awesome. No backtalk? No second guessing? If you discover a brilliant tactic you can just do it and not to have some knight turn left instead of right because he felt like it? Sounds amazing, although not nearly as useful for teaching how to think. We have to play Muggle chess! Later, though. "

Draco took out his wand, tapped it on the table. The pieces stood up a bit straighter, at attention.

"Silver pieces – Just as Father gave you to me, I now give you to Potter. You follow his instructions. Understood?" The pieces agreed, some grumbling. The queen, apparently, didn't like the look of the new boy. A few pawns whispered conspiratorially. The king's bishop snored, only to be prodded awake by the King himself, who lilted disapprovingly.

"Pawn to King Four," said Harry Potter. The pawn stood there, twisting slightly, as though looking over it's shoulder back to Harry. "Um … Pawn to King Four Please?" The pawn untwisted and marched forward two spaces. The game proceeded quickly. Draco, whenever making a move, would simply point out that it was good move, offered the piece a chance for glory, to help his teammates, or simply promised the piece it would be safe. Harry, by contrast, had to wrangle the pieces considerably. But like many gifted children Harry had been introduced to Chess and spent several weeks studying it deeply before he realized that becoming great at chess meant that he'd become great at chess, and little else. Still, Harry had a decent grasp of tactics and positional strategy. In Muggle chess Harry felt he'd trounce Draco, but Draco's pieces always did what he wanted, while Harry's pieces committed their own follies. It was an even game.

"Castle Queenside please," said Harry Potter. "It will protect the king, and bring the Rook to bear on the upcoming battle in the center. You'd like that, wouldn't you?" The rook nodded enthusiastically. "And everyone will be much safer."

"That's a bad move, Harry," said Draco.

"I think it's a good move, it does exactly what I've told them, and the pieces will do it. I doubt I could convince that Bishop sacrifice itself in an attack, which was my other choice."

Draco shrugged and Harry confirmed the move. His King shifted over two spaces to the queen's side, and then stepped aside to let the rook pass. But as the Rook went by it took out a sword and stabbed the King, shouting "Aha!", shimmering from Silver to Green. The other Silver pieces booed and shouted "Traitor!"

"You lose," said Draco, taking out the box to start storing his pieces.

"You knew that rook was a double agent! That's not …," Harry paused while Draco just looked it him quizzically.

"Fair? What's fair got to do with it?"

"So is that normal, Draco, in wizard chess? Traitors?"

"Of course not. This is the set Father taught me with. A set for teaching." In his mind Harry could hear Draco's words from before the game. Just as Father gave you to me, I now give you to Potter. "And my first lesson – Learn who to trust."

Harry remembered that Draco had offered this game to provide an insight into Draco and his earlier Duel. "So you are upset because you aren't trusted?" asked Harry.

"No. We don't play that game, Harry," said Draco, who had taken out the box for the green pieces and ordered them back. "I admit I'm not thrilled with it but I'm a Malfoy, I understand. And we have history. But think about the game, and now consider why I just asked you to play chess right then."

Harry thought. Harry remembered logic puzzles where a question is posed, "How many blue-eyed people exist on this island" where everyone is a perfect logician, or the solution to some obscure math puzzle among expert mathematicians. The islanders don't know. Nobody can see their own eyes, since they don't have mirrors (and only trust what they can see). But then a wise old man says "I see someone with blue eyes." And as they days go by eventually all the islanders, using their perfect logic, know the answer. Because they realize that if only one person had blue eyes, he'd know after a day or two (seeing only brown eyes) that he was the only one. The more people with blue eyes, the longer it takes, but a person who can see one other islander with blue eyes will know that the other islander should figure it out instantly, if his eyes weren't blue.

They'll all figure it out, eventually, no matter how many blue eyes exist, once they recognize the inferences when other people can or can't solve the puzzle.

So, while Harry couldn't narrow it down before, the fact that the Chess game had been meant as a lesson. A lesson with two purposes, a primer on trust and Draco's answer to Why did I resign? Still, he couldn't decide between two answers until he heard Gregory's small "Oh." Realizing that Gregory had missed the solution made it easy.

"You resigned to avoid revealing your anger at your Father, not your Mother. Lucius Malfoy trusted Voldemort, no that's not really it, he distrusted Dumbledore and you fear making the same mistake with me."

Draco nodded. "He couldn't tell which pieces were on his side and that's the first lesson. The very first lesson." Draco's voice seemed to crack. He'd carefully considered this speech earlier. It might reveal that Draco knew what Parseltongue implied, but he didn't have to admit that. Draco had agonized over this for the summer. "For a while, I thought that maybe Father knew what was going to happen and just sacrificed himself. But if he knew he'd have probably found an excuse to let Gregory and Vincent's fathers not show up. Maybe I'm wrong but Father didn't know. You talk about the fundamental rules of rationality, but the fundamental rule of politics is to understand your relationship with those around you and Father failed. It's ... haunting me. You seem like my friend, but we both keep secrets. I'm mad at Father for getting it wrong. I believe you, but … I wonder if I'm making a mistake trusting you. If I won't end up dead because of it, the same way Father did. I'm sorry, Gregory."

"Don't worry. We've all thought it. If we turn up dead at least the others will know," Gregory shrugged, displaying an indifference he didn't feel.

"What," said Harry, even though he knew the answer.

Gregory kept putting the chess pieces away. "You clearly had some connection with Voldemort, through your scar. You could see through it, the night he came back. We discussed it over the summer."

"Like I said, Harry," Draco continued, "I understand. I can't prove a negative, but I have doubts. Maybe you have doubts about me, but you need me in your conspiracy. It will reassure us both. We complement strengths, I'd be useful. I have to keep an eye on you, you are too important, and if you didn't freeze me out we could trust each other faster. Shave years off the process. You must understand this, now."

"I do. But, I'll have to discuss this with others."

Gregory, having put away the pieces, was now back at his desk and working on some Transfiguration homework. He didn't look up. "I hope you investigated them more than your borrowed chess set."

"I could give him Veritaserum..." Harry saw the flaw. "Wait, there's no way to know if someone is an Occlumens, is there?" The same informational attack that Harry used to deduce how the Dark Mark worked applied here. If some test existed, nobody's deception could be perfect. The phrase Perfect Occlumens implied no such test existed or had yet been discovered, anyway. Headmistress McGonagall started to answer, but got interrupted.

"I would have trusted the serum, before. Never imagined someone so young could even start training. Just goes to show." said Mad-Eye, stomping around the office in a slow circle. He hadn't yet taken the cure, despite providing security for the new hospital. He still had doubts. And while he would never admit it, Moody enjoyed his current appearance and the fear he caused. Made his life easier, too, lots of people surrendered to him. Those he attacked a touch less violently, before arresting. Just in case they were faking.

"Then how do Auror's know who's testimony you can exclude," Harry asked. The Wizarding legal system, despite seeming quaint, clearly had a staggering number of flaws.

Amelia Bones answered "Tradition. Most people can't, so the default is that we accept it, certainly for anyone as young as Draco. Once you've started training or been caught in a lie using it, well, you can never use what you say under Veritaserum to convict someone else, but your memories can be used against you, of course. And as a matter of tradition we tend to discount accusations by certain Houses once they reach maturity."

Harry thought about the implications of this, trying to see if they matched his experience. If what he'd heard was accurate, Dumbledore could have raised the issue to save Hermione, if he had any suspicion of Draco. But would Dumbledore actually have objected? Dumbledore had been willing to let Hermione go to Azkaban... he'd played such a complicated game Harry couldn't judge anything from Dumbledore's actions, because he'd been reacting to complex prophecies and who knows what else.

Harry sympathized with Draco. This would be easier if everyone could trust everyone. Harry felt reasonably certain Draco had been turned, but...

With the revelation that Harry couldn't trust Veritaserum to make him fully certain, the other obvious solution required a carefully worded Unbreakable Vow. Harry doubted Draco would accept. In any case, Harry didn't want to use a vow on Draco or on anyone he knew personally. It would cause resentment. Letting the Philosopher's Stone fall into the hands of a Dark Wizard? That was an existential threat. Harry couldn't allow that.

And Harry Potter couldn't rationalize away his knowledge that the greatest threat the world faced was Harry Potter.

Harry's Vow automatically stopped him from doing anything rash, like breaking the Statute of Secrecy without preparation. That was the good part. But it only stopped him when he was somehow aware of the problem. Like Veritaserum or Parseltongue, the Vow wasn't an Oracle. It didn't stop him from ending the world accidentally or provide him with knowledge he didn't know at some level. Harry spent the summer considering various ways he could topple that first domino that led to Armageddon, because once he did know something then the Vow would protect the world from himself.

Unfortunately Harry Potter had a particularly vivid imagination.

The more he'd thought about the problem, the more restrictive his Vow became. It tightened as summer went on, as Harry became more and more aware of the number of ways he could destroy the world. At first - in the early days - his Vow empowered Harry. Now it restricted him considerably. Decisions he would have made quickly, neglecting a tiny probability of failure, now had to be examined in detail.

The odds of Draco turning Dark? Small, but there. Not quite negligible.

Casting a Vow on Draco might make Draco bitter, might nudge Draco out of the light. Eventually. And honestly the Vow didn't guarantee safety.

Harry defeated Voldemort while operating under the Parseltongue curse. He could still end the world accidentally, if he didn't know some crucial piece of information. If he rushed things. Harry could imagine Draco, wounded by his Father's death, becoming the next Dark Lord. Probably not an insane Voldemort persona, but a Dark Ruler? Harry couldn't dismiss it outright, couldn't rationalize it away without detailed consideration that frankly he didn't have time for. As Draco himself had pointed out, trust was a complicated issue and not Harry's strong suit. He'd be able to do it, later. Time would let him turn his 95% probability of Draco's redemption into 98% into 99% into some number so certain that to not act on it would be irrational.

But Harry's own rationality, coupled with the Vow, enforced caution. Four months ago Harry would have spilled the secrets of his victory over Voldemort to Draco. Harry would demonstrate trust and not seal the memories. After his Vow Harry couldn't confess without pre-committing to seal those memories away. It was just the first of a growing list of things-he-found-he-couldn't do.

Harry could imagine a perfectly safe Vow to make, but now that he lived under that burden he wouldn't inflict it on another.

He'd had to talk with Hermione, convince her.

Harry couldn't do anything now, realized he was wasting time, and went back to the business at hand with the Order of the Phoenix. He had details to attend to, things to do, things he could affect right now that he needed to do, before he could progress to the next phase of his plan.

Chapter 19: Asymmetric Warfare, Pt 2

"People promise according to their hopes, but perform according to their fears." - Lucius Malfoy

They came just after midnight, hours after the battle ended.

By tradition - almost as old as Hogwarts itself - Slytherin plots inside the dorms were limited to maneuvering. No fights, no thefts, no duels (saving Slytherin Duels) took place in the Dungeons itself. A Slytherin could rest safely inside his room, inviolate, protected by tradition. Pranks occurred, but actual attacks were unheard of.

Draco heard a quick shout, then Somnium! cast three times. Gregory slumped off his bed just as Draco's eyes opened, then his sight was cut off quickly, a bag placed over his head, and a few punches thrown in for good measure. There were voices, muffled voices, and Draco was carried away. Thoughts of they wouldn't dare mixed in his head with a voice that replied they did. Draco thought they were taking him upstairs, but they doubled back and went down. Draco could tell they passed through the common room, and now the voices spoke up, more jovial. How many were there? The hands holding him circled his biceps easily. Older students. His wand? Probably dropped besides his bed. The Sigil? Draco thought for a moment, then decided to hold that in reserve.

They mean to scare me. Not kill me. Thinking it didn't make it less scary.

Eventually they threw Draco into a chair and ripped the bag off his head. There were just three assailants, Draco thought there would be more, but just three. Maybe some had left? The wall torches flickered behind his captors, they hadn't bound him but then again he had no wand, and they were upper years. Draco could see the stairs leading up and out, but couldn't make it past them. They wore black robes and black gloves, but plain white masks shone dimly in the reflected torchlight.

There didn't seem to be anything worth saying, at this point.

The tallest one cast Petrificus Totalus! Draco went rigid in his chair, but didn't quite slide out of it. His breathing grew more ragged, shallow. Two others started casting Frigidero while the tall one created water and doused Draco repeatedly. Their voices were distorted and impossible to recognize, but Draco didn't think the tall one was Robert Jugson. A bit too round. Maybe he was just hoping, though. Draco started shivering and, as the temperature got colder, panicking.

It hadn't been real, his duel last spring with Hermione.

He hadn't actually been cursed by a Blood Cooling charm. But fake memories feel just as vivid as real ones. Draco remembered lying on the wooden floor, shivering and unable to move. He remembered getting so cold that he felt hot, wished he could slip out of his robes but limbs too tired to move, teeth not so much chattering as vibrating.

After a few more spells his captors seemed satisfied. Draco shivered but it wasn't that cold, nothing compared to the Blood Cooling curse. The tall one kicked Draco's feet up, he slid out of the chair and cracked his head against the stone floor and his vision exploded into lights.

"Now, you just stay here and think about how we don't need saving. We've gotten along fine without Little Lord Malfoy and we'll do it again this year." They doused him a few more times, cast a few more Frigidero spells, and extinguished the torches. Draco shivered, alone, and tried to get his breathing under control.

"Over here!"

Draco focused and saw Harry's face over him as several spells freed him and warmed him up. Gregory, a hard look on his red face, burst down the stairs followed by Padma Patil, wand out. A second later, Colin Creevey came. Gregory helped him up, then handed him his wand. Draco pulled himself into the chair, not really listening to any of the questions or comments. Potter was saying something about contacting the Headmistress.

"You can't, Harry," Draco said, "You know you can't. No! You handled your bullying yourself."

"General," said Padma, reaching out and touching his still wet sleeve, "this isn't just bullying. All the upper classman, in the common room, you know what they were doing this morning? Casting Aquamenti and Frigidero. To put out the fire, they said."

Draco realized the implication. Any inspection of wands will hide the culprits. A show of solidarity, against me. Draco took his wand and dried himself, fixed his clothes, hid his bruises. .

"I suppose I should lose," he said calmly. "There's too many of them and they are unified, apparently. They aren't playing by any rules. It's the smart play." Draco, who spent last night remembering the false memory of his near death, felt his blood run cold. "I suppose I should." Draco made his decision and quickly went up the stairs, taking them two at a time, as Harry shouted after him. Gregory ran behind him, whispering in his ear.

"Calm down. Don't do anything rash. We can handle them, if you think about it. We've been doing well, we just misjudged. We've got allies, we need to figure what to do." Gregory's words ended when they made it to the public area, the common room full of laughing upper class students who smiled and waved, overly amiable. Padma hadn't exaggerated much, if at all.

Harry Potter came up the stairs just in time to see Draco, face composed, walking back into the common room with Gregory by his side. Gregory's wand was out, as was Draco's. Draco's left hand held his cane, he tapped it slightly along the ground as he walked.

Harry reached for his wand. Padma, seeing Harry's motion, drew hers as well. Draco walked over to a large upperclassman. The room hadn't gotten quiet, students still chuckled as Draco stopped in front of MacNair, sitting in a plush chair.

Draco's right hand came up and pointed his wand at the boy, who gave a bemused smile and said with mock indignation "Why Malfoy, what has gotten..." Draco brought down the cane hard against the floor.

With a loud crack, Draco Malfoy and Michael MacNair disappeared from the Slytherin Common Room.

In the white haze MacNair reached for his wand and Draco lifted up his cane, shoving the head against the older boy's cheek. Michael gave a start as he realized the snake head was hissing, fangs bared.

"Do you know, Michael, we keep a Krait at Malfoy Manor. It's the symbol of my house, but don't you think that's carrying it a bit far? Who keeps a deadly snake as a pet? Around small children? Why would you do that? I never really considered it until I got this. I wouldn't reach for your wand." Draco moved the cane up slightly, and now the fangs dominated Michael's view, a scant inch from his eye.

Michael's hand slowly slipped out of the robes. Draco lowered his cane, slightly.

"I honestly have no idea if you were the ringleader behind that stunt, a participant, or just found it amusing. I had plenty of time to think about it, but I don't particularly care. If I get attacked by anyone in the future, I'm blaming you. It's nothing personal, but you're one of the oldest and strongest. Innocent or not, if I ruin your life everyone will think twice. Even if it costs me detention, expulsion or worse. The way I see it, if my life becomes a horror I may as well deserve it."

Draco could feel the strain of keeping them isolated draining him. Michael started to say something, but Draco didn't have time to make this a conversation.

"So if I get attacked by masked Slytherins I'm blaming you and we discover just how many friends are willing to avenge you. Well, I find out. You should probably keep that to yourself if you have enemies. I'd hate to encourage someone who hates us both."

"You just publicly attacked me," said Michael, who had found his voice.

"That just makes it interesting," said Draco, then added a sneer to his voice. "Just imagine, I'd be the first Malfoy to publicly get away with a crime everyone knew he committed." He dropped his voice back to normal. "And are you really just going to admit that I got the better of you in here?" The snake slowly retracted its fangs, closed its mouth and returned to its original form. Draco cracked the cane against the ground, and the Slytherin commons jumped back into view.

Draco turned and walked back to his room, ignoring Harry Potter's questions, while a visibly shaken MacNair settled back into his seat.

"What do you think that's supposed to accomplish?" asked Harry, when they were back in their room. Draco carefully set his cane back on his desk.

"Well, I doubt anyone will attack Gregory again, even if they attack me. That's got to count for something."

"Look, we're in this together," said Gregory

"You can't just threaten," said Harry over him, then they both stopped. Draco's eyes shifted between them, and he realized that Padma had started to follow them in, but had stopped in the doorway. He waved her in. Colin Creevey, thankfully, was nowhere to be seen.

"Did I threaten anyone?" said Draco. "Did you see me threaten anyone? MacNair won't say anything. That's not how things work."

"Yes, just like we are always safe in our dorm," said Gregory. "I don't think we can rely on that anymore. I'm not saying it was a bad move, whatever you did."

"You escalated," said Harry. "But I understand. I've done my share of things that weren't smart."

"Just because it isn't the smart play," said Draco, "doesn't mean it was wrong."

Padma let out a sigh. "What can we do to help?"

Author's Note - Lucius's Quote is actually by La Rochefoucauld.

Chapter 20: Acting Headmistress

"Always remember: others may hate you, but those who hate you don't win unless you hate them, and then you destroy yourself." - Lucius Malfoy

(Acting) Headmistress McGonagall looked down at the young Malfoy boy sitting opposite her desk. He'd gawked at the various devices scattered around the room, which was only natural. She'd done the same when she'd first been in the office as a student, and during her interview. It had taken years to get used to their strange presence. McGonagall spent an hour every day during the summer investigating them, to no avail. Every item had an obvious purpose or was totally inscrutable. From the dial with eight hands, to a small bulb that changed colors imperceptibly slowly and smelled of oranges, to weirdly shaped thing that vrooped once every few weeks, Minerva had no idea what they did. Worse, she'd begun to suspect that her very desk was more in- than -scrutable. She'd appreciated the sherry that had turned up in the lower left drawer the second night of school, but it certainly hadn't been there that morning.

Draco Malfoy had gawked.

But unlike other children summoned to the office - she still thought of it as Dumbledore's office - Draco Malfoy didn't glance around worriedly. He didn't tremble, or sweat, or reveal any nervousness. She'd left him sitting there because that's what you did to children summoned to the office, checking in a mirror to make sure you looked every inch the Headmistress. But when she'd swept into the room and sat down Draco wasn't examining the room to avoid her piercing stare - he'd already made eye contact, held it for a beat, then released it.

Draco's examination expressed polite interest in his surroundings, and no fixation. As soon as she spoke, Draco focused on her again.

"Mr. Malfoy," she said, "I was going to assure you that you were not in trouble, but seeing as how you need no such assurance I will simply ask what exactly happened last night."

"A group of older students thought it would be fun to kidnap me from my room. They stunned Gregory, dragged me out, paralyzed me, and left me down in the dungeons for the night, after dousing me with water and lowering the temperature." Draco's voice held no bitterness, she noted. The reports described Draco calmly composing himself before returning to the Commons and and disappearing with Michael MacNair.

"And how, pray tell, did they get past Mr. Potter as well." It wasn't really relevant, but Minerva had been dying to know. Harry dealt with bullies handily enough last year, she found it amazing that they could have gotten past him so handily.

"Oh, he slept through the whole thing." Draco's voice took on a slightly nasal tone, just for a word or two, and then returned to normal. But he did smirk, some private joke. "Harry can sleep through anything."

"And as to what happened this morning?"

"For which I am assuredly not in trouble," Draco said, making it sound like a statement instead of a question. "I decided that I would have some words with Michael MacNair. I suspect he knows the ringleader, if it isn't actually him. Obviously it had to be a private conversation, to be effective. He couldn't very well tell me the culprit in public. But he chose not to reveal that information."

The annoying thing, Minerva thought, was that it could all be true. If only Draco had flown off into a rage and attacked someone she would have understood. But he seemed so calm and had enough ready answers that she felt her anger slowly rising. She tried to keep it from her voice.

"And did you threaten Mr. MacNair?"

"I let him know that I considered him culpable, and that he should use his considerable influence to handle the situation. Did he say that I threatened him?" Draco sounded mildly intrigued by the thought, and Minerva had to clamp down to keep her anger in check.

"Mr. Malfoy. I rather like you, despite your Father. As Deputy Headmistress I would have never dared say that. But as Acting Headmistress... I find I shouldn't behave the same way." She paused and tried to gather her words, arrange them correctly. "Right now the family resemblance is striking. But you don't remind me of the first or second year Lucius Malfoy, a charming lad like yourself. Now you look like a smaller version of the cold, calculating seventh year that I despaired of redeeming."

Draco's voice took on a hint of sadness. "Last May I knew that I would be Lord Malfoy some day, but that was the distant future, too far away to imagine. It didn't affect my thinking much. Having it suddenly thrust upon me, at such cost...I suppose it has," Draco's voice trailed off.

"Still, I think you should hold onto our childhood for as long as you can. If there is anything I can do to help." She saw Draco's eyes flash, but he just shook his head. She sighed. "Well then, about your cane."

"Yes, Headmistress?"

"There is some concern that a student as young as yourself should not have such a powerful device."

"Openly, you mean." A small twitch of disapproval escaped before she clamped down on her reaction. Draco continued, "Hermione has the good sense to leave her Phoenix in her dorm. That sort of thing. But I haven't taken my Sigil to classes."

"Nevertheless, Mr. Malfoy, You must send it home."

Draco considered for several seconds. "That cane ... what I did, provides everyone a convenient excuse to leave me alone. They can't back down from someone so young. Just like the bullies couldn't back down from S.P.H.E.W. last year. They have to escalate against me, but against something scary and unknown? Against the symbol of my house? They can all quietly agree to let the matter drop and give up the fight without losing face. Without relying on your office or Harry Potter or anyone else."

"Professor Slughorn is certainly capable of controlling his house," she said with more conviction than she felt, and resolved to have a long discussion with Horace about what had been going on in Slytherin.

"Not like Professor Snape," said Draco. "He needs more time, and I need time."

McGonagall considered this. "If all you need is a symbol, I don't see a problem with that." She opened up a drawer and started pulling out a surprising array of objects, shoving others aside, and them mumbling to herself before finally revealing what looked like a beater's club, but slightly longer and flatter. The Headmistress took out her wand and waved it over the club, and it shifted in form to the size of Draco's cane. A few more swipes of the wand and the two objects appeared identical, although the Headmistress could feel the difference, the power in the original cane.

"I will keep your cane here for the time being, or you can have it sent home. This," she said, handing him the Transfigured club, "should work admirably as your replacement. I advise against trying to transfigure anything for so long, Mr. Malfoy. I doubt someone so young could handle the strain, and this club has certain enchantments that will allow me to maintain it at a distance until Christmas break."

Draco took the cane, judging it's heft. He nodded, sadly, while the Headmistress continued. "If you need to beat someone over the head with it in the heat of the moment I will take into consideration the fact that I removed a more subtle option. I should give you detention, you realize, for your comments," she sighed, "and I most certainly would except for the fact that it would encourage your tormentors. You may go."

Draco got up to take his leave when she added, "I do want you to know that I regret what I said about your Father at Hermione's trial. I meant it, but it was in a moment of extreme stress and I certainly did not consider that it might reach your ears. I wish you to be the delightful child I remember instead of the man he became. If not forever then for as long as possible. You may go."

Draco, who had frozen during her speech, made a small bow. "I understand. Thank you, Headmistress," he said, turning to leave.

"Acting Headmistress, Mr. Malfoy," she automatically corrected.

"Acting Mr. Malfoy, Headmistress," he replied sadly as he walked out the door.

Author's Note - Lucius Malfoy's quote was also said by former U.S. president and honorary Slytherin Richard Nixon.

Chapter 23: Correspondence, Pt 2

Do not mistake hesitation for caution. - Lucius Malfoy

Draco sat carefully at his desk, it was dark, so he took out his wand and cast Lumos once, carefully placing his wand so the light didn't wake Gregory. Draco had spent the last few days thinking about his encounter with the vision of Dumbledore. Had it been real or a false memory? Right now he wasn't sure, but he could at least verify or falsify what he'd learned. After a minute in the dim light Gregory still snored gently, so Draco opened his diary and started writing.

Falsifiable predictions made by Albus Dumbledore (?) on Harry Potter Day:

Voldemort's original name is Tom Riddle

Voldemort possessed Professor Quirrell

Voldemort killed Nicolas Flamel

Draco paused, then rubbed his thumb along the last line, which disappeared from the journal. Draco already knew Flamel had been murdered that night, so it didn't count as an advance prediction. In any case he had no way to investigate a complex, months old, distant murder.

Draco considered what else he'd heard. He started to write Harry Potter is, in some way, Voldemort. But that didn't count as an advanced prediction either. Everyone already wondered that. That thought had consumed Draco for months, and yet he didn't feel any distrust towards Harry. Concern, perhaps, but not distrust.

Was there some way to make a more specific prediction about Harry? Something bolder? Dumbledore had said "All of Tom Riddle's icy brilliance," the phrase stuck in Draco's mind. Draco chewed in his quill and thumbed through the transcript he'd written after waking up. Now he wasn't looking at what Dumbledore said, so much as what he implied.

Harry Potter arrived on the scene in a way that surprised Dumbeldore, but not Voldemort.

Draco remembered the final moment, where Dumbledore realized he'd lost and thrown away his long wand and the much shorter dark stone rod, instantly recognizable to all members of the Wizengamot and, in some cases, their heirs.

Albus Dumbledore was trapped in an elegant device (a mirror?) like the one I saw.

The Headmistress had said he was lost in time, and seeing him repeat like that mattered, but she hadn't mentioned a mirror. So that counted as something new.

Dumbledore threw away his wand and the Line of Merlin Unbroken

Which raised the question: Where did Amelia Bones find it?

Draco sighed, even if he managed to verify this information the memory still could be false or planted, but at least it would have been planted by someone who knew something approaching the truth. In plays investigations only took a few hours. Real life seemed so … messy, especially after last year's attempted murder and the last few months, Draco realized. Draco picked up his quill.

To do – Figure out how to prevent false memories, or if my memory is tampered with.

Draco paused, and then the letters wrote on their own.

I do not believe that memory is false.

Draco stared at the page, then quickly scribbled Why not?

Because I keep your secrets

Draco wrote further questions, but the words did not change, and his questions stay unanswered.

To: Gringotts Bank

From: Draco Malfoy, son of Lucius son of Abraxis Lords of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy, son also of Narcissa daughter of Druella Lady of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Black, scion and heir of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy:

As is well documented, both in journalistic accounts such as in the Daily Prophet and by the official investigation conducted by D.M.L.E. (now Chief Warlock) Amelia Bones: my Father Lucius Malfoy, formerly Lord of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy, died at the hands of Lord Voldemort sometime during the night of June 13th or morning of June 14th, 1992.

As is also well documented, Lucius Malfoy's late wife, Narcissa Malfoy, Lady of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy, did not appear before the Wizengamot until June 19th. Before that time she was legally dead.

This fact is also not in dispute.

Narcissa Malfoy's death was not in doubt to Lucius Malfoy at the time of his death, as the revisions to his Will from over a decade ago make clear. Lucius Malfoy made provisions for myself in case of his death and no mention was made of his late wife. While I am not fully of age, the facts and the law are clear: Narcissa Malfoy is not my legal guardian, nor I her ward, and while I do have reduced rights (due to my age) over my vault, she has none.

Therefore, in accordance with the Last Will and Testament of Lucius Malfoy (&c &c), of the Most Noble and Ancient House of Malfoy, I, Draco Malfoy (&c &c) do instruct Gringotts bank that:

First, the Lady Narcissa Malfoy (&c &c) has no claim to any of the wealth currently stored in the Malfoy vault at Gringotts. I wish to receive a personal letter, delivered to Hogwarts, acknowledging that fact.

Second, please continue to allow Lady Malfoy to make any reasonable withdrawls and show all the courtesy to which a customer of Gringotts is due. Reasonable withdrawals shall total no more than 400 Galleons monthly. Please send a copy of all transactions to me at Hogwarts.

Third, Lady Malfoy shall be allowed into the vault, but may not remove any magical artifacts from said vault without my prior approval. Non-magical trinkets and all ladies jewelry is pre-approved, and I will send a complete list after my inventory, which I will conduct over the Christmas break. Please let me know the days & hours that Griphook would be available to assist.

You will receive an Owl from my solicitor, confirming this instruction and requesting copies of all relevant correspondence.

Draco Malfoy, Heir and Acting Lord of House Malfoy.

Draco read over the letter, checking his wording from the template his solicitor had provided, then sealed it, and placed it on his desk.

He didn't wake up Tanuxa, she'd get to it later, after her morning hunt.

Draco, Gregory and Harry were walking back from another session of the Bayesian Conspiracy when Harry, feet automatically moving him back to his room, woke up from his reverie and ask "Draco, How long is a good plot? I mean, a good plot should be short, but what's the longest that a good plot has lasted?"

Gregory just shook his head. He'd gotten used to the odd questions that Harry sometimes asked, but that didn't make them any less odd.

"You aren't just counting feuds are you? Those can last centuries, but aren't really plots. As you point out, shorter is usually better. Some plans just take time to come to fruition, you can't grow a plant any faster than it grows, so if you need a branch off a hundred year old oak planted on a full moon then you have to wait a hundred years. Some plots just take time."

"I'm not counting that," said Harry, "I'm talking about a long term strategy that requires active planning and modification."

Draco thought about it.

"Well, dynastic maneuvering lasts generations, and never really ends. Just the Noble Houses fighting for position."

"No, I'm not counting that either. That's a zero-sum social game. I'm talking about something with a beginning, middle and end."

"OK, I can think of several that stretch out a decade. Maybe two. Typically any play based on history will cover a plot that long, but those are probably embellished. Mellar's plans before he even arrived at Castle Black are rumored to have taken well over a century, but that story predates Merlin and supposedly all of the participants were a thousand years old. And he got thwarted anyway. It's tough to plot out a century, how could he know someone who was barely fifty would intervene? So, discounting that," Draco chewed on his lip for a second,"I'd put the upper limit at maybe twenty five years. For serious plots, not career climbing or dynasty. Even twenty years is rare. Pretty much any good plot of that length becomes a play, although I suppose it's just barely possible that someone pulled off something better without ever bragging, even on their deathbed."

"That makes sense," Harry said, "Professor Asimov has one of his stories about a plotter who can predict the future and plans out thousands of years, but it's just a story, and even then he has people actively modifying it after he dies. I think he has a line 'To succeed, planning is not sufficient, one must improvise as well.' I had given a range of ten to thirty years, so it's good that your number matches with mine."

"Why do you ask," Gregory piped in.

"Oh, I was just wondering what the record was," said Harry.

Chapter 24: Asymmetric Warfare, Pt 3

"People do not despise others for their vices, they despise those who lack virtues." - Lucius Malfoy

Professor Slughorn, slathering jam liberally across a piece of toast, turned to Adjunct Professor Lockhart and said "You know if you do this, things could get ugly." Slughorn then slid the toast into his mouth, grabbing a croissant

Professor Asimov, sitting on Slughorn's left, fiddled with his strawberries and cream. He'd tried to eat healthier since rejuvenation and didn't want to get fat, not with long decades stretched out in front of him and a vividly compelling counter-example sitting beside him. He stared at Draco Malfoy, nibbling on his breakfast and talking with several Slytherins at once.

"You don't think they'd attack him in public like that, do you?" Isaac said, putting down his spoon and greedily eying the pastries.

"If things turn ugly it will be due to your meddling, Horace. I don't imagine they would," said Professor Lockhart, cutting into a sausage, "I mean, that doesn't seem clever. Practically every teacher will be watching."

"Oh," chuckled Professor Slughorn, "that's the thing about cleverness. A plan some quivering Hufflepuff considers clever would seem terrible to a smart Ravenclaw. Then a bold Slytherin pulls it off. So, was it a clever plan? Should our Hufflepuff try it? Of course not, he'd muck it up." Horace had used his fork to stab a piece of sausage and waved it like a baton, swinging it towards the various Houses tables at the appropriate point in his discussion. Now he took a bite, then continued.

"But the Ravenclaw wasn't correct, either. A plan can be clever and not clever at the same time. Hufflepuffs and Gryffindors never deal with ambiguity like that. Loyalty and Bravery aren't mercurial and fluid. Cleverness and ambition wax and wane like the moon. Shirkers think that too many witnesses makes a flawed plan, ambitious students see an opportunity. I mean, you can't watch everyone while judging a battle, can you Gilderoy?"

Professor Asimov leaned across, "You … you're prodding them into it, aren't you? Plotting against your own students!" Slughorn chuckled and reached for a danish. He liked the little cheese ones best.

"Isaac," said Professor Lockhart cautiously, "Well, you are right of course, but that's how these things are done. I may have issues with his methods, but Horace's ... meddling produced a slew of immensely talented individuals over the decades. But exactly who are you promoting, Horace? Malfoy doesn't join your little chats, but Zabini does."

"I have a wide variety of interests," sniffed Professor Slughorn, "and I'll ruefully admit that my methods are blunter than usual, but you have no idea the mess I inherited from Severus. I'm hoping to limit the damage to several expulsions, personally."

"Expulsions?" said Professor Asimov, "You are angling to get your students expelled? That seems drastic."

"We can't all be good students, Isaac," said Professor Lockhart, "I might have turned out better if I'd gotten a shock like that at fifteen. Not that I did anything worthy of expulsion, mind you."

"Oh, if you had been in my house, you would have," chuckled Horace Slughorn, stretching his arms out and patting both his colleagues jovially on the back, "but I think you've turned out well enough in your own time. Looking back over my history, I played it a bit too close to my chest at times. Perhaps last year could have been avoided, if I'd trusted my judgment a few decades earlier."

"You … you taught Voldemort," said Professor Asimov too loudly, then looked out over the House tables. Professor Lockhart saw his glance. But the assembled students kept up their chatter without pause. Professor Asimov remembered what he'd been told, magic kept students from overhearing anything said at the teacher's table unless a Professor specifically addressed the students.

"Don't worry, we all do that a few times. That's why we have the spell," said Gilderoy.

"I don't know that," said Professor Slughorn, dropping the remaining half of his Danish and shoving his plate away. "No. I do know that, but I didn't admit it to myself. I'm not certain, but it all adds up. My greatest mistake. That boy had such potential I blinded myself to his danger, told myself that no mere teenager could outwit me. If he'd been expelled he might have turned out just as poorly, but at least my hands would be clean. He might have very well lashed out right away, limiting the damage. No ... I think things would have turned out better if there had been a few more expulsions in the past. Maybe, one every few years, perhaps ... one or two? Yes. Two expulsions."

Isaac had just picked up his spoon and taken another tentative bite of his strawberries and cream when Horace added "Or one murder, I suppose."

The Howler exploded as dawn broke besides the lake, the last wisps of moonlight glittering off the surface, turning the morning fog silver. The howler ripped open along the edges, noise pulsing outwards, screaming "Good morning Slytherins" loudly, with an elongated drawl. Nobody in the dungeons heard, of course.

Startled by the howler, Draco whipped awake, wand out, sitting up so quickly that he tumbled out of a small green cot onto the dew-laden grass. Gregory's face appeared as he leaned over his edge of his cot. They glanced at each other and heard the rest of the shouts and exclamations as the Slytherins woke up.

"How did we get out here," "What's going on," "Fifteen more minutes, just fifteen..." "Why are we by the lake," the murmuring grew into conversations into shouted accustaions until finally a second howler appeared overhead. This one opened slowly and deliberately. It didn't scream, but the voice carried well over the lake shore, echoing slightly.

"Good morning, my young apprentices," Professor Lockhart's voice boomed across the lake, "As I mentioned in our last class, today the N.E.W.T. armies, along with some selected fourth years, are conducting battlefield exercises. I promised you an exciting spectacle. What I may have neglected to mention is that in any real war there are civilian populations. You can define civilian in any number of interesting ways I suppose, but I define it as people who don't particularly care about the outcome of the battle. It most certainly doesn't mean non-combatant."

Draco looked across the group, boys from the first four years. A mere hundred yards along the shore he spotted another cluster of cots and a blinking and stretching coterie of Slytherin witches. Two mermen poked their heads above the lake, stared at the Howler and assembled students, then disappeared underneath the still water. Scanning the crowd, Draco accounted for every healthy Slytherin of third year or below, except Harry Potter.

That didn't surprise Draco.

"War can come at any time, often you only have the vaguest of hints and little time to prepare. In short, wars inevitably lead to refugees, simulated today by my younger students. All younger students have been transported onto the battlefield for the duration of the battle, although each house has has been put into a different area. Because this simulates a sudden evacuation, we only transported the items you slept with – although clothes were provided in a few cases. Large capacity items, such as mokeskin bags, are still in your rooms. If you proclaim that you would have taken it with you, well, you may be right. But often refugees find that someone stronger may steal what you have saved."

At this, a large groan and several students started crying, Draco had started sleeping with his wand after the night he'd been abducted. A quick pat of his robes revealed that his mokeskin pouch didn't get transported with him. However, he felt the reassuring bump of his pocket flask next to his heart. Draco raised an eyebrow at Gregory. Gregory flashed his wand, gripped tightly in his hand. That made two.

"Refugees, as a rule, have a single goal. Survival. But I'll concede that watching this battle is more fun that being a refugee, which means my more clever students would be tempted to get themselves killed, have breakfast, and enjoy the show. To help align our incentives anyone killed before sundown tonight will have detention for the rest of the weekend. Those restrooms do clean themselves, but they can always use some extra shine! But this wouldn't be interesting for our N.E.W.T. students if every refugee behaved the same, there are always a few idealists interspersed with the displaced masses, people who don't fear death as much as others. Which leads us to my next point..."

The sky, lighter as the sun poked over the water, darkened slightly as a massive fluttering of wings approached carrying the morning mail. Unlike most mornings every student got a letter. Draco didn't recognize the owl, a large woodland brown owl with a cruel beak that landed on the side of his fallen cot. It hooted twice, dropped a letter, and then flew off without even looking. Draco reached over and opened it.

Draco,

Be careful. Some of your Housemates mean you actual harm. Simulated dying is to be much preferred to actual death, and you will receive no detention if you die to avoid real danger. If you need to discuss your situation, I am always willing to help.

G.L.

Draco read the letter quickly. He started to hand it to Gregory, but it burst into flame. Of course, thought Draco, nobody should be able to verify your motivation by some in-game scroll, where's the fun in that? Draco walked over to Blaise Zabini, who saw Draco's wand and shook his head mournfully. Since the upper years were combatants, Draco probably didn't have many enemies in camp. Draco cast Sonorus and addressed the crowd.

"The armies will be here shortly. If you have anything useful, like a wand, let one of the Generals know. Our first order of business is to make sure that any army that comes by has a strong interest in leaving us alone. Do you like scrubbing toilets? No? Then we want to be left alone. First years, gather up any wand shaped twigs. Anyone with a wand, let someone borrow it so they can transfigure the twigs to make them look more like wands."

They wouldn't last long, but most second years could turn twigs into wands and maintain the transfiguration for a while, at least while they held the twigs.

There were brooms overhead. Draco saw two, three, four formations. The fliers coming from the North East veered towards the western group, and spellfire flew between them, red, green and a cone of purple that produced a thunderclap and sent the water rippling. Powerful spells.

"Anyone with a good plan, talk to one of the Generals. Everyone, lets move towards the witches, safety in numbers. Take your cots! They may be useful." Draco canceled his spell, then summoned his patronus, it floated in the air besides him, tongue flicking tentatively.

"Find Neville Longbottom, we'll give him any information we come up with, as long as they do the same. Right now I don't have anything to offer. I'm just a refugee, no special goals." Draco glanced at the broom overhead. All of the armies must know the positions of the underclassman by now, no point in hiding it. "Slytherins are on the lake shore, if he wants to form up."

Draco nodded and his Patronus slithered off. He started jogging towards the witches, pausing only to pick up a twig and start a Transfiguration. As he jogged, he glanced around at roughly half of House Slytherin. Combined on the lake shore, not split into armies.

Modest stakes, for the rest of them. Nobody would be making a serious attempt on Zachary Smith or Blaise Zabini, so they didn't have to worry about that. But nobody relished detention. Draco couldn't convert enemies today, but he could make dozens of friends and solidify some lukewarm allies. All he needed to do was figure out a way to save them all. Draco stumbled again as another spell crackled overhead, sounding like the whimpering of whipped dogs. Draco smiled, reaching into his robe for his flask.

General Wood sat on his broom, hovering a dozen feet above the ground, a safe distance above the assembled Slytherins. They'd built up a barricade of cots. It wouldn't stop any real spells, but it did make it difficult to see who was who, and the gaps fairly bristled with wands pointing at him.

A suspiciously large number of wands, Oliver thought. He pulled his broom up a bit higher, next to Fred Weasley. "What do you think, Fred?"

"Is Potter down there, hiding?" asked Fred.

Oliver shook his head, "I saw him in the bleachers."

"Then it's a bluff," Fred said firmly. "Some real wands, but probably not many." He peered down inside the barricades, and saw the Slytherin generals conferring. "Malfoy's tricky, and not just Slytherin tricky. Potter's rubbed off on him. Me an' George swap ideas with him, and he's good. And you've seen him fight."

Oliver kicked away, and then shouted down to the Slytherins. "PARLAY?" There was a huddle, and several patronus rushed away in all directions. Mist, snake, owl and maybe a sparrow. A shout came back ... "AGREED." Draco Malfoy walked away from the rest of his generals, hands up, no wand showing. After his brief show, he jogged towards a small hill and past it.

Oliver Wood landed the broom just as Draco took a small swig from his flask. "Can you believe they didn't provide us food or water," Draco asked, smacking his lips as he put the flask away. "I choose this hill because for all I know someone in my camp has a grudge against your army, and I don't want to be accused of plotting against you."

"What do you mean someone has a grudge?" Draco just shrugged "Lockhart sent every one of us a letter explaining how he'd judge if we won or lost. Most of us just need to survive, but I have no idea what every letter said. That's true of every camp, by the way."

"You've been in contact with them, then?"

Draco nodded, slowly turning, surveying the scene. The brooms had mostly disappeared, early scouts just getting the lay of the land. Even second years knew the value of good battlefield intelligence. Plans were being made now, but there were still skirmishes when groups encountered each other unexpectedly. Oliver followed Draco's gaze and saw spells coming from the non-forbidden forest, a few trees had caught fire but a small rainstorm appeared overhead to douse the flames.

"We sent word about your offer of parlay, so if you attack us now, the other camps will know they can't trust you. So, what do you want?"

"We need a logistical support and more soldiers," said Oliver.

"And you are offering ..." Draco drew out the question.

"We could just take it. Armies are press-ganging the others as we speak."

"General Wood, I like you, I trust you. But I don't trust your orders. For all I know you drew the Voldemort chit this game and want to murder everyone. And if we do join with you, you'll face the same problem. Someone may have a goal of murdering a General, or aiding your enemy, and I don't even know how many teams there are. So if I made a deal with you, I could only say that most of the people involved won't try to betray you, and some would actively help you. If you want, I'll ask for volunteers and we won't stop anyone who wants to join you."

"That doesn't seem like much," Wood said.

"If you want me to recommend we join up with you, we need real concessions as a show of good faith. We keep our wands, you can execute traitors, but no mass retaliations. Volunteers only for combat missions and our logistical support people get a reasonable sized garrison. And two brooms for us to use"

"Two brooms? Get serious. I could just kidnap you and destroy your group. From what I've seen, that may be better. At least we wouldn't be tied down defending everyone and watching our backs. And it would eliminate a threat."

Draco slowly pushed back his robe to reveal his dueling holster strapped to his left arm and the wand it held. Oliver had his wand out and pointed instantly. Draco pulled out the wand by the tip. He kept the wand pointed at himself, then slowly brought his other hand up and snapped the wand in half.

He dropped two halves of a wand, but only snapped twigs hit the ground.

"Now you can murder me," Draco said, "But kidnapping me is useless, unless you loan me your wand. From my point of view, I win if you murder me. I loaned my wand to someone else, and I'll have an ally in real life if he gets to use it for the rest of the day. You can leave us alone, and rest easy in the knowledge that no other general can use us, or you can try to kill us all."

The fire in the non-forbidden forest grew dimmer, and the rising cloud of steam reflected the morning sunilight. Draco shrugged and started back towards the rest of the Slytherins.

"It probably won't even cost you two of your soldiers. But you'll have lost two," Draco added, "and all those armies will have gained how many?"

Oliver Wood paced, then went back to his broom and kicked off the ground, hovering. This wasn't good at all, but he had to make the most of a bad position. Just his luck, being close to the Slyltherins. He turned back to Malfoy and asked "What do you need the brooms for?"

"Rescuing survivors from other camps and some defensive patrols," said Draco. Oliver thought about it, then took a quick flight to examine the Slytherin contingent and confer with his officers.

"One broom now to Goyle and he flies with us. You get the first broom we capture and any more that Goyle brings down or your people personally scavenge, but he's part of our team."

"Gregory would enjoy that," Draco agreed. "What else?"

"I counted at least three or four patronuses, we add those people to our signal core or combat operations, their choice."

Draco thought about it, "We keep our wands. No trying to figure out which ones are real, and no mass reprisals if there are traitors?"

Wood nodded, "I didn't draw the Voldemort chit. You try to sniff traitors out before they attack. And you take your wand back from whoever you loaned it to and assist as I see fit."

"Put Weasley in charge of the garrison defenses and I can sell that."

"Done," said Oliver as they shook hands, making sure that the brooms overhead as well as the Slytherin camp saw.

Ten minutes later, joint operations began.

Daphne Greengrass suddenly pivoted, shifting her aim. Draco didn't have time to shout, he'd already started casting, swinging his wand towards Daphne and he finished Stupefy right as she did. Daphne fell to the ground suffused by the red glow that indicated a casualty of war. A mere twenty feet off to her right, Oliver Wood lay sprawled on the ground besides his broom, glowing red, victim of Daphne's treachery.

"Dammit," said Penelope Clearwater, "I thought you vouched for her." Penelope's wand pointed at Draco while the rest of the squad, what was left of it, watched. Penelope's free hand brushed away the sweat of the mid-afternoon sun. It wasn't that hot, but they'd been moving and fighting for hours.

"I did vouch for her," Draco said, "and you saw her, she did fine. What can you do when someone hides in your midst for hours? Maybe she had an objective of killing General Wood." Oliver had only joined this squadron in the last half hour, his prior group dead. "This doesn't change the deal. I held up my side as best as I could. And in any case, killing me doesn't help you. " The squadron exchanged glances, shoulders hung low.

Draco didn't know the exact situation, they'd cut him out of a planning, fearing treachery, but he'd sent some messages and seen their army whittled down. Maybe other armies took heavier casualties, but he didn't think so. Draco could read it in the downcast eyes and slouched shoulders. They'd lost – they'd had hope as long as they had General Wood – but it died with him.

They were in an endgame, on the losing side. But chess teaches that sometimes you could sneak out a draw despite being down a few pieces.

Draco looked up at the sun through the trees – through edge of the forest - trying to gauge the time. His stomach growled, they'd barely eaten anything. "I figure we just need to hold out for an hour," he said trying to rally them without sounding bossy, "let's find a place to hole up, ride this out." Penelope had resuscitated Olivier and Daphne, who trudged off the field without a word. (Speaking after you died was unrealistic. Roger Davies tried to impart some crucial information in spite of Professor Quirrell's ban last Spring. Professor Quirrell made sure to take a few minutes from his next lecture showing a recording of Davies on the battlefield, coughing up chicken feathers and making sad gurgling noises in front of his horrified squad mates. Nobody tried to break that rule anymore).

Draco saw the approaching brooms, five of them, with a sinking heart … all older Slytherins. He spotted MacNair's face from beneath the robes. Draco couldn't tell about the others but they'd stripped off any army insignia. No time for a logical decision, Draco acted on instinct. He reached into his robe, took out his flask, and drank the last of the Felix Filicis in several gulps, ignoring the looks.

Draco had maybe two hours of luck.

As the first drop hit his stomach, Draco felt clarity. Some options fell away instantly, Draco knew he couldn't talk his way out of this. But he could see that Penelope and the others would let him go, if he just gave them some hope. Draco ran to the broom, and the others turned their wands to him, but he just shouted "It's an ambush, but they're after me, I'll lead them off." Penelope lowered her wand and the others followed their lead. "Head into the forest, keep low, they can't follow you on brooms anyway." Draco kicked off. He started North, away from the oncoming brooms, but instinct told him to head West, towards the lake and the makeshift refugee camp. At least, that's what it had been this morning. He accelerated as fast as he could, and he heard the shouts.

"After him," came Hestia's screeching voice. Draco didn't bother casting any hexes, there were too many of them. He stayed low to the ground, and sometimes made a quick turn, just a few degrees. Spells kept narrowly missing him but the others were getting closer. He could see the refugee camp ahead, and he aimed to go past it as close as possible. He might have enemies in the camp, but he doubted they'd be able to hit him. But if anyone behind him had an enemy...

After he passed the camp, he veered back, heading directly into the sunset while over Hogwarts lake. None of the people chasing him had been shot down, but they'd been shot at, which gave Draco time. Draco saw brooms ahead, a grueling dogfight. Four brooms, moving faster than he was - even at full speed - but these brooms flew in jagged arcs, suddenly veering and darting. Seekers and Beaters and Chasers, but Draco's instinct said to head straight for them and he did. He elevated, gaining altitude to join the dogfight. One of the brooms glowed red and fell from the sky, splashing into the water, followed a second later by a second splash. Draco heard Gregory's triumphant whoop.

"Incoming," Draco shouted, passing between the other two brooms. Angelina Johnson almost fired at Draco, then turned to her team-mate and shouted "Ignore him." In calmer times Draco may have protested but he didn't feel offended when the two brooms shot off towards his attackers. Draco banked hard left, heading back towards land.

"So, what's up," Gregory asked casually. Draco looked over his shoulder and Gregory was there, slightly above and just behind him, robe pulled up over his face to keep the brunt of the wind out of his eyes. Draco pulled his own robe up to cover his face, then glanced back over his shoulder, the brooms behind them made complicated patterns, a furball of maneuvers and spells.

"It's MacNair and Hestia and the others, after me," Draco said.

"If we go around the forbidden forest we can make it to the spectator stands," Gregory answered.

"It's faster if we go over," Draco said. "Well over. We need at least twenty feet clearance." Draco glanced behind them, the brooms were catching up. Why did Oliver Wood own such a terrible broom if he played Quidditch? If he'd been alive, Father would surely have bought him a Nimbus 2001 by now. If he'd been alive. Draco ignored the thought.

"If we go that high we'll be easy to track," Gregory said. "They just took down the other two, but there are only three following us now."

"We've got time, I can feel it." Draco felt drawn towards the forest, he just knew that he should head into the forest. Given his luck so far, he didn't question his instinct to go there. Draco gained altitude again, broom not even slowing.

Gregory said, "Warn me if you break," then moved in closer, put his hand out, fingers brushing Draco's broom. Gregory turned his head, looking over his shoulder and took a long look, letting Draco's broom guide him.

"They're back and climbing. Maybe in spell range in a minute. Someone's pursuing them, but too far back to matter."

Draco nudged his broom up slightly. Gregory rose with him, while Draco explained "There's some webbing in the trees and a mist over the forest, twenty feet isn't enough."

"Webs?" Gregory said, worried, but didn't look forward. They passed over the boundary of the forbidden forest and Gregory spotted the webs behind them. "Another broom just kicked up, eight o'clock. Coming fast."

"Break right on three, take any shots, into the mist. I'll break left. Meet you near the stands but stay in bounds," said Draco. Gregory started to protest but Draco just said "Trust me! One, two, three!"

Gregory whipped his head forward on two and ducked under Draco, turned hard, but Draco's foot grazed the edge of his hood and knocked it back as Gregory climbed towards the mist. Gregory – realizing that they'd all follow Draco now that they could tell them apart - started to dive and ignore the orders, but there were webs everywhere and he climbed up and disappeared into the mist, having to take his time to circle back safely.

Draco dived low, knees brushing the treeline. He weaved between webs thick enough to hide him, narrowly dodging the sticky tendrils. The brooms behind him had to slow down to navigate, their speed advantage wasted. Draco felt a pull, lower felt safer and if he stayed visible Gregory would find him and risk himself. Draco dropped below the treeline, moving slowly. Branches scratched his face, light peeked through in small beams. He heard a muffled whumf behind him, and branches shook.

The screaming sounded like Hestia.

Draco quickly dropped to the ground. He wasn't sure, but he felt like he had maybe a quarter of a mile to the edge of the forest. The forest was thick here, he doubted anyone could spot him unless they moved. Draco heard a scuttling, and his instinct told him to veer right, so he did, confidently walking a mere foot past the triffid.

Vines quickly entangled his arm and jerked him ten feet into the air. Draco felt the sharp searing pain as foot long thorns ripped into his shoulder, piercing straight through and grinding hard against his bones.

There was a flash and Draco heard someone shout his name and then heard nothing.

Author's Note - Lucius' quote is (again) by La Rochefoucauld.

The next chapter will be published in two weeks.

A note on the Hot Hand discussion from earlier. Science marches on! See /2015/07/09/hey-guess-what-there-really-is-a-hot-hand/

Chapter 25: Security Conscious, Pt 1

"Security means imposing costs on your friends to inflict a much greater cost on your foes. To make something perfectly secure means rendering it useless." - Lucius Malfoy

Draco screamed as thorns ripped into his arm and shoulder. Hermione was running towards him, shouting, her Phoenix launching off her shoulder, beak opened in a wordless scream. The vines around him writhed, engulfing him. He dangled sideways a dozen feet above the ground and then there was a snapping and his arm was at the base of the tree, roots move and pulling his fingers slowly towards a grotesque maw...

Draco woke up groaning, remembering the pain, the pulling and snapping. He lifted his left arm and felt it move but the sheet covering him didn't raise, just bulged beneath his shoulder. His left arm tingled - Draco felt it tingle - but didn't seem to work. Draco opened his eyes - the brightness shocked him for a second - but he focused and made out the row of beds opposite him and the small table beside him. Draco shuffled his feet and the sheet pulled down from his chest and he saw the bandages on his shoulder, the stump that ended several inches lower. His arm was gone. Draco sucked in air. He wanted to cry out but it didn't hurt.

He remembered Hermione's shout, and the fluttering of wings. Mostly, he remembered the pain.

Draco looked around with a start and realized he wasn't in Hogwarts, but in Peverell. He recognized the rows of beds and the Aurors posted at the emergency entrance, he heard the primary Thief's Downfall splash in the distance, and the secondary Downfall activate nearby. The sun shone directly down through the skylight (too small for a man to fit through and loaded with traps for anything smaller) not much time had passed, or several days perhaps.

A shadow appeared over Draco and his eyes tried to adjust as he blinked them a few times.

"Eh, this better not be one of your tests, lad. I've got my eye on you." Draco focused on the brilliant blue eye swiveling around, then quickly snapped his eyes shut.

Alastor Moody hadn't bent over to look at Draco, he kept his head up and wand out. He didn't bother looking down at Draco, just spoke a bit louder so he could be heard as he slowly circled in one spot.

"I don't think I'd give up my arm just to help you," Draco said. He heard Moody chuckle then move away. Draco cautiously opened his eyes and saw Moody across the room, inspecting other patients.

Orderlies moved around the patients, comforting them, getting them water, preparing to move them. Draco recognized some of them, the middle aged nurse with the small ash wand that liked Chocolate Frogs. The intern studying Healing who practiced his scowl but screamed like a girl when Draco offered Weird Sisters tickets. Draco had learned quickly enough that everyone who worked at Peverell took bribes, but didn't stay bribed. Not about anything important, anyway. Even for his tests. Every five minutes or so the orderlies moved a patient out. Some of them groaned, but the room felt pleasant as it always had.

Nobody here complained or despaired, like in a regular hospital.

"Well, now, giving up an arm wouldn't stop some people," said Moody, stomping around the room. "Do you think I complained about losing my eye? My foot? Anyway, that was the past. Now you aren't losing an arm, so much as misplacing it for a few hours. Barely an inconvenience at all." Draco remembered the grinding in his shoulder socket, the tearing and pulling as his arm ripped off, but decided not to press the point. Draco watched an orderly giving water and noticed Moody's eye lingering on that particular orderly. The young man looked to be about thirty, and had hair nearly as blond as Draco's own, although with a wild unkempt look. He was simply going from person to person, giving them water and barely talking. Moody's wand covered the room in intervals, but seemed to pause on that orderly, as if desperate to cast. Draco felt a strong urge to talk to that orderly, there was something about him, and that's when Draco realized He felt the liquid luck still racing through his system.

Shouldn't it have worn off by now? Maybe it didn't get used up if you were unconscious. Hey may have only been out for half an hour, for all Draco knew. People probably didn't get knocked out and lose an arm when they used it, before. Losing an arm seemed unlucky. But misplacing it for a few hours? That could work.

Draco coughed and asked "Could I get some water?" He waved at the orderly, dressed in simple grey robes. Coupled with his pale skin and blue eyes, people might think he was Draco's cousin. The man came over and handed Draco a cup, and water wordlessly appeared. Draco propped himself up so that he was sitting, then drank deeply.

Nearly dying is thirsty business.

"How do you stop wandless magic in here, anyway?" Draco asked Moody, who just gave a barking laugh and left, muttering to himself. The orderly's eyes followed Moody's departure closely, then he turned back to take the glass and his eyes widened with shock. He sat down next to Draco.

"I have seen you here before. You are a student, helping perfect security. What happened to your arm?" Draco caught the accent and started wondering if there was some branch of the family in Germany, because Draco knew he'd seen a portrait of this man somewhere. Possibly in a cousin's house? A formal sitting portrait, perhaps. The orderly had been older, had lines on his face and greying hair, but still the same piercing blue eyes. But age didn't mean much, if you worked in Peverell.

"Yes," Draco put down the cup and held out his hand. "Draco Malfoy. I stumbled onto a Triffid, I think."

"Ah, A Malfoy. I met an Abraxas Malfoy let's see, fifty six years ago I believe. Gellert Grindelwald." He shook Draco's remaining hand firmly.

Draco felt too stunned to say anything other than "Abraxas was my grandfather."

"Was? I am sorry."

"Thank you. Dragon Pox, two years ago. At the time, it seemed like a natural thing. We all said it was simply his time, so it didn't seem like a tragedy. Of course now," Draco started to widely gesture towards the room that he knew contained the Chalice, but he was trying to use his left hand. They were moving another patient, a wizard who looked to be pushing one-fifty and had exceedingly long hairs coming out of his ears. Draco pointed with his right hand and shrugged.

"Yes, now we live in the Age of Wonder. I find myself shocked to be witnessing it." Gellert spoke with the formality of a bygone age, and seemed patient with long pauses.

"I wonder about that as well. I don't suppose you can tell me - for my security research - why they trust you? I mean, clearly Mad-Eye Moody does not trust you." Draco reached for his glass of water, which Gellert refilled and handed to him.

"I cannot tell you about security. Of course I am under an Unbreakable Vow, as are most around here, although mine was ... more extensive than usual. But even if I were free from compulsion, I would not tell you. It is not that prison reformed me - although the toll of the years does weigh heavy - just that I now have a chance to actually help the greater good, and that is better than dying in prison. So I agree with those who offer my parole; they need me, or people like me. I give my word and after the vow they trust me. Except for Alastor Moody, he thinks I may have some way to defeat the Vow. That I may have devised such a scheme in Nurmengard." He paused to refill Draco's cup.

"But they just have you as an orderly! That doesn't make sense. You could do anything to help them."

"I do this because I wish it. My job takes little time, and I do not wish to spend the remaining time alone in my room. I have not spoken with many people, and those who I offer water think me a kind young man, until the staff tells them. Only the truly young, such as yourself, do not react with horror. You have read about it in books, yes? But they lived it. They hate me for what I did. And the Aurors and staff, they are like this as well."

"So, in your spare time you comfort the wounded, and you'll be stuck here for the rest of your life? I suppose that's better than isolation in prison..."

"No, no. Once my magic weakens enough, I will be released. I have taken one vow, but have bound so many others."

"They won't turn you into a Muggle, will they?" Draco didn't hide his horror. Draco no longer hated Muggles, but the thought of his own magic draining terrified him. Seemed unnatural. He supposed it was better than life in prison, but it would be like losing an arm. Permanently losing an arm.

"No, I suppose I will be as powerful as a seventh year. Perhaps weaker, but I will have the knowledge to compensate. They are bringing in another batch of recruits for security and once I bind them I suspect I will be free to go. Time served, as you say."

"What will you do? You should teach!" As soon as Draco said it he realized it would never fly. He considered other options. They would have to be appealing to Grindelwald, a proud man although one apparently not so proud as the youth in history books.

"You are too kind, but Durmstrang expelled me. They would not offer me a position. I am an embarrassment to them. I will certainly get no offers from another school, but I will find something."

"Would you consider tutoring me, over the holidays? I couldn't afford this full time, but just for a month I suspect I could."

"I doubt your family would want to be associated with this. What would your parents say?"

"I would have to talk to Mother, but I've typically had the best tutors, although nothing like you. And it would just be a few hours a day. We could spend some time trying to find you a suitable career. My family still has connections, although less so than after Voldemort's defeat. You'd have better luck in London than Europe."

"I was planning on going to the Americas - where memories are short - but I will consider your idea. It is not without merit."

At this point a Doctor – Draco struggled for a moment and came up with Zharkov, but didn't think he knew the first name. Doctor Zharkov sported a neatly trimmed brown beard speckled with gray and wore the red robes that Peverell had instituted for medical staff. "There are other patients, Gellert. Draco, it's time to fix up your arm. I'll just need to put you to sleep for the procedure." Draco knew patients were always unconscious when they went through healing, just to keep the details hidden. The doctor pulled out his wand.

Draco placed the cup on the table and slid back down into the bed. Gellert said his goodbye and stood up, barely brushing the doctors arm as he cast Somnum! But the slight touch sent the spell into the sheets next to Draco, barely missing him.

Draco, realizing what had just happened, snapped his eyes shut then relaxed.

"Watch what you are doing, Gellert! If it were up to me we would have never let you out!"

"Well, it was up to your superiors, Hans, and they did. Besides, the boy is asleep. You know I cannot interfere. It was an accident. I would not touch you on purpose."

Doctor Zharkov grunted and Draco heard the Levicorpus! And felt himself lifted off the bed and several pairs of hands guide him down the hall and into the medical procedure room. As they passed through the door, the second Thief's Downfall splashed on him, cold, but he'd been expecting it and didn't gasp or react, and it disappeared shortly. (Draco realized months ago that he could mimic the visual effect of the Thief's Downfall with a slightly modified Comed-Tea, but hadn't figured out a use for that tactic). Draco felt himself placed gently and then all the spells on him were dispelled. He could feel his arm itching, but he didn't hear any casting.

Perhaps they cast wordlessly? But why? It required more effort and healing didn't need the element of surprise. Draco let his head slowly loll over to the left side and cracked his left eye barely open. He could see a delicate wand flicking above him, and a wooden mannequin arm being attached. He was lying on a padded table but was actually resting on a stretcher, it seemed. It happened quickly, already the arm up to the elbow looked just like his old arm, perhaps a touch paler. Draco closed his eye and thought about it.

Free Transfiguration was wordless. You envisioned the form. Like every student who ever took Professor McGonagall's course, Draco had memorized the rules for transfiguration and they jumped out at him.

Transfiguration is not permanent!

I will not transfigure any living subject! It will make you sick and possibly dead.

If this were a fixed transformation, they'd say a charm. Draco shoved back his panic. He knew that other people had been cured, so obviously this worked. No doubt healers specialized in this, so there was no need to panic. Peverell had replaced plenty of limbs. After another minute or two he felt Doctor Zharkov lift his arm, massage the muscles, stretch out the fingers.

"OK, that's good. Finish up." He heard the Doctor go back through the downfall and then he felt the poles on either side of him lift up as he was carried (carried?) through a doorway opposite the one he came in. The stretcher was placed gently on another table and Draco risked cracking his eye open, again. The room, the part he could see anyway, looked identical to the previous one in size, but less ornate. One hand placed a stone on Draco's arm. It was small and blood red, perhaps the size of a scarab but irregular, like a sculptor hadn't finished polishing it. Draco didn't feel anything in his arm.

Draco did feel like he'd pressed his luck hard enough. He didn't feel the confidence and presence of Felix Felicis - hadn't felt it for a few minutes - so Draco closed his eyes thirty long seconds before he felt the stone turn slightly on his skin. Draco was sure that nobody else had moved it, he'd heard the orderlies step away from him. But right after it turned he heard Chocolate Frog Witch say "OK, he's set" and grabbed the Stone off his arm while the other orderly cast Levicorpus on him and floated him gently into the recovery area.

Chapter 26: Security Conscious, Pt 2

"How did you avoid getting damaged during the War, Father?"

"Everyone gets damaged, Draco. You just continue on."

The healers floated Draco, still pretending to sleep, into the recovery room. Draco knew that patients who woke up prior to recovery got obliviated. He half expected to be obliviated in any case. Draco had walked the area often enough - probing for security weakness - and knew that most patients got up within about half an hour, inspected themselves, and left.

No slow recoveries at Peverell.

Draco spent twenty minutes trying to consider what he had learned and what it implied, but his mind kept going back to his arm ripping off, the pain, and then the flash of fire as Hermione arrived with her Phoenix, right before he passed out, the world blurred behind tears. Draco replayed is several times, shivering. He couldn't focus well. Without the distraction of something to do, something to learn, Draco relived his memories. After a few more near-deaths Draco heard Mad Eye Moody clomping around, and felt relieved to be back in the present. The footsteps stopped at his bed and Draco forced himself to keep his breathing regular, but not too regular. After a minute or two they clomped off. Draco counted out five minutes before 'waking up.'

His robes spoke volumes. The left arm was torn ragged at the shoulder, mud and blood caked together turning the normally black clothe an angry brown hue, streaked with red. Draco sat up and spent a few minutes poking his left arm. It felt ... like his arm. He'd had a small mole below his elbow, now missing, and the color seemed paler below the shoulder than above it, but it looked like his arm. His hand worked normally, and didn't hurt. Not now, at least.

"Hello Draco," said a young witch who'd walked up to the foot of his bed. Draco hadn't noticed, he'd been entranced with his new arm. The witch had long black hair under an outlandish oversize hat, wide brimmed and trimmed with gardenias. Her robe was stylish but ill-fitting, and she had a long grey shawl thrown on top of it. She looked to be a sixth year, maybe sixteen or so but Draco didn't recognize her. Draco stared at the hat again, and the witch started laughing. Not a girlish giggle, but a strong guffawing laugh.

Draco remembered where he was.

"Madam Longbottom?" The witch stifled her laughter long enough to make a formal curtsy that may have been in style during Abraxis Malfoy's youth.

"I happened to be in the stands watching this battle – they've become quite the event, you know, particularly the massive battles that involve all classes – and was sitting next to the Headmistresses when we heard the commotion. Neville had already been knocked out of the fight, he did quite well and I know from his letters that you and Potter have been tutoring him,"

"I think he would come along in any case," Draco interjected.

"Yes, well, I know he's also been talking to you about his parents. Like I told you last summer, it's rare that we both got someone back, and Neville hasn't had an easy time of it. Well, they wouldn't let anyone in to see you, some hogwash about security, but they couldn't very well deny me my cure, now could they? I must admit, I am rather delighted by it." She started to laugh, but then caught herself and giggled, which made her seem younger still. She twirled around, giggling. "You know, I've always felt like I was in my twenties, even yesterday, although I know how I looked. But the years creep up. I didn't remember how it feels, to be young!"

"Most of the people I've seen choose to be in their mid-twenties, or perhaps thirty," Draco agreed.

"Well, if you are going to get young, get young I say. I asked for a few years younger but the healers refused. Times were different from now, when I was this age, the first time. Now I plan on enjoying every moment of it, but I did want to make sure that they took good care of you, and to thank you for your talks with Neville, and those lovely thank you notes. That means a lot to an old woman," she said smiling.

"I'm doing well, thank you. All things considered." Draco clenched and unclenched his left hand, and suddenly realized he had no idea where his wand was. In the grand scheme of things, it didn't matter.

"Well, then, I suspect your friends are all waiting. I'll pop you back to Hogwarts, and won't we make quite the entrance?"

Despite her promise – or threat – Augusta had simply escorted Draco over to the Hogwart's infirmary then quickly took her leave before she could shock Neville or any other students. Madam Pomfrey fretted over Draco for a few minutes before releasing him. As he left Draco spotted Hestia Carrow lying asleep, bandages covering half of her face and most of her body. Asleep she looked just like any other girl, not the bloodthirsty witch who'd attacked him several times this year. Draco felt bad for her, for a brief moment. He'd been watching her for about a minute when Harry Potter walked into the infirmary.

Harry stopped beside Draco. "It's funny, in a way. You were so badly hurt they simply had to fix you up, but her wounds will heal normally." Draco shot him a glance and Harry said, "I figured you didn't want to talk about it – that's kind of normal – so I'm just making small talk. I grabbed one of your spare sets of robes from the room, if you want." Harry reached into his mokeskin pouch and said "Draco's Robes."

After Draco had changed they walked in silence for a few minutes, slowly descending from the infirmary back to the school. "So," Draco asked, "what happens now?"

"I have no idea. Detention for going into the forbidden forest, but beyond that? I don't know... " At that moment Draco and Harry turned a corner were face-to-face with a scowling Professor Lockhart.

"Beyond that," said Lockhart, "we will see. Come with me, Draco." He turned down a hallway and strode off without waiting for Draco.

"We'll talk later," Draco said under his breath, then caught up with the Professor. Lockhart quietly reached into his robes – the motion set off alarms in Draco's head, but the Professor pulled out Draco's wand and handed it to him.

"That was a stupid thing to do, Draco," said Lockhart, handing back Draco's wand, "A calculated risk, I suppose, but stupid. But since I had an inkling that something like that might happen no harm done. Still, you should know better than to rush into uncharted territory that you've been explicitly warned about."

"I wasn't thinking," said Draco, and realized it was the truth. He'd merely followed wherever the liquid luck had guided him.

"No, you weren't. Despite what Potter doubts there is a serious debate about expulsions, although Professor Slughorn is talking the Headmistress down. Look, I'm worried." Professor Lockhart stopped and turned to face Draco. "Not just about the attacks. I know you've gotten in over your head in … something."

Draco hoped he betrayed no sign of the shock he felt. "Oh, it's just school work and stress."

"I know for a fact it isn't that," said Lockhart icily, "but I'm not going to pry. You are flying bareback on a Dragon and holding on for dear life. You hide it well, but not from me." Professor Lockhart turned and strode off, still talking. "I know it's important, at least, you consider it important. When the time comes, I hope you remember my offer to help."

Draco's head was whirling. Professor Lockhart seemed ... eerily well informed. Draco considered further and realized that the Professor hadn't actually said anything concrete. He'd made guesses, spun a vague story that made Draco feel important. Lockhart probably had been informed by his other professors. Slughorn seemed friendly with him, and had probably played both sides as well as his own game. After a few more steps Draco's confidence returned, but he'd already started speaking.

"Thank you, Professor. It feels good to have an ally like you in this." Two months ago Draco would have considered the matter settled, but now he knew Lockhart wasn't a stereotypical Gryffindor who could be placated by appeals to glory and vanity. He suspected the Professor saw Draco's acceptance as a stall.

That didn't make stalling wrong, just less effective.

"On a more practical matter, would you like me to lock away your memories of the attack?" asked Professor Lockhart, "Most people find that kind of thing unpleasant, and they suffered a lot less than you did."

Draco considered this for several steps. He definitely needed his memories of the recovery. Professor Lockhart piped up.

"I can leave in the details, the knowledge, but you wouldn't remember how it felt, just that it happened. Like you read it in a book."

Draco felt sorely tempted. "My memories are who I am," he said flatly. Professor Lockhart shot him a questioning look, then shrugged.

"Where are we going, anyway?" Draco asked, to change the subject.

"Oh, we're here," said Lockhart, as they stopped before the Prefect's restroom outside the great hall. "You did die before sunset, I'm afraid. Rotten luck, that."

Monday Morning

"Professor Asimov," Draco said, "Thanks for the insights into the Muggle legal system ... systems, I guess." They were in Proffessor Asimov's study, Draco had a few questions about the Muggle legal and financial system. Harry's snide comment about wizarding lawyers being 'cute' had stuck in Draco's mind and he wanted another opinion. Professor Asimov had used the American legal system as a reference, but the facts were boggling. Contracts that were hundreds or thousands of pages long, lawyers working in teams, trials taking years. Madness.

Draco stifled a yawn. Even by his standards he hadn't slept well the night since his encounters with the Triffid, when he had nothing to do but remember.

"I do have one other question. My friend Harry Potter said that Science Fiction has solved - or at least addressed - problems that magicians have, if you can just translate the ideas correctly. But unlike him I haven't read it my whole life..."

"What do you need, Draco?" said Professor Asimov.

"Suppose we have a creature that's clever and useful, but dangerous. In the past we'd just avoid and kill them, but we have a spell that can force this creature to do what we want."

"Very convenient, that," said Professor Asimov. "But this sounds remarkably like slavery," his tone was dark.

"It could be construed that way, but the spell can be shaped to be minimally restrictive. We could make this creature do whatever we want, but we could just say 'Don't kill anyone.' But these are clever, malevolent creatures and they hunt for loopholes where they don't kill directly, but still harm and injure. Even if we wanted to, we couldn't setup on an exhaustive condition of rules. But the spell is draining. Permanently. And the more instructions given the more power the caster looses, so we want to give a minimal set of instructions that can cover all situations cleanly, and don't leave any loopholes, while still granting the creature full use of it's abilities. We don't want to cripple it, at least any more than necessary. I realize this is probably something far fetched …."

"I do believe I have just the thing," said Professor Asimov, pulling I, Robot from the shelf.

Chapter 27: Problem Solving

"Great plotting can be learned. Perhaps it can also be taught, but if so I do not know how. You must use your experience and intuition, those are the best teachers I know of. At best, I can only teach you how to avoid bad plots." - Lucius Malfoy

The Bayesian Conspiracy, now one larger, found time to squeeze in one last session before exams and winter break that didn't conflict with Draco's detention. Harry had used the delay to help Blaise get up to speed.

"I know that I said I'd try to discuss how you come up with solutions," Harry said just as Draco was walking in, still covered in dust. "For something practical in battle. It's actually surprisingly difficult for me to describe this. I don't want to sound like I'm bragging, but usually I just kind of … see the solution. Then I double check it. That's important, because sometimes you see the wrong solution. But it's hard to explain how I do it."

"How can you do something but not know how?" Blaise asked. His cat-like eyes had narrowed to slits, like he still expected an ambush, but he didn't seem shy. Zabini radiated a confidence Draco suspected he didn't feel. Draco cast a few minor spells to clean himself up.

"Gregory," said Harry, "You've seen Neville fly. You're the best flyer here. What's Neville doing wrong?" Neville let out an annoyed snort, but didn't contradict Harry. Daphne giggled a bit, until Hermione gave her a piercing look.

"His balance looks off," Gregory said after a pause. "I can't really explain."

"Gregory can't explain because true mastery means doing things automatically, without thinking. Some great artists can tell you why they picked a colour, but others would just say 'It looked right.' If Gregory stopped and thought about what he was doing when he was flying, he'd fall out of the sky. Like Draco said earlier this year, in a battle you don't feel like you are thinking. When I solve a problem, I solve it. Sometimes I have to think about how I'm thinking about it, but sometimes I don't. Anyway, I went back and solved some puzzles since last time and paid attention to how I thought, so I can explain it better. But I had to do it with maths puzzles," he finished sheepishly.

Everyone groaned. Harry continued. "Sorry, but it's easier to explain and experiment with. I won't do anything complicated but I had to pick something simpler. A battle just has too many variables for me to explain. This is more about technique. But look, here's a puzzle. You have to make an 8 digit number, using each digit 1-4 twice. So, 11223344, or 12341234. Something like that. But you want to make one so that there is exactly a single digit between the two '1's, and two digits between the '2's, and three between the '3's and four digits between the '4's. It's not really even a maths puzzle, see? Just a regular puzzle using digits. Go ahead and try and do it, and think about what you are doing."

Harry took out some paper and pencils. Hermione took one and started writing figures and scratching them out. The others reluctantly followed.

"Come on," said Harry. "Try it."

Hermione got the answer quickly, but three minutes later nobody else had solved it. Neville, sweat beading on his forehead, fidgeted as he started again. Draco had been scratching out numbers and writing new ones diligently, but showed no progress. Harry had been walking around and looking over shoulders. "OK, The rest of you are stuck. Let me give you a hint."

"Problem solving is about meeting constraints. In a battle your constraint is what spell or strategy to use. In this, it's the order of the digits. But what if you have a lot of constraints? Deal with the most restrictive constraint first. That usually narrows down the solution space – the number of different answers you have to consider – quickly. There are lots of 8 digit numbers. Even if you only consider those with the digits 1-4 twice. We don't want to try them all. We want to solve the hardest constraint first. The one that narrows down the possible answers fastest. Now try it again."

"It's like you are speaking another language," Draco complained as they started again.

"He does that a lot," said Neville. "I thought you'd be used to it."

This time Blaise and Daphne got it relatively quickly.

Harry still walked around the room, inspecting work and offering encouragement. "Maybe it's a maths thing, Draco. Don't let it block you because it's not your standard subject. In this case, the constraints are how you build the numbers. You can't change the fact that it has 8 digits, or the fact that it has four pairs of numbers. Those are just part of the problem. But how you arrange them, those are the constraints. What's the most restrictive constraint, Hermione?"

"The fours. They have to have the most digits between them."

Harry took out some paper. "Right, there are only a few ways that can work." He scratched them out.

4xxxx4xx

x4xxxx4x

xx4xxxx4

"The first and last are the same, just reversed. Symmetry is another way to cut down the number of solutions, but that's specific to math and not often in the real world. Anyway, now we've got two candidate solutions. The one with a four at the end, and then one with both fours one off the end. So now the most restrictive constraint is how to place the threes. If you put a three right next to the first four the other three won't fit three spaces away. So you can try two places."

4x3xx43x

4xx3x4x3

"And you can keep going if you have to, or you can just see the solution." He pushed the paper to Draco, who examined the two numbers above and wrote out.

41312432.

"Yes. Or the mirror image, due to symmetry. That's how I solved it. Combinatorics aren't my strong suit but If I've done my calculations right we started with 1,260 possible legal 8 digit numbers that have the digits 1-4 twice. And we quickly came down to two patterns that might work with the first constraint, and by adding the second constraint we got close enough to the solution we could just see it. The constraint let you not have to just keep trying random things, and let you get to the answer quickly."

"Anyway, for puzzles like that I have a bag of tricks. But the general technique is simple: Understand the problem. You have to know what you've got to work with and what you are trying to do. You'd be surprised how often just looking at what you can work with gives you a clue to the answer."

Draco interrupted. "But in the real world you can do practically anything. Not like a math puzzle."

"That's true," said Harry. "But especially in the real world clearly defining your goals may clarify the situation. Still, it's a good general technique. Anyway, after you understand the problem you look how to link what you know and what you are trying to do. Then you carry out your plan, you do the solution, examine your strategy. And you see if the answer works."

Daphne said, "That's still vague."

Harry nodded. "I know. If you didn't have a strategy you could just try every legal combination until you found it. That's a plan. It's not a great plan, but if you can't think of something better it works. Science doesn't care how you get the right answer, whether it's counting on your fingers or doing calculus. Efficiency comes from practice. Draco, what's nine times seven?"

Draco barely paused "Sixty-three."

"Right, you didn't have to think. But if I asked for larger numbers you'd take longer. If I asked a big enough number you'd need a pencil and paper and a lot of time. Just because a solution exists doesn't mean you can get to easily, even if you know what to do."

"Anyway, here are some techniques I use that don't specifically apply to math. But I'll use math examples. You could try to think of a similar problem, or a related problem. That may clear it up. In the real world history is often a good guide. Muggle Science Fiction books often address problems similar to things I've seen here, and Professor Asimov is an expert in that field. If you can explain the magic he may have seen a clever solution before. I found a cool dueling idea in one of his stories and I'm sure there are lots of great ideas I've missed. In fact, several of my battle ideas came from books. And no, I'm not going to tell you which ones."

"Sometimes I think he reads books just to annoy me," Hermione whispered to Daphne, while Harry was talking.

"If he likes you, he does anything to annoy you," she whispered back. Then, a bit louder, "Or if you like him...everything he does annoys you."

Draco tried not to show any emotion during that last speech. He didn't inspect Harry for any sign. Did Harry know that he'd been consulting with Professor Asimov? Draco worried about it for a few seconds, then realized it didn't matter. Harry's use of Unbreakable Vows weren't much of a secret, the entire staff knew about them, so Draco's investigations could be easily explained as just testing Peverell's security for weakness. Asimov's Three Laws didn't seem to apply directly to Unbreakable Vows, but Harry had probably used the approach of simple layered directives in an order of precedence, with more layers for Grindelwald than for trusted Aurors ... Draco realized his focus had wandered and turned his attention back to Harry, who was still talking.

"What else? You could solve a really simple version of the problem, then a slightly harder version, and look for a pattern. Proof by induction is messy, but powerful. Or you could try to break the problem into a bunch of smaller problems. Or try to solve a much harder version..."

"That doesn't make any sense at all," said Neville. "If I can't solve a simple problem how can I solve a harder one?"

"A harder problem forces you to be creative. For example, if I asked you to add up all the numbers from 1 to 10? You'd probably just add it up. But what if I asked you to add up the numbers from 1 to 100? Or a thousand? Or a million?" Harry paused. "Another trick is to assume there is a solution. Let me tell you a story. A Muggle teacher told his students - kids younger than us - to add up the numbers from 1 to 100 to keep them busy. And one kid gave the correct answer in a minute. Way too fast to do it the long way. Granted, that kid turned into a great mathematician, but he had a simple insight."

"I thought this wasn't about maths," said Hermione, to general approval.

"OK, let me think about something I can admit to," Harry said. "You think about the problem. Don't try to solve it, just try to think of what the insight is."

Harry though while they doodled with math. He glanced at the papers and said "Daphne's on the right track." Everyone looked over her paper. Daphne had written 1,2,3, and then skipped the middle and written 98,99,100. They all looked at her paper.

"They add to one hundred and one!" said Hermione. "One plus one hundred, two plus ninety nine, three plus ninety eight." She drew lines connecting them.

"Yes, that's the key insight. The rest of it is technical, and we don't have to worry about the rest. Anyway, the problem I had was that newspapers were writing trash about me. My first thought was: I need to get them to stop. But that's not the right question. This is just like the eight digit number. We need to understand the problem. So let's restate it clearly. The Prophet wrote rumours about me and I was worried that people believed them. You see what that does?"

"You don't have to get them to stop, you are just trying to keep people from believing them," said Daphne. "So you got them to publish that ridiculous story about Ginny Weasley."

"Well, not that exactly. But restating the problem clearly gave me the key insight: I had a new way to attack the problem. Anyway, after I had the idea I didn't actually implement it. I was here at school, in any case. But when Headmaster Dumbledore read the article he demanded to know how I'd done it. He thought I'd spent my entire inheritance and started working through all the things he would have to do to get that story published. When I told him I'd just spent forty Galleons he figured it out almost instantly."

"By making the problem harder," Draco said slowly, "you gave him another constraint, And that was enough."

"Right. My sunlight potion came from the constraint that I had fewer people in my army. Focusing on constraints lets you zoom in on the right option."

"And what if you still don't see it?" asked Blaise.

"Then you try something else. If you have time, maybe you try every solution. Look, rationality keeps you from making mistakes and it points the way. In science, we build experiments, but usually a scientist has a decade of experience to guide them. People spent years trying to figure out the structure of a chemical called Benzene. A chemist named Kekulé had a dream about it, his subconscious gave him the answer. He used the scientific technique and skills as a rationalist to build experiments to verify the answer. But how he got there was no better than a guess. Sometimes you just get lucky, although having a good bag of techniques helps you make your own luck. A real problem usually blends many skills. With experience, you'll recognize patterns and solutions."

Harry paused. "I know that I warn against seeing patterns where none exist. That's a real problem for people. But our minds are amazingly good at spotting patterns, so if you think you've found a pattern its usually a good idea to test it, even if it just popped into your head."

Author's Note - Polya's "How to Solve it" has an extensive list of heuristics and examples for pure math problems (not puzzles). I stumbled across the first puzzle (the eight digit number) presented here on kottke dot org , which often has delightful little puzzles like that (some of which I can solve, some of which I cannot). Solving that puzzle inspired this chapter.

Chapter 28: Holiday Shopping

"A man who tells lies may hide the truth, but he remembers it. A man who tells half-lies forgets the truth entirely." - Lucius Malfoy

December 22nd

"That's ... expensive," said Draco, then hastily appended "Not unreasonable, just quite expensive."

Griphook sat across from Draco, in the table set up inside the Malfoy vault. He stared at the small boy and screwed his face into his closest approximation of a pleasant smile. It came across as predatory.

"You want these things, and you want them quickly," said Griphook. His eyes were staring at the cane on the table, completely ignoring the quill recording their words into Draco's journal. When he'd first entered the vault Griphook had inspected the journal with some interest. It was clearly powerful, but not made by Goblins. Unlike that Sigil of House Malfoy. Draco, trained by history and knowledgeable about the Goblin revolutions, wasn't surprised by this.

"Perhaps instead of paying so much up front I could return the items earlier?" Draco offered.

Griphook shook his head, "To create these items quickly requires expensive components and crafting. My already generous terms are a token of esteem. Your House has never reneged on a deal and always returns our creations in a timely manner."

Draco nodded. All prior deals were studiously recorded in the family history. Griphook's price - though steep - fell well within the typical range.

"Very well. You may take payment from my vault as of next week." There were no handshakes or contracts. Goblins worked on their word, and were truthful to it, if you understood the nuances. Draco knew exactly how much House Malfoy had driven the subjugation of the Goblin race and he suspected Griphook knew it, too. Griphook didn't like him, but knew that powerful people - of all races - played both sides from time to time.

Personal feelings aside, Griphook would profit from this deal. They both knew it, that was all that mattered.

Griphook, now acting as an employee of Gringotts instead of a personal broker, gave a small bow as he stood up. "Will there be anything else?"

Draco made a gesture with his wand, and the quill dropped to the table, still. He picked up his journal and examined the record.

"I will be down here for a few hours conducting my inventory and writing correspondence," said Draco. Griphook nodded. Clients often wrote inside their vaults for security. "Please send someone down an hour before closing, I wish to discuss issues of security. No, I have no doubts about the security of my vault, I wish to see if I can acquire some similar security measures elsewhere."

Griphook's eyebrows raised. "That would also be expensive, if allowed."

"Well, in that case I will talk to you about it. Oh, and as for our … arrangement. Please do not discuss it with me at any point. Simply send a letter when the items are ready and I will arrange to have them delivered."

If Griphook thought this an odd request, he gave no indication of it and merely said "As you prefer." Draco nodded and Griphook showed himself out, closing the vault door securely behind him. Draco finished reading the transcript, then picked up the nearby quill and wrote out:

As before, conceal this information until the appropriate time.

He had barely finished writing when the words reformed.

I again counsel against this course of action. It is too dangerous.

Draco considered this, particularly the word 'again.' How many times had it been? He didn't know, of course. That was the entire point.

It is dangerous, but not too dangerous. "And there are too many Legilimens around," he mumbled to himself. Draco put down the quill and the book journal shut abruptly, a chiding gesture Draco had learned to recognize. A minor petulant tantrum. Draco pulled out his wand, and scanned the vault, as if some master thief could breach Gringott's security and follow him here but be foolish enough to stand in plain sight. Draco chuckled as he steadied his wand, laughed at his own instinct, the useless caution. He took several deep breaths and lowered his head to the table then pointed the wand at his forehead, concentrating and then casting his spell. He felt his panic rise, wondered if it happened every time then cast his spell:

Obliviate

Draco put aside the formal letters, and glanced at his watch. He'd fallen asleep during his inventory of magical items, so it had taken far longer than he'd expected. He barely had half an hour left to finish his letters, and he'd been putting off this last one. He quickly filled out the cover letter, instructing his solicitor for the conditions of delivery. That was the easy part. After he finished that Draco pulled out a formal scroll, elegant, and dipped his quill into the ink.

To my friend Harry Potter,

I write you this letter on Winter Break inside Malfoy Vault, safe from any scrying. Here it will stay, hopefully never to be read, because I have left my solicitor instructions to deliver this letter if I die betraying you. I hope it does not come to that.

Draco sighed, dipped his quill into the ink, then continued writing.

December 23rd

Mundungus Fletcher shifted nervously in his booth, both hands cupped around his firewhiskey as though it would keep him warm. And safe.

"Don't fink I don't know Armageddon Robes when I see 'em. Good quality, too. Iff'n you want to sell it at some point..."

The figure hidden inside the Armageddon Robes sat, unmoving. There was a face inside it, but Mundungus couldn't see it. He saw nothing but the outline of the cloak. Most wizards say Armageddon Robes were forged by the same dark magic that allowed Dementors into the world, for the cloaks hid their wearers not by illusion but by fear. You could easily find out who it was just by pulling back the hood.

If you could overcome your fear.

It wasn't even that gripping of a fear. Nothing nearly as powerful as a Dementor. Just a cold chill. Most people could gather their resolve and pull back the hood. Few, except Aurors, would risk it in any case because wearing an Armageddon Robe advertised that you were up to no good and didn't want to be recognized. Armageddon Robers weren't a concealment, they were a threat. The real fear the robes inspired were that if you pulled them back, you'd face the wrath of a powerful wizard who may kill you on the spot. The figure in the robes slowly raised his right hand, wand pointing at Mundungus.

"Look, mate. No need fer all that. I ain't gassed nobody yet and you don't want me to know who you 'ar then I don't want to know. Mum didn't raise no fools."

The wand slowly lowered and the other hand slid a sheet of paper across. Mundungus picked it up, read it and blanched.

"I don' know who told you what, but I don't associate with those types. I just buy and sell. Them? They've no respect for the working stiffs like me. They'd as like to kill me iff'n I actually found them. Murderers. Wanted murderers, not just those who you hear rumours about. I just buy and sell." He gulped down his firewhiskey.

The figure slowly pushed across a sealed letter then placed a bag of Galleons on top of it. Mundungus stared at the bag greedily. "I'm not promising nuffin," he said as he picked them up and they disappeared into his sleeves.

Draco Malfoy, hidden by the Armageddon Robes he'd found during his inventory, smiled to himself and got up from the table.

Dec 26th, Boxing Day

Harry, Vince and Gregory all unwrapped their boxes and opened them. The remnants of their late lunch were still spread across the table.

"I got us all an identical set of dress robes," Draco said. He'd considered getting Harry some Noble robes as well, but that would leave Vincent and Gregory out. They all pulled on the robes. "These all have the extra enchantments that House Malfoy gets for their robes, to prevent staining, ripping or shredding. Basically, if these robes show any sign of damage, you probably won't be in any condition to care."

Vincent and Gregory saw Draco's small shudder.

"And they'll adjust in size as we do, of course. Very important for wizards our age."

Hermione opened the letter that had been left on her windowsill. The elegant writing, the red wax seal on the envelope, and the overall style marked the writer. Nobody else put much effort into their letters. Hermione looked around but didn't see Draco's owl on any of the nearby rooftops. She leaned out her window and whistled, and an answering hoot came. Hermione craned her head up and saw Tanaxu standing on the chimney. Owls apparently don't like sharing a room with a Phoenix. She pulled herself back into her bedroom and turned to Xare, "When did this letter arrive?"

"CAW!" Xare said, mixing the screech with the audio equivalent of a shrug. Phoenixes were wonderful, Hermione thought as she broke the seal, but didn't have any sense of time. Probably a side-effect of being immortal. Will I be the same, after a few hundred or thousand years, if I live that long? She looked inside the envelope. There was a card, and a small parchment poking out behind it. She pulled the card out and read it.

From Draco, son of Lucius, son also of Narcissa, scion and heir of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy:

To Hermione, daughter of Leo, daughter also of Roberta, Lady of the Noble House of Granger

I would be honoured if you would join me for a viewing of The Tragedy of Light at the Globe Theater on the evening of Tuesday, December 29th.

Draco

Hermione read the card several times. She thrilled at the thought of being invited on a formal date (instead of having to trick a boy into it). On the third reading she noticed that Draco had omitted most of his title, shortening it so that it matched Hermione's title in length. He'd also dropped most of the flourishes he used in formal correspondence. She wasn't sure, but she thought that Draco had used the bare minimum for politeness, trying to keep the tone informal and pleasant instead of stuffily aristocratic.

She put the card aside and read the parchment.

Hermione,

Please excuse the form of the invitation. There is a production of The Tragedy of Light I had been hoping to attend, and I though you would like to join me. I've enjoyed Muggle Movie Night and thought you might enjoy seeing a wizard's play, although I'll warn you not many Griffyndors like it. Some mild chaperoning will be involved, but it should be discrete. Please let me know by owl at your earliest convenience.

Draco

PS I'm embarrassed to admit that it would be easiest to travel by Phoenix, but I can make other arrangements if you prefer.

December 27th

Draco rounded the corner, jacket tightly wrapped about him against the winter cold. It was a touch under ten degrees, despite the sun shining brightly this afternoon, for once.

"Hey guys," he said. There was a small crowd of teenagers, mostly fifteen and sixteen years old, smoking in the alley off Picadilly Circus. They wore jackets, some leather but some just plain old winter coats. Underneath, Draco knew they'd be wearing T-shirts for various bands, but it was too cold.

"Tom!" said a Roger, a husky guy with black hair in small ringlets whose stubble of several days didn't make him look nearly as rough as he imagined. He tossed his cigarette down on the ground and came over and grabbed Draco in a bear hug. "They let you out of St. Brutus after all!" he said, laughing.

"Hey Roger," Draco said, "I brought my cousin. Hope that's ok?" Draco motioned back to the corner, and Robert nodded at them all. The groups joviality dropped slightly, which Draco had expected. After all, they had several years and half a foot on him, but Jugson was even older. "This is Robert."

Robert nodded curtly and said "Hi," while Draco went around the group. "Roger, Samantha but everyone calls her Sam, Dave, Mike." They all nodded, but Sam, the short red-head, seemed taken with Robert, which caused some hidden scowls.

"You a Felton, too, Robert?" Sam asked, blushing slightly.

Jugson wasn't comfortable around Muggles, and his discomfort showed, but he'd agreed to play along with Draco and his brief time spent in Professor Asimov's class had shown him the 'Draco Malfoy' was a name that would stand out in a crowd. Still, he'd quickly grasped the implication …. Draco had invented his Muggle persona before taking Muggle Studies. This had been part of Draco's test: to see if Robert Jugson would actually treat Muggles as equal and bite his tongue. Robert was of age, having turned seventeen last month, if he wanted to stun and obliviate this lot of Muggles there was nothing Draco could do about it.

"I'm a Jugson. My mum and Tom's mum are sisters." Robert shook hands and tried bumming a cigarette from Mike, a wiry lad who actually looked dangerous and had a spiderweb tattoo creeping up his neck. Mike just looked at Robert's outstretched fingers and raised eyebrow, then sighed and shook out a cigarette.

"You at St. Brutus' as well," asked Mike. Robert just laughed once and took a drag on the cigarette – a lighter had appeared in Sam's hands the instant he put it in his mouth."

"I'm thinking of not going back," Robert said. He didn't cough, just held the smoke and then released it. Draco wondered if that were a spell or if Robert actually smoked. Most of the older wizards had at least tried it. There was some small talk and Draco shucked off his jacket.

The small talk died as the group of Muggle watched Draco's shirt. It was a plain white tee shirt, with an outline of an Aztec sun, but as the watched the fabric changed colours to sparkling yellow and a rainbow background. There were gasps.

"How does it do that?" Roger asked.

"What am I, some egghead?" answered Draco lightly, then chuckled. "It's some chemical, reacts to sunlight. One of my relatives, he gave me this at Christmas." Draco's shirt brightened in the sunlight, and Draco tried not act cold. It actually wasn't that bad, but the wind was picking up. The glamour was a relatively minor one, the type that would be applied to robes, but the novel approach was mixing it with a sunlight trigger. Draco had gotten the idea from Harry's sunlight-capturing potion. Grindelwald – a master of Transfiguration – had been intrigued by the idea of robes that changed color in sunlight and had helped work out the formula.

"Wow!" said Mike, looking more interested than dangerous. "Where'd he buy it at?"

"They're pretty expensive," Draco said, "and I don't think you can buy them in London yet. Apparently the company mainly sells them on nice beach islands. My uncle knows a guy thinking of importing them. They'd be pretty pricey, maybe sixty pounds each."

"Oh, I'd definitely buy one," said Sam, "or nick one at least."

"Oh yeah," said Roger. "Definitely cool."

Draco stood in front of his fireplace, warming up.

"You see?" he said to Jugson. "They'd be popular."

"Yes, but it's violating the magical secrecy act," Robert said, but Draco could tell from his tone it wasn't a serious objection, just stating a fact.

"Well, we'll produce them in the Caribbean. They have the same laws, but are a bit more …. open to interpretation. Besides, these will sell much better in a beach climate. How often could you really wear sunlight powered shirts in this weather? But I don't think there's a serious risk. Those muggle's just think it's chemistry – which really is just another version of potions and Transfiguration – and for all we know Muggles may be able to do this. We'll do it magically at first, hire a few local wizards. Then we'll figure out a Muggle way later to increase production. We'll make these shirts and sell them for an obscene amount of money to tourists."

"Muggle money, but yeah. So what do you need me for?"

"I'm going to stay in school, but I want to start this right away. You go out to the Caribbean handle day-to-day operations and also be the muggle expert in the company."

"What, me?" said Robert.

"We're going to have to hire a lot of Muggle bankers and lawyers to make sure that nobody catches on. I'll assist with that as best I can, I can do that while at school. And someone has to be the public face of the company. Between the two of you, you are most up to date on Muggles."

"Two," said Robert blankly as the footsteps started coming down the stairs.

"Yes. Our third partner. Robert Jugson, I'd like you to meet Gellert Grindelwald."

Author's Note – The quote from Lucius is a modification of the famous quote from Lawrence of Arabia (the movie).

Del Sol was publicly founded in 1994, according to the Muggle Wikipedia.

Chapter 29: The Date, Pt 1

Hermione stood on the doorstep of Malfoy Manor, checking herself in her mirror once she'd knocked on the door. Her hair hadn't gotten messed up, of course. Her hair never messed up. Draco answered. Hermione saw his surprise. As promised, Draco had taught her anti-glamour spells earlier in the year and she'd been using them for the last two months to dampen her aura of purity, but she'd removed them for her date. Her mum had spent hours fussing Hermione's hair into french braid, and she wore a red and gold evening gown. Her simple chain necklace reflected the setting sun and the flames hovering around Xare, who sat on her shoulder. She smiled.

"Hello, Draco." She'd gotten over her nervousness during her preparations. He looks nervous, though.

"Good evening, Hermione. You look lovely," Draco stuttered, glancing down at his own robes while standing aside. "Please come in." Draco closed the door behind her. "I suddenly feel under-dressed." Hermione looked at Draco's robes: elegant, formal robes, black tinged with green. Draco looked pale, was he nervous? Well, that didn't bother Hermione, she'd felt nervous for the last few hours. It was normal, on dates.

When they entered the living room Draco spoke up, "Hermione, do you mind terribly if I changed? It will just take a few minutes." Hermione frowned, confused. Draco looked fine. Xare flew from her shoulder and took one lap around the living room before landing in the fireplace. She sat on the log, soaking up the fire and sighing contentedly.

"Did I do something wrong, Draco?" Hermione asked.

"No, no! I thought you'd be going more … incognito, but that's stupid. You could hardly do that with a Phoenix..."

"She's called Xare," Hermione said.

"...with Xare. I don't know what I was thinking. Five minutes?"

Hermione smiled and Draco disappeared up the stairs. She walked over besides the fireplace and the dusty portraits gawked, introduced themselves, and complained about her dress. A recent picture, judging from the frame, studied her carefully, then said "So, you are the girl giving my grandson such fits."

Hermione looked at the portrait. The man in it carried more weight, especially in the face, than Draco or Lucius did and his hair looked strawberry blond rather than platinum, but the family resemblance was unmistakeable. She started to say something, but the portrait harrumphed and turned his back. Hermione heard footsteps coming down the stairs. That was fast, but she looked up and saw a tall man descending the staircase. At first she thought it was Lucius Malfoy, before she remembered. The man could have passed as Draco's cousin or uncle, perhaps fifteen years older. As his face came into view he smiled without warmth.

"Abraxis, where are your manners?" he asked the portrait. "Miss Granger." The words were barely out of his mouth when Xare cut him of with a scream of rage and accusation, head poking out of the fireplace. Hermione recognized him at last.

"Grindelwald," she said curtly. "I didn't realize you were friends with the Malfoys." Gellert Grindelwald strolled smoothly into the room and sat down in the master chair, in front of the fire. He ignored Xare's hissing wail, then seemed to notice the Phoenix when it stopped.

"Tell me, where is Fawkes? What has become of him, now that Albus is gone?" Grindelwald steepled his fingers in front of his face, contemplating the Phoenix hissing at him. He added softly, almost to himself. "It is still strange, to have outlived him."

"I watch him," Hermione said evenly, "He and Xare keep each other company, mostly." Grindelwald seemed satisfied by the answer, and nodded.

"That is well. A Phoenix lacking his master pines and mourns. And they are picky about the company they keep. As you can see." Xare clucked disapprovingly. "If you have need, I can watch Fawkes for a time."

Hermione blinked. "Fawkes doesn't mind you?" She found it difficult to keep the edge out of her voice, but if Gellert heard any danger in her he ignored it.

"Fawkes has known me for decades, of course. You have your opinion of me, which your Phoenix shares. Fawkes shares Albus's opinion of me. I think that of the two, Fawkes resents me more." He paused, "But it is a mild grudge, only. I would enjoy his company, it has been almost three seasons."

Hermione considered this, rage growing. Gellert Grindelwald caused untold suffering, misery and death, yet apparently he expected Dumbledore's Phoenix to accept his presence calmly. Harry had told her that Dumbledore visited Grindelwald in prison. He probably traveled by Phoenix. Dumbledore hadn't abandonend his friend after their fight, they'd kept a relationship. Hermione couldn't imagine it. She could see Dumbledore being cold and cordial, he'd always been friendly enough to students but the man sitting before him had been Dumbledore's peer and apparently the former Headmaster had been unable to let that relationship go, even after his eye's had opened to the evil. He'd captured Grindelwald, defeated him, and imprisoned him. But never abandoned him.

How could this be, from the most famous Gryffindor of the age?

During the height of his power the man in front of her ordered the murder of innocent millions to power his dark rituals. The Muggle world blamed Hitler, but he'd been Imperiused. Now Hermione stood watching him soak up a nice fire in a comfortable living room. His magical power had been drained and she knew Unbreakable Vows kept Grindelwald from doing anything harm. But ... he sat free and Hermione resolved that she would not feel sorry for this man, not forgive him and not ignore his crimes.

Like Fawkes did.

Hermione said nothing, but her face slowly grew redder and the fireplace grew slightly brighter. She didn't know if her anger made Xare burn hotter, if the link between them drove her Phoenixes anger or if her Phoenix simply recognized evil when she saw it.

Grindelwald, noticing the fire burning higher, said "You have a kind soul, so it angers you, yes? That your friend released me?" Hermione heard Draco rushing down the stairs and Grindelwald - still staring at the fire and the Phoenix - said "Enjoy your evening, Miss Granger."

She saw Draco's finely polished shoes, black leather gleaming in the crackling light. Draco's robes were still the same colour, black tinged with green, but the fabric had a mildly metallic tint the caught the light and reflected a silvery glow. His neck clasp showed not a snake, but a silvery flower Hermione couldn't quite place. Even his hat seemed taller.

The effect was impressive, she thought.

Draco proffered a delicate purple flower to Hermione. He quickly took out his wand and cast Collorchidea and magically pinned the flower to her dress, just below her right shoulder. Grindelwald glanced over at the young pair of them and chuckled once before falling back into his reverie.

"Shall we?" asked Draco, grabbing his cane leaning against the chair that held one of the greatest monsters the world had known.

The Globe Theater (the real one, not the Muggle reconstruction in London) had been old in Shakespeare's youth. Even then the Globe had toured the country for centuries, magically appearing on the outskirts of the next town preceded by a small advance squad of Wizards hawking tickets for "One night only!" shows. Families would gather in an abandoned field to watch the entire structure Apparate and settle into the ground, usually only an inch or two but up to a foot if there had been recent rain. As the Wizarding world was small, the Globe was an intimate venue, able to only hold five hundred patrons. Still, for all but the largest cities it rarely sold out. But The Tragedy of Light was a big seller, revived every Christmas season for a full week in London, and a few days on the continent.

Since the theater had sat still on the outskirts of town and not recently moved, there was only a small crowd of wizards gathered on the cobblestones outside the theater. The cobblestones traveled with the structure. They were a recent addition - not quite a century old - by a former manager who thought modern wizards would fork over extra knuts for 'authenticity' in the theater-going experience. Setting up the stones on nearby roads had turned a tidy profit and also kept out stray Muggles. The few couples standing outside the round, white theater were enjoying the mild snowfall, magic protecting them from the real cold, when suddenly a glow brightened like a murderous dawn and a young woman's voice could be heard.

"...believe he'd be at your house!" she finished. The red colour disappeared, leaving only a young couple, a Phoenix riding the shoulder of a girl who looked younger than the voice they'd just heard. Most of the assembled wizards and witches stared at the now-famous Hermione Granger, she who defeated Voldemort, before coughing and returning to their conversations while sneaking glances at the young couple in their peripheral vision. Several men chuckled at the boy: who would date such a dangerous girl? Hermione gave them all a glance, then ignored them. This still bothered her, all the attention she got in public. At least nobody had come up to her, thanked her, asked for her autograph, or otherwise pestered her. One girl, probably eight, with a small ponytail sticking out from underneath her hat, said her name and started forward, but her parents caught her shoulder and told her not to be rude, that The-Girl-Who-Revived didn't want to be bothered.

She didn't, but Hermione wouldn't have minded being bothered by a star-struck girl.

"Wow," said Draco, stumbling. Hermione removed her arm from his shoulder. Draco ran his hands up and down his sides. "That was … odd. Do you get used to the sensation?" Draco ignored the stares of those around them, had spoken in a normal conversational tone.

"Well?" Hermione asked, still whispering like they were in a library. She felt guilty, questioning Draco on their date. Then she realized that Draco should be feeling guilty, not her. He was the one harboring a murderer. That Harry freed. By the time Draco answered she felt conflicted again. This was not how she'd envisioned the night going at all. She'd expected it to be awkward, or maybe for Draco to be charming, or even too glib to cover his nervousness. She hadn't expected a fight, especially one that Draco didn't seem interested in.

"Where should he go?" Draco asked calmly. A young wizard in purple robes coughed quietly, and the crowd started to move away, across the cobblestones, towards the theater. "We are going to be late."

"We'll discuss this later," Hermione said sweetly and caught an elderly witching nod and smile approvingly. Hermione's anger hadn't dissolved, but several voices in her head continued arguing about it. Draco didn't deserve all of her anger, and it wasn't like she had to save the world right this moment. It could wait until after her date, when she had time to think. And argue with Harry.

"Certainly," said Draco, as he extended an elbow. Hermione intertwined her arm with his as they went to the will-call window.

"Why this play, Draco?" she asked quietly after the usher had escorted them to their seats. She'd left Xare in the lobby. The manager provided a sturdy iron pole for her to rest on, assuring Hermione that "many a familiar had spent a pleasant evening here" and "yours would be the 8th different Phoenix to have been in our lounge," before asking if he could take a picture. He pointed to a wall that showed a number of wizards, standing besides the same pole illuminated by the dripping fire of a Phoenix. In the last picture a middle-aged Dumbledore looked at her over half-moon glasses and nodded approvingly, while Fawkes seemed to smile besides him.

Hermione could still hear the whispers, see the pointed fingers. They'd been seated after most of the audience, but even without Xare people had recognized her, those who spotted her pointing her out to those that hadn't. It didn't help that she and Draco were the youngest couple by a decade, not counting children attending with their parents, and her dress stood out among the muted Slytherin colours the crowd favored. Red and Gold were not in fashion. Draco had warned her, but she'd taken it as a challenge. Hermione could hardly complain about the attention. She felt giddy at having the power to provoke Wizarding's self-described nobility with her fashion choices. That was a power Hermione Granger never expected. She giggled slightly and added "I mean, I read the synopsis and it doesn't seem like a date play."

"Well," said Draco, who sounded like he'd suppressed a cough then cleared his throat, "I like this play and haven't seen it in several years. And its nothing like a movie theater, where you have ten screens to choose from. This is the play they are showing."

Draco - who had spent the entire last fifteen minutes ignoring every stare and cough from those around him - had been subtly inspecting the audience. Hermione would have felt annoyed but Draco had been a perfect gentleman, paying attention to her throughout the evening. And, after all, people watching was Draco's unique skill. Harry rarely noticed the number of people around, much less their characteristics. Harry only focused on people he considered important. Draco probably did that, too. He just hid it much better. And it was an interesting crowd, she admitted. Draco was still talking.

"And I enjoyed Muggle movie night. Harry said part of the reason was that they only showed the really popular movies, that there were lots of terrible ones, so I thought you might enjoy this. It sells out fairly consistently. So, even though I know it's not," he paused, looking for a phrase, "your favorite genre, I figured you might like the quality. If not the content."

Hermione gasped as she caught a glimpse of a familiar face peeking over a railing from the box seat above them and off to the right. Gilderoy Lockhart glanced down at the audience, five o'clock shadow on his cheeks making him appear even more rakish and dangerous than normal. Hermione smiled at him and started to wave, then his face disappeared behind the railing.

"Draco! Professor Lockhart is here. He's in a box seat, up there." She pointed just in time to see Professor Lockhart's face re-appear, but now he was saying something and pointing at Hermione, who looked over at the witch next sitting next to Gilderoy, smooth blond hair pouring out from underneath her stern hat surrounding an aging but still beautiful face, formal noble robes strikingly similar to Draco's. Hermione gasped and turned to Draco, who seemed to be doing his best to try to pull himself into his seat and hide in the growing darkness as the lights started to lower.

Hermione's mind froze for a second. Then she leaned over to Draco. "We're here to spy on her date?" she said as the curtain started rising.

"I did say there'd be mild chaperoning duties," Draco mumbled defensively before the crowd started shush-ing them.

Chapter 30: The Date, Pt 2

Hermione spent the entire first scene mentally reviewing the exact phrasing of Draco's letter, which she'd read well more than six times even before showing it to parents. Mum had squealed with delight at the invitation, while Dad just scowled. What did she know? Draco had originally dressed formally, but not flashy. He'd changed after seeing her dress. He'd brought them in at the last minute, to a place where he'd know - of course he'd know - that Xare would be watched and kept away. Draco had commented about traveling incognito.

He'd planned to spy on his mother all along. Was this even a date?

(Out in the lobby, the manager stared at the Phoenix. Turning to the ushers, he said "Is it getting brighter? You see it, right?")

By the second scene Hermione had calmed down. Draco clearly liked her, but maybe he was more nervous than he looked – Draco almost never looked nervous – and he'd clearly be hearing all about this when he got home from Narcissa. She glanced over and saw that Draco was entranced by the play. It clearly had an affect on him, he hadn't been lying about wanting to see it.

And he hadn't really lied to her. He hadn't come out and said all of his motivations, but that didn't indicate what his primary motivation was. This could be a date, in Draco's mind, but also a date with some spying. That made it exotic. Maybe too exotic for a first date said the teenage-girl Hermione. Or maybe he couldn't admit it was a date to himself, and needed an excuse, said her inner librarian. The librarian reminded her of all the books that stated boys matured slower.

By the third scene, which revealed Lights's father as the Auror leading the investigation into the murders committed by his own son, Hermione had built up a convincing internal story where Draco had invited her as a romantic gesture, but had been too worried about rejection to couch it as a date. He hadn't dared hope that Hermione would accept it, hadn't felt worthy of Hermione. A year ago she never would have thought that, but she heard the whispers.

When the curtain fell for intermission Hermione realized she was being silly. Once they were in the lobby, age appropriate drinks in hand, she just asked Draco "Is this a date, exactly?"

"Yes! Of course," he said, a little too forcefully, and Hermione realized Draco might not have been entranced by the play, but had probably spent a good portion of his time worried about his situation and having an internal argument about her. After all, he already knew the plot on stage. She liked that thought.

"It's just," he said, slowly, glancing around to make sure that nobody seemed too near, "a bit of a working date. No, that didn't come out right. I wasn't sure how much of a date you considered it, or if it was just … hanging out. I've spent time with Muggle teenagers, you know. Things are done differently. I thought you'd be treating it like they did. Casually."

"And once you saw how I was dressed," she said and Draco nodded, taking a sip of his drink. Narcissa came out into the Lobby and Draco started to subtly move them into a crowd, not realizing that Xare's eyes glanced in Hermione's direction ever few seconds, providing anyone the ability to track them even if they were fully hidden. Still, Hermione went with him. "I don't see why you'd worry about your mother's dating life. I mean, I can see why it would upset you..."

"I didn't expect her to be with Lockhart!" Draco said, somewhat crestfallen.

"Does that make it better, who she's with? It doesn't matter, it's her business, not yours," but Hermione's voice didn't sound scolding. Draco's offense – a boy judging who a girl dated – offended her. In theory. Since it was his mother ... well, if one of her parent's died Hermione knew she'd be overly protective of the other. She felt Draco deserved a pass. And she was intensely curious. "Who did you expect?"

Draco glanced around again and whispered "Professor Slughorn" and at that moment Hermione forgave Draco's overly protective interest in his mother's dating life. She took Draco's hand firmly in hers, walked them out of the crowd to go and say her sweet and pleasant hello to Narcissa Malfoy and Gilderoy Lockhart.

Draco was, of course, too polite to refuse. Even if he blanched slightly.

Hermione beamed her most intense smile, "Good evening, Professor. Madam Malfoy."

"Mother. Professor." Draco said formally.

Gilderoy Lockhart may have spent the last few years in a jungle, but he'd spent prior decades living on his looks and his charm and he smiled radiantly, as though running into Draco and Hermione had been all he had hoped for this evening. "Generals," he said, "I must admit I'm surprised to see the two of you here, and looking wonderful."

Narcissa smiled sweetly, "Yes, everyone looks lovely, but I will not participate in this charade." Her smiled faded into a scowl. "But that is a lovely orchid, Hermione. Did Draco pick it out for you? Of course he did, where would you get that. And did he tell you what it symbolizes?"

Hermione knew that subcultures - especially wealthy aristocratic ones - assigned symbolic meanings for colours, flowers, flags, practically anything. Usually it was a game played by the upper class. Judging from Professor's Lockhart reaction, he didn't know what it meant either. But Draco clearly did.

"It doesn't symbolize anything Hermione," Draco said quickly, "it's just all I could find on short notice."

Narcissa leaned down to Hermione and looked into her eyes. Hermione held her breath and raised Occlumency barriers. She might not be able to keep Narcissa Malfoy out, but she'd know. Narcissa just smiled a crocodile's smile and said "I'm not surprised you don't know, even though it's an obvious symbol. Orchids are difficult to breed."

Narcissa stalked away. A few seconds later Professor Lockhart shrugged helplessly and started to turn away. Before he took even a single step Hermione started giggling. By the time he'd caught up to Narcissa, Hermione was laughing loudly.

Hermione, once she controlled herself, offered Draco her arm. "Your mom really doesn't understand me, does she? I didn't grow up in a Jane Austen book."

The ice cream shop, unlike the theatre, had customers of all ages. Teenagers, some nicely dressed and others in the latest shabby fashions, chomped on cones and slurped milkshakes alongside families with small children and older couples. Xare sat on the windowsill, looking in sadly – a young girl cried and screamed after Xare melted her banana split's ice cream and Hermione had scurried back outside before returning.

"Well, I knew the murderer was the protagonist – Muggle literature has anti-heroes, too - although I never understood the appeal," said Hermione, sipping her milkshake, "I just didn't expect the crowd to be cheering him."

"It's just a play, Hermione, it's not like they were..."

"I'm teasing you," said Hermione. "I don't judge people based on escapism. It didn't surprise me that they cheered Lawliet, but that the cheered at all during the play. Muggles might cheer during movies but in a play with actors I hadn't expected it. Although I suppose if you consider it a melodrama and give the victim a mustache to twirl...and in any case, it was an interesting play."

"Yes, similar to a Sherlock Holmes story" Draco said, taking a bite of his chocolate sundae.

"Yes, wait, you've read that?"

Draco paused and held up his hand, silent for a moment, then tapped his forehead. "Brain freeze. A few. It has charm, and I'm told they turned it into plays and movies. In some ways it reminds me of Harry."

"The lack of manners," said Hermione.

"The maniacal focus," Draco added.

"The fact that his companion is ever so much nicer," said Hermione, with a smile.

"Wait, which one of us is Watson in your imagination?" he asked.

"That depends on how we define Watson. If he's a competent soldier cleaning up after Holmes's social failings, that would be me. If he's comedic relief and serving as an audience surrogate, then I'm afraid the role falls to you."

Draco said "It would be the height of folly and rudeness for me to disagree. You are clearly the noble Watson to Harry's Holmes." He raised his spoon in salute, then continued eating. "In all seriousness, the trait that gets me is Holmes ability to quickly winnow down possibilities. If I see a man with ink on his robe, a shabby hat, and a brand new pocketwatch, I merely think he's written a letter and bought a watch more recently than a hat. But Holmes manages to come up with some much more esoteric theory."

"He's just a fictional character, like Lawliet, or Auror L."

"Yes, but you've seen Harry do it. I've seen it. I make some minor statement and then he's deduced the most amazing things." Draco looked down sadly at his empty bowl, then set down his spoon. "The methods he taught us, they can correct mistakes and guide us, but I don't know if he can teach us to make these stunning insights. That may just be his innate genius."

"Harry lent me a book about one of his scientific heroes that said something like, 'There are two types of genius. The first type you look at and say, if only I study harder, practice harder, and spend the long years required for mastery, then I could do that. And the second type, you don't even know where to begin.' Harry does seem like the second type."

"Yes, I mean, I figured out how he did a lot of things from last year. And those things impressed me quite a bit, Neville's Rememberal."

Hermione put down her shake. "You know how Harry did that?" She had to hear this.

"The last piece of the puzzle was when you saved me from bullies. I know you weren't there when you caught me, and I realized … invisibility cloak. I'd already figured out his spinster wicket was a time turner. With the two of those you can do a lot. You aren't wearing yours tonight, I noticed. But it's almost midnight … I can't imagine your parents let you stay out this late."

Hermione blushed. "I put it in my purse. It didn't go well with the dress. And coming back from the dead makes your parents recalibrate curfew hours. But yes, I'm going to be home before ten," she added, feeling a small frisson of delight in keeping her father in the dark.

"That's really good, Draco, I never figured it out."

"Well," he said, "you didn't grow up around magic. Anyway, those tricks are impressive, but not because of what he did. Because I wonder how he managed to get those devices so quickly. But I've seen him, in conversations with Father, quickly infer subtle little details like Holmes would do and smoke out plans. I know he's improvising and not cheating. Or if he is cheating, it's still impressive. Harry's …. flying on a broom while juggling, dodging bludgers, blindfolded. And making it look easy. I don't see how the techniques are going to get us to that level."

"I don't think they will," added Hermione, finishing her milkshake with a small slurp.

"No, but wouldn't it be nice?"